<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="index" xml:lang="en">
    <info>
        <title>Dealing with Hypomanias</title>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
                    <surname>Fish</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <email>shlomif@shlomifish.org</email>
                        <uri type="homepage" xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/">Shlomi Fish’s Homepage</uri>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <copyright>
             <year>2008</year>
            <holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
        </copyright>
      <legalnotice xml:id="main_legal_notice">
            <para>
<!--Creative Commons License-->
This work is licensed under the <link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 License</link> (or at your option a greater version of it).
		<!--/Creative Commons License--><!-- <rdf:RDF xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
		<Work rdf:about="">
			<license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/" />
	<dc:title>The Case for File Swapping</dc:title>
	<dc:date>2005</dc:date>
	<dc:description>An essay that explains why Internet File Swapping (using Peer-to-Peer networks, etc.) is not only moral and ethical, but also should be legal, and cannot be banned. Discusses other issues.</dc:description>
	<dc:creator><Agent><dc:title>Shlomi Fish</dc:title></Agent></dc:creator>
	<dc:rights><Agent><dc:title>Shlomi Fish</dc:title></Agent></dc:rights>
	<dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text" />
		</Work>
		<License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction"/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution"/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice"/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution"/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks"/></License></rdf:RDF> -->                
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
        <abstract>
            <para>
                I’ll discuss some of my experience as a person who had
                been through clinical depressions, clinical anxieties, 
                hypomanias (= “below-manias”) and even a few manias,
                (and as a result probably has Mania-Depressia or 
                “Bipolar disorder”) and how I deal with the various periods of
                “hypomania”, which I still have occasionally: periods of
                strong excitement and feelings of self-grandiosity.
            </para> 
        </abstract>

        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>5389</revnumber>
                <date>30 May 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Forked the template from a previous work and working on 
                    it.
                </revremark>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </info>

<section xml:id="introduction">
    <info>
        <title>Introduction</title>
    </info>

    <!-- TODO : Rephrase -->

    <para>
        Have you ever entered a mood where you thought you were a bad person,
        that all your past achievements did not count and were bad? Did you
        find it difficult to perform many tasks that you could do normally,
        found it hard to concentrate, was flooded with bad thoughts, and had
        problems going to sleep? If so, you may have been
        <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Major_depressive_disorder">clinically
            depressed</link>, or clinically anxious. In addition, people who
        suffer from <link
            xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bipolar_disorder">Mania-Depressia
        also known as “Bipolar disorder”</link>
        (like me) also tend to get into opposite states called 
        <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypomania">hypomanias</link>
        or Manias. While “hypomania” contains the word “mania”, they
        are actually below-mania, and the person is still in control to some
        extent, and, with some awareness, may realise they are in a bad mental
        condition.
    </para>

    <para>
        Clinical depressions are not everyday “I am depressed.”
        or “being down” depressions, but rather a feeling that one is bad, and 
        being consumed with guilt, with a tendency of being less communicative
        and less able to perform one’s responsibilities.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        I probably have <link
            xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bipolar_disorder">Mania-Depressia</link>
        (or “Bipolar disorder”) because I had a
        single “Great Mania” and a few shorter manias, because I have frequent
        Hypomanias, and because I had some periods of clinical depressions
        and clinical anxieties. So I’m writing about this from
        experience.
    </para>

    <para>
        One should note that one swallow does not make a spring. Some people
        had a few clinical depressions at certain points, and have since
        led happy, normal lives. An example for this are
        <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Postpartum_depression">Postpartum
            depressions</link> which happen to some women after giving birth
        to a child, but there are other cases.
    </para>

</section>

<section xml:id="symptoms">
    <info>
        <title>Symptoms</title>
    </info>
    <section xml:id="symptoms-of-depression">
        <info>
            <title>Symptoms of Depression</title>
        </info>
        <para>
            Quoting from <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_depression">the 
                Wikipedia</link>, the symptoms of depression are:
        </para>

        <blockquote>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Persistent sad, anxious or “empty” mood 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Loss of appetite and/or weight loss or conversely overeating and weight gain 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Insomnia, early morning awakening, or oversleeping 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Restlessness or irritability
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Psychomotor agitation or psychomotor retardation
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Feelings of worthlessness, inappropriate guilt, helplessness
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Feelings of hopelessness, pessimism 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Difficulty thinking, concentrating, remembering or making decisions
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Thoughts of [[death]] or suicide or attempts at suicide
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Loss of interest or pleasure in hobbies and activities that were once enjoyed
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Withdrawal from social situations, family and friends
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Decreased energy, fatigue, feeling “slowed down” or sluggish
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Persistent physical symptoms that do not respond to treatment, such as headaches, digestive problems, and chronic pain
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Decrease/Feeling in motor-speed (time seems to slow down)
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </blockquote>

        <para>
            These are mostly the external symptoms. While the exact thoughts
            vary from person to person, here is how I felt:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I felt I was bad and evil. That I was a bad person, having
                    a bad influence on the world, and that “God hated me”.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I felt this was my true state, and that my happy, capable, 
                    intelligent and active state was due to “a pact with the
                    devil” or something along these lines.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I found that the thoughts haunted me, that I couldn’t 
                    really sleep, and was afraid of thinking.
                </para>
            </listitem>


            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I believed the entire world was bad and kept perceiving 
                    everything as bad.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I had trouble communicating with others, and was afraid to
                    tell them how I felt.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I found it harder to do things that I normally find easy to
                    do. For example, I spent hours on end solving a single math
                    problem. I kept convincing myself that it should be easy
                    which made me feel much worse.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I was consumed and overwhelmed with guilt. I felt guilty for
                    many things that I perceived as wrong.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="symptoms-of-hypomanias">
        <info>
            <title>Symptoms of Hypomanias</title>
        </info>
        <para>
            In regard to hypomanias, Wikipedia <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypomania">gives the following symptoms</link>:
        </para>

        <blockquote>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Pressured speech; rapid talking
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Inflated self-esteem or grandiosity;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Decreased need for sleep;
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Flight of ideas or the subjective experience that
                        thoughts are racing; 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Easy distractibility and attention-deficit
                        (superficially similar to attention deficit
                        hyperactivity disorder);
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Increase in psychomotor agitation; and
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Steep involvement in pleasurable activities that may
                        have a high potential for negative psycho-social or
                        physical consequences.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </blockquote>
        <para>
            It’s a pretty good description of me when I’m hypomanic.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
<section xml:id="depressed-people-i-know">
        <info>
            <title>People I Know who Suffer from Depressions</title>
        </info>
    <para>
        Many people (mostly computer developers) I’ve talked with admitted to 
        have been clinically depressed:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                One of my best friends has admitted that she used to have many 
                depressions. Whenever I met her in real life, or talked with 
                her (on the phone, on instant messaging, etc) she seemed very 
                cheerful, fun loving, intelligent, and rational.
            </para>

            <para>
                She claimed that when she is depressed she tends not to
                communicate a lot and also cannot achieve too much at work,
                which she said only makes her feel worse. I can relate to both
                of these, as I recall that that was the case for me on both
                accounts when I was depressed.
            </para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

            <para>
                I talked with a programmer, well into his 50’s (and still
                active) who admitted to having got into depressions several
                times in the past. He again seemed normal (if somewhat
                eccentric to me).
            </para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

            <para>
                One time on irc.oftc.net someone joined and started speaking 
                in
                <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leet">l33t-speak</link>, 
                asking how he can become a “haxor”. People thought he
                was a troll, but I ended up PMing him and it turned out he was
                depressed. I spent the afternoon trying to help him.
                Eventually, during his (and mine) evening, he claimed that 
                he was feeling better and parted. (It is known that often 
                depressed individuals feel better in the evening and at night.)
            </para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

            <para>
                A fellow programmer I talked with admitted to having got into 
                depressions in the past, and that she tried to function 
                despite that.
            </para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

            <para>
                A fellow Perl monger I talked with said that he sometimes 
                exhibited some of the symptoms of hypomania. He seemed 
                very hyperactive to me, so I wasn’t really surprised, but it 
                may also be plain excitement and not a medical condition.
            </para>

        </listitem>
        
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        <link xlink:href="http://www.mental-health-today.com/bp/famous_people.htm">A 
            list of some famous people who had Mania-Depressia can be
            found at 
            http://www.mental-health-today.com/bp/famous_people.htm</link>.
        Bipolar disorder is relatively uncommon and many more people are 
        only “Unipolar” and only have depressions and anxieties. Depressions 
        and anxieties are considered the “common cold” of mental illnesses, 
        and are exhibited in a large percentage of the populace.
    </para>

    <para>        
Someone told me that he read a study that said that roughly 50% of the
authors in the English language today have Mania-Depressia. I haven’t been
able to find it online and would appreciate any references.
    </para>

</section>
<section xml:id="dealing-with-clinical-depressions">
        <info>
            <title>Dealing with Clinical Depressions</title>
        </info>

    <para>
There is a lot of mis-information and dis-information about depressions in
the public. When I was depressed and hypomanic as a teenager I didn’t know
how to call these “conditions”, or how to effectively deal with them. If,
after reading the description on the Wikipedia, you feel that you have been
depressed in the past, read on.
</para>

<para>
The best advice I can give on dealing with clinical depressions (and possibly
also as a preventative measure or just to understand what people think) is
to buy <link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/Feeling-Good-Therapy-Revised-Updated/dp/0380810336">the 
    excellent book <emphasis>Feeling Good</emphasis></link>.
</para>

<para>
It is a self-help guide for <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_behavioral_therapy">cognitive-behavioural therapy</link>, that was
originally written in English and was recommended to me by my therapist.
Just reading it helped me understand the source of my hypomanias, and I found
the exercises recommended there to be helpful as well.
</para>

<para>
One important omission from an earlier draft of this essay was that I did not
summarise the <emphasis>Feeling Good </emphasis>book here, while I should have tried to in order
to give a taste of the book here (because I know I always hate “go read X at
some place because I don’t have the nerve to explain it to you.”). So I am going
to summarise <emphasis>Feeling Good</emphasis> here.
</para>

<para>
Note that if you are depressed, (and if you’re feeling suicidal even more so),
you need to consult a cognitive-behavioural therapist for a session, as
soon as possible. I am not a mental health professional and am not qualified 
to give professional therapy, and this essay is not a substitute for it.
</para>

<section xml:id="summary_of_feeling_good">
        <info>
            <title>Summary of Feeling Good</title>
        </info>

<para>
Burns starts by giving a way to diagnose your mood and determine if you are
depressed or not. I didn’t focus on it because I normally can eventually tell
when I’m hypomanic (or could when I was depressed). He then goes on to explain
that your feelings are affected by the thoughts that go through your head,
and that by challenging your irrational thoughts, you can improve your
mood. 
</para>

<para>
He then lists 10 cognitive errors that people make which may make people
depressed. Among these errors are:
</para>

<orderedlist>

<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Should statements</emphasis> - you try to motivate
yourself by saying things like “I should be more careful”, or 
“I should not have talked to him like that.” or 
“I ought to be more considerate”. What these
should statements do is actually demotivate, and make you feel down.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Disqualifying the positive</emphasis> - an example for
this is that when you receive a compliment, you say something like 
“they didn’t mean it.”, or “it doesn’t count.”, or “he doesn’t know the real me.”
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Mental filter</emphasis> - here you focus on one negative
detail (a “fly in the ointment”), while ignoring the rest of the picture.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">All or nothing thinking</emphasis> - you want everything
to be perfect. For example, you’ll accept no grade below 90% or so (even if
it’s a passing grade), or so.
</para>
</listitem>

</orderedlist>

<para>
Dr. Burns then gives a simple recipe to gain self-esteem: one writes down an
automatic thought that disturbs him (or her), and then the feelings that
he feels (with percentages). Afterwards, he should write which cognitive
errors he has made followed by a rational response to the feelings, and after
that the new feelings. 
</para>

<para>
Burns then discusses several useful techniques for anger management, and for
dealing with criticism.
</para>

<orderedlist>

    <listitem>
        <para>
            <emphasis role="bold">Approval Addiction.</emphasis> - you
            want to be approved by other people and fear disapproval for
            them.
        </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
    <para>
<emphasis role="bold">Productivity Addiction</emphasis> - you care about your
work, how productive you are, how much you achieve, etc. (Much more common
among men.)
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Love addiction</emphasis> - you want to be loved
        a lot. More common among women.
        </para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
    <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Perfectionism</emphasis> - you want to be perfect
        in everything you do.
        </para>
</listitem>

</orderedlist>

<para>
    The book <emphasis>Feeling Good</emphasis> focuses on depressions and not on hypomanias.
    As the psychologist I’ve been seeing noted, a hypomanic person should
    perform cognitive exercises on his grandiose thoughts that are
    running in his or her head when they are hypomanic. 
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="few-facts-to-realise">
        <info>
            <title>A Few Facts that Should Be Realised</title>
        </info>
    <section xml:id="mentally-ill-is-not-eccentric">
        <info>
            <title>Mentally Ill is not Eccentric</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            When people say that someone is “crazy”, “insane”, 
            “out of his mind” etc. they usually mean that he or she is eccentric or 
            behaving irrationally, not that they are mentally unsound. I know 
            and have heard about many people who are eccentric or very 
            eccentric and yet are perfectly sane, and lead perfectly happy 
            lives.
        </para>

        <para>
            There’s a difference between conformism or “being normal” and 
            mental health. 
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="some-bad-moods-are-ok">
        <info>
            <title>Some Bad Moods are OK</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            Some bad moods are normal and are a healthy part of living and
            would not lead to depression. For example, if someone you cared
            about died, it’s perfectly OK to feel sad. Rational fear is also
            normal and healthy. My point is that one cannot or should not be
            fully happy all the time. Sometimes it is also OK to be a little
            “down”.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="drugs">
        <info>
            <title>Drugs are not the most Effective 
                Way to Treat Depressions</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            Depressions have a cause. According to
            <link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/Feeling-Good-Therapy-Revised-Updated/dp/0380810336"><emphasis>Feeling 
                Good</emphasis></link>, it is
            usually a thought or a group of thoughts that is bothering someone,
            and caused someone to feel depressed. These thoughts are normally
            triggered by something difficult or intimidating, but it is not 
            necessary that something like that will make one depressed - one
            can often cope with it without being depressed. 
        </para>

        <para>
            In any case, Psychoactive medication attempts to deal with the 
            symptom that is a chemical problem in the functioning of the
            brain. However, it does not deal with the actual cause that is
            the mental problem.
        </para>

        <para>
            In order to deal with the cause instead of the symptom, you still 
            need Cognitive-Behavioural Therapy and to read
            <link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/Feeling-Good-Therapy-Revised-Updated/dp/0380810336"><emphasis>Feeling
                Good</emphasis></link>.
        </para>

        <para>
            That put aside I should note that I am taking medication,
            prescribed to me by a Psychiatrist. It does not prevent me from
            becoming hypomanic, but it may make the hypomanias less severe
            (I’m not entirely sure about that).
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="depressions-are-not-desirable">
        <info>
            <title>Clinical Depressions are neither Desirable nor 
                Inevitable and Can be Overcome</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            Some unipolar individuals I talked with, who seemed to have been
            somewhat
            <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Relativism">relativists</link>
            argued that being clinically depressed or hypomanic, was perfectly
            OK and that it was just a natural state, and that it was just
            “society” or the “environment” that didn’t like it. All of this
            is non-sense, because I clearly recall feeling miserable when
            being depressed or clinically anxious and after gaining some
            awareness, was able to tell that my hypomanias were not desirable
            either. It’s not a belief that people have conditioned me to 
            believe - it’s one that I developed myself. 
        </para>

        <para>
            I can rant much more about Post-modernist relativism, that
            some of proponents of it claimed people with disabilities such as
            deafness or blindness, who can be treated to some extent,
            should not be, because deafness or blindness were just different
            ways of perception, and not actual disabilities. But the point
            is that while you may experience depression or hypomania, it is
            neither desirable nor inevitable, and that you can overcome it.
        </para>

        <para>
            During my normal state, I had, like other people, experienced many
            positive and negative emotions: joy, anger, frustration, fear,
            boredom, a feeling of disorientation, love, exhilaration,
            attraction, disappointment, hatred, remorse, sadness, etc. This is
            perfectly normal and these emotions have a purpose, and I was
            otherwise happy when I experienced them. But they are more natural
            than depression, which is much longer, and is mentally and
            physically unhealthy. <footnote
                xml:id="emotions-are-not-our-master" label="Emotions">

                <para>
                    One should note that emotions and feelings should not be 
                    our master. Often they can be misleading and irrational.
                    For example, if my friend failed a test that I did well
                    on, I may feel smugness or superiority, but this feeling
                    is probably not rational or will make me happy in the
                    long run. 
                </para>
                <para>
                    Feelings should not be
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.mkprojects.com/fa_emotions.html">repressed</link>, 
                    in the sense that we deny that we feel this way. But we
                    sometimes can acknowledge that we feel like it, and behave
                    in a different way. A person is allowed to 
                    <emphasis role="bold">feel anything</emphasis>
                    including a desire for mayhem and murder. Only behaving
                    based on these emotions in either words or deeds may be
                    bad.
                </para>
                <para>
                    While we can enjoy a rational happy emotion, and
                    try to behave on a rational bad emotion, we sometimes
                    need to take actions that will make us feel bad. 
                    For example, validly criticising a friend in private,
                    or admitting you’ve done something wrong.
                </para>
            </footnote>
        </para>

        <para>
            That put aside, you shouldn’t feel bad about being depressed when
            you do. It’s perfectly OK to feel it, and being consumed with
            guilt about being depressed will only make it worse. You should
            accept the fact that you’re feeling bad or being under-productive
            and realise that this feeling will pass.
        </para>

    </section>

</section>

<section xml:id="computer-devs-and-anxieties">
        <info>
            <title>Computer Developers and Anxieties</title>
        </info>

    <para>
Computer Developers are probably more likely to become anxious than people
of most other professions. With the irrational working hours (see 
<link xlink:href="http://www.igda.org/articles/erobinson_crunch.php">Evan Robinson’s
“Crunch Mode” article</link> ), tight schedules,
tactless or unfriendly co-workers, bad software management practises,
bad code and lack of craftsmanship, irrational management that
demands the impossible, too few vacations, and other factors - it is
probable that they will feel trapped, resentful, unhappy, and as a likely
result, anxious or depressed.
    </para>

    <para>
        As a software manager, it is your job to keep your software
        developers happy.  This means doing the exact opposite of the
        above-mentioned points. Refer to <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/computers/software-management/perfect-workplace/">an essay 
            which I started writing titled “The Perfect IT Workplace”</link>
        for more information on how to do that.
    </para>

    <para>
        As opposed to common belief, treating your software developers with
        superb conditions, will make them much more productive, not less. So
        make sure you read my article above (and the links pointed to from it),
        and integrate its recommendations into your workplace.
    </para>

    <para>
        Naturally, this is more difficult to do if you’re a regular programmer
        who isn’t in management. However, you can still refer your boss to
        what I wrote if you feel he’s reasonable enough. If not, it may be a 
        good idea to quit or even to relocate to somewhere with more job 
        opportunities. Some jobs are worse than being unemployed.
    </para>

    <para>
        Obviously, from reading <emphasis>Feeling Good</emphasis>, it is evident that
        depressions, anxieties and hypomanias are not limited to programmers,
        and actually predate programming by a long time. Many retired people
        also find themselves the sudden victims of these mental ailments.
        However, I feel that due to the bad state-of-the-art of software 
        management in the world today, it is especially common there, than in 
        most other jobs.
    </para>

</section>

<section xml:id="advice-from-my-experience">
        <info>
            <title>Some Advice from My Experience</title>
        </info>

    <para>
        Like I said earlier, I still haven’t fully recovered from my
        psycho-medical condition and am still getting into hypomanias.
        However, here is some advice I can give from my experience:
    </para>


    <section xml:id="do-cognitive-exercises">
        <info>
            <title>Do Cognitive Exercises</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            This is probably the single best advice one can give. Read 
            <link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/Feeling-Good-Therapy-Revised-Updated/dp/0380810336"><emphasis>Feeling
                Good</emphasis></link> and do the exercises given there. They have
            proved very helpful to me.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="physical-exercise">
        <info>
            <title>Physical Exercise</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            Exercising and especially doing aerobic exercise (jogging,
            biking, dancing, swimming, etc.) is very useful 
            for preventing or lessening anxieties.
        </para>

        <para>
            My therapist recommended that in order to sleep well
            during days in which I’m hypomanic, I should exercise during
            the late afternoon and evening.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="diet">
        <info>
            <title>Diet</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            I don’t consume alcoholic beverages, don’t consume caffeine,
            have never smoked, and have never consumed any of the currently
            illegal drugs, such as marijuana. While it does not prevent
            hypomanias, I find that it makes me less moody, more energetic
            throughout the day, and allows me to sleep better at nights. (I had
            also tried to refrain from eating sugary foods, but I couldn’t
            persist in it very well.)
        </para>

        <para>
            I also take multi-vitamin pills, and some people take many more
            individual minerals than I do, and while I’m not sure it helps
            with anxieties, it’s very good for health and longevity.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="relaxation">
        <info>
            <title>Relaxation</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            I also find that relaxing or doing things you love to do is
            helpful for keeping a good self-esteem. It’s especially important
            during anxieties.  Listening to music, sitting, thinking and doing
            nothing, taking a time for leisure at the computer, are useful for
            relief from troubling thought.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="perform-your-priorities">
        <info>
            <title>Try to Perform Your Priorities</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            That put aside, I should note that working on what you have to
            do, will make you feel better, and is better than just 
            procrastinating, and will also displace a large burden from
            your heart, that keeps you nervous.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="write-down-your-thoughts">
        <info>
            <title>Write Down Your Thoughts</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            When I’m hypomanic, I’m getting lots of good ideas: for stories,
            for essays, random useful thoughts, etc. While a lot of them had
            seemed silly in the past, some of them proved to be very useful and
            rational.<footnote xml:id="mania-stories" label="ManiaStories">
                <para>
                    I even ended up finding many really crazy delusions I had
                    during my “great mania” as useful inspiration for the 
                    following stories:
                </para>

                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/humour/humanity/">Humanity</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/humour/Star-Trek/We-the-Living-Dead/">Star Trek: We, the Living Dead</link>
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>
                    And, naturally, my hypomanias have been catalysts for most 
                    of <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/humour/">my
                        other stories.</link>
                </para>
        </footnote></para>

        <para>
            It would be a good idea to write the ideas down, or even work on
            realising the essays or articles, because it makes one less excited
            and calmer. I would be a good idea not to publicise them in public
            until you’re well out of a hypomania, because they may prove to be
            immature or silly in the short-run.
        </para>

        <para>
            I personally may have sometimes been rejected from jobs because
            of the many things I’ve written and placed online, and which are
            easily accessible using a Google Search.  I don’t mind that because
            I feel that expressing and publicising my creativity is more
            important than making myself a better job candidate to some
            “attractive” jobs. And some employers seemed to be very impressed
            by some of what I wrote online, or at least did not mind that, and
            these seem like jobs I prefer.
        </para>

        <para>
            It is naturally a good idea to receive as much commentary as
            possible about one’s articles or writings in private before
            publicising them for all the Internet to see.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="be-honest">
        <info>
            <title>Be Honest</title>
        </info>

        <para>
It is a good idea to admit that you’re “stressed” - anxious, etc. My therapist
said that the word “hypomania” is intimidating because it contains the word
“mania”, so one should rephrase it in case the other party is not that
knowledgeable about Psychology. Sometimes you may find some of your
friends or family (but not all) good candidates for consulting with your 
thoughts or feelings. I once spent an hour or so on an IRC (= Internet
Relay Chat) conversation listening to a 19-years-old whom I knew, talking 
about her problems. I also consulted people on IRC or IM about my own issues 
and often found creative solutions or empathy.
</para>

<para>
This is doubly correct for talking with my family members.
</para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="maintain-low-profile">

        <info>
            <title>Maintain a Low Online Profile</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            During a hypomania, it is a good idea to maintain a low online
            profile.  Namely, don’t post too much to mailing lists or other
            forums, don’t chat on the IRC too much (and try to focus on
            technical problems or your psychological situation), and in general
            try to maintain a low-profile.
        </para>

        <para>
            However, I feel that real-life meetings with people and talking
            to them face to face is actually very good for one’s well-being
            during a hypomania.
        </para>

        <para>
            So if you can get a friend or a few to meet with you in a café ,
            or go to a club meeting, it will be a good idea.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="philosophy">
        <info>
            <title>Philosophy</title>
        </info>
        
        <para>
            It is my impression that often the philosophies and idea systems
            that we are generally exposed to (e.g: most western religions), 
            are very harmful for one’s self-esteem and prevent one from
            properly getting out of depressions.
        </para>

        <para>
            An example for this is what the New Testament says in the Sermon
            of the Mount: <quote>But I say unto you, that whosoever looketh
                on a woman to lust after her, hath committed adultery with her
                already in his heart.</quote>. As I explained before, people
            have no control over their immediate emotions and should
            not feel guilty for possessing ones that they may consider
            bad. While most Christians I’ve talked to about that, did not
            think that what that means is that lust was as morally condemnable
            as rape is, this has been traditionally interpreted as such,
            and is how I interpret the meaning of the this verse.
            And naturally, this is just a small example.
        </para>

        <para>
            Therefore, I suggest you instead study and adopt a more benevolent
            psychological philosophy, which will help give you enough tools
            to live your life more happily and to deal with clinical
            conditions as they arise. My personal favourite is
            <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/philosophy/guide-to-neo-tech/">Neo-Tech</link>,
            which is an extension and re-organisation of 
            <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Objectivism_(Ayn_Rand)">Ayn 
                Rand’s Objectivism</link>, with many vital corrections.
            However, I do not rule out the premise that different personal
            philosophies will be better for different people.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="reliefs">
        <info>
            <title>Get some Relief for Your Condition</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            It’s possible that if you’re a university student or a
            grunt employee, then you can get some relief for your
            psycho-medical condition. So try to see if it is possible, and if
            so - do that.
        </para>

    </section>

</section>

<section xml:id="curse-and-blessing">
        <info>
            <title>The Curse and the Blessing</title>
        </info>

    <para>
        In <link xlink:href="http://memory-alpha.org/en/wiki/Tapestry">the
            <emphasis>Star Trek: The Next Generation episode</emphasis> “Tapestry”</link>,
        Captain Picard dies and then is 
        given a choice to revert an incident in his past that has caused him
        an injure which would have eventually caused his death. After he does 
        that, he discovers that he is no longer Captain and that he have 
        lacked the self-motivation that was needed in order to become the
        hero that he  used to be. As a result, he says that “I would rather 
        die as the man I was, than live the life I just saw.”
    </para>

    <para>
        Or consider <link 
            xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helen_Keller">Helen
            Keller</link>, who was born deaf-blind. If she had been born 
        normal, she would most likely have led a happy life. On the other
        hand, without her disability, she might not had become the superwoman 
        that she did, because there would have been nothing to motivate her.
    </para>

    <para>
        Would I rather lead a normal life? Yes, I would. But, on the other
        hand, I recognise that getting into hypomanias is part of who I am,
        and probably the price I have to pay for being so creative. While I 
        would like to reduce its effect, I thank God (so to speak) for 
        allowing me to be able to write so many articles and essays, compose 
        so many stories, and being a capable programmer.
    </para>

    <para>
        So I guess the curse and the blessing are part of what makes me who
        I am. 
    </para>

    <para>
        Nevertheless, as I noted earlier, it is probably possible to combat
        the harmful effects of Bipolarity or Unipolarity as much as possible
        using Cognitive-Behavioural Therapy and other means, and I intend
        to work on that. It is my hope that you are now wiser on how to 
        better deal with such harmful psychological moods, in case
        you have been suffering from them.
    </para>

    <para>
        Feel good!
    </para>

</section>

<section xml:id="doc_info">

    <info>
        <title>Document Information</title>
    </info>

    <section xml:id="about_the_author">
        <info>
            <title>About the Author</title>
        </info>
<para>
    My name is Shlomi Fish and I am an Israeli software developer, essayist
    and writer. I am a user, developer and advocate of
    free and open-source software (FOSS), free and open content (
    <link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/">Creative Commons</link>,
    the various <link xlink:href="http://www.wikimedia.org/">Wikimedia
    projects</link>, etc.) and freedom, rationality and openness in general.
</para>
<para>
    I have been suffering from depressions and hypomanias since I was 14, 
    and they proved to affect my professional life, academic life
    and Internet life, for better or for worse.
</para>
<para>
    You can learn more about me by visiting 
    <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/">my homepage</link>.
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="copyright">

    <info>
        <title>Copyright</title>
    </info>

<!-- Creative Commons License -->
<para>
This work is licensed under the 
<link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative
    Commons Attribution 3.0 Unported License</link> or,
at your option, any later version. Year of copyright is 2009.
</para>
<!-- /Creative Commons License -->

</section>

<section xml:id="thanks">

    <info>
        <title>Thanks</title>
    </info>

<para>
    Thanks should go to
    <link xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/user/cefarix">Moutaz 
        (cefarix)</link>, Drew Dexter and
    <link xlink:href="http://jacintarichardson.cgpublisher.com/">Jacinta
    Richardson</link>
    for going over early drafts of this essay and giving some comments
    and corrections. I’d also like to thank my therapist (whom I won’t mention
    by name) for his constant good advice and analysis and for recommending 
    that I read the book <emphasis>Feeling Good</emphasis>.
</para>
</section>

</section>

</article>    <!-- End of the article -->
