<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="index" xml:lang="en">
    <info>
        <title>The Perfect IT Workplace</title>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
                    <surname>Fish</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <email>shlomif@shlomifish.org</email>
                        <uri type="homepage" xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/">Shlomi Fish’s Homepage</uri>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <copyright>
            <year>2008</year>
            <holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
        </copyright>
        <legalnotice xml:id="main_legal_notice">
            <para>
                <!--Creative Commons License-->
                This work is licensed under the <link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 License</link> (or at your option any greater version of it).
            </para>
        </legalnotice>

        <revhistory>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>1841</revnumber>
                <date>30 April 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Forked the template from a previous work and began working
                    on it.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>5762</revnumber>
                <date>02 July 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    The first revision as publicised on Reddit.com, by
                    pkrumins.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>5977</revnumber>
                <date>26 July 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Forked the revision 1 version and started working
                    on revision 2. Fixed many typos. Added the motivation
                    for automated tests. Added more text to the design
                    section.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>6036</revnumber>
                <date>02 August 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Started adding the essential tools section with
                    more information, instead of just the knowledge
                    in the Ether.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>6048</revnumber>
                <date>04 August 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Added the “Building, Configuration and Packaging”
                    section.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>6201</revnumber>
                <date>14 November 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Added the Maturity, Mind-share and Distance from the
                    Mainstream sub-section to “Choosing a Technology”.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>2319 (svn)</revnumber>
                <date>27 February 2009</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Added missing id attributes to footnotes, so they won’t
                    be randomly generated.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

        </revhistory>
    </info>

    <section xml:id="introduction">
        <info>
            <title>Introduction</title>
        </info>
        <para>
            I originally wrote <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/computers/software-management/end-of-it-slavery/">“The
                End of Info-Tech Slavery”</link> a few years ago, shortly
            after I was fired from a job I liked and for which I worked
            about three months. Some people who commented on the
            article found it of good value. However many people who commented
            on it have voiced some criticism.
        </para>

        <para>
            One of the comments I received said that I kept giving bad
            examples for conditions I disliked from previous workplaces,
            instead of positive elements I would have liked to see or
            have seen. As much as I like liquidating negatives, I agree
            that I should also mention some good things that a workplace
            needs to adopt.
        </para>

        <para>
            Another commenter told me in private, that he felt
            that the “End of IT Slavery” and other essays of mine reflected the
            fact that I had a “primadonna attitude” instead of a more
            positive “team-player” attitude. While this may be deduced
            from my “The End of IT Slavery”, I found that as a tech worker,
            I tended to just get my job done as I told, try to be as
            productive as I can be, try to adjust to the surroundings,
            and even be a little <link
                xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/items/2004/12/06.html">of
                what Israelis call “rosh qatan” (= “small-head”)</link>
        </para>

        <para>
            I can see why people would think so after reading the
            “End of IT Slavery”. However, my intention in the article was to
            guide
            employers (and employees) as to how to best treat their employees,
            and give them good conditions, so they’ll be happier and more
            productive. Going over the original article, I can see that I
            indeed had a very ranting tone, and had given bad examples
            for what not to do, exclusively.
        </para>

        <para>
            So this time, I’m going to try again and hopefully be more
            successful. This article aims to cover the elements that
            <link xlink:href="http://www.paulgraham.com/gh.html">great
                programmers</link> would love to see in a perfect workplace.
            By implementing as many of them as possible, or at least giving
            them a serious thought, you can make such potential employees want
            to work for you, love to work for you, want to stay, and be
            happy as long as they are working for you. Furthermore, you will
            know better than to irrationally fire perfectly good employees.
        </para>

        <para>
            I’m not trying to be original in this article, because an essayist
            (or any kind of artist) does not get credit for coming up with
            perfectly original concepts or ideas (as
            <link linkend="great-poets-steal">I note later</link> in a
            different context). What I’m trying to do is summarise everything
            I’ve learned, judged and concluded, so far, based on the many
            sources I’ve read. I may be just a dwarf standing on the shoulders
            of giant, but hopefully I’ll still be able to see farther than
            most.
        </para>

        <para>
            There is a lot of material on good software
            management out there, and not everybody took the time to read
            all the important one. This material can sometimes
            be contradictory, and sometimes false. Nevertheless, I decided to
            integrate it here into what I’ve perceived and concluded to
            be the best choices.
        </para>

        <section xml:id="intro-sources">
            <info>
                <title>Sources from Which the Advice was Taken</title>
            </info>

            <para>
                This is a non-exhaustive list of major sources of
                influence.
            </para>

            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.catb.org/esr/">Eric S.
                            Raymond’s Homepage</link> and especially
                        his <link xlink:href="http://www.catb.org/esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/">the
                            <emphasis>Cathedral and the Bazzar</emphasis> series</link> and his
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/hacker-howto.html">“How
                            to become a Hacker”</link> document.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        The
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/">wonderful
                            <emphasis>Joel on Software</emphasis>
                            site</link> by Joel Spolsky.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.paulgraham.com/">Paul
                            Graham’s essays</link> - tend to be interesting,
                        but often suffering from some problems.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/">Extreme
                            Programming</link> - seems a bit too
                        rigorous, but still has many good ideas.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Damian Conway’s excellent book
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/perlbp/">Perl
                            Best Practices</link>
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the-elements">
        <info>
            <title>The Elements of a Perfect Workplace</title>
        </info>
        <section xml:id="hire-the-best-developers">
            <info>
                <title>Hire the Best Developers</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/"><emphasis>Joel
                    on Software</emphasis></link> and others have written about
                the importance of having very good developers. See for
                example his
                <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/GuerrillaInterviewing3.html">“Guerilla
                    Guide to Interviewing”</link>.
                Bad programmers will create code that’s buggy, insecure,
                hard-to-maintain, etc. The so-called “Medium-level techs”
                will probably not, but will be heavily under-productive in
                comparison to star programmers. (And according to
                <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brooks'_law">Brooks’
                    Law</link>, you can’t effectively replace one good
                programmer with many worse ones.)
            </para>
            <para>
                As I noted <link xlink:href="http://discuss.joelonsoftware.com/default.asp?joel.3.197867.7">there
                    are many aspects that qualify someone as a
                    good programmer</link>. However, it does not change
                the fact that hiring a large number of mediocre programmers
                will never be as effective as hiring one or two good
                or very good programmers.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="openness">
            <info>
                <title>Openness</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                One of the most important trends in the software world
                recently was towards “openness”: open-source, open-content,
                open-specifications, etc. Most good programmers you can find
                will find the open source (also known as “Free Software”)
                movement very appealing, and share some of its ideals. I
                don’t propose you should make your software open-source,
                although, of course, this is often a good business model.
                However, there are other aspects of openness that you should
                follow if you want to attract and keep good programmers.
            </para>

            <para>
                First of all, don’t over protect your code. Make it
                open-source if possible, give your contractors and consultants
                (including outsource ones) access to it, and allow your
                programmers to show parts of it to their online friends to get
                some advice. You should make as much of it as possible public,
                under
                <link
                    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open_source_license">open
                    source licences</link> to allow it to be used more often,
                increase its quality, and grow a culture around it. From my
                experience, working on “shrinkwrap” software that is used by
                end-users in the wild, and open-source software in particular,
                is the best way to increase the <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/computers/high-quality-software/">quality
                    of the software</link> as it requires the most discipline
                to work on and support.
            </para>

            <para>
                Openness does not end at that. Another important aspect is
                to allow your programmers to tell their friends and family
                about what they do. Some defence-related companies seem to
                think keeping everything confidential is a good idea, but
                that will cause your employees to feel unnecessarily
                trapped and unable to get help. So if you want to attract
                the best programmers, make sure they can tell other people
                of what they do, and what problems they are facing. (I’m
                not advocating complete transparency, if it’s not appropriate,
                but rather not being overly secretive. )
            </para>
            <para>
                Finally, you should avoid vendor lock-in: use standard
                or documented protocols and specifications,
                <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000052.html">take
                    Joel Spolsky’s advice
                    of letting your users go back</link>, and make sure
                your users have control of their data and can access it,
                back it up and convert it to different format.
            </para>
            <para>
                A good example for this is
                <link xlink:href="http://flickr.com/">the photo-sharing
                    site Flickr</link>, which has
                published full APIs for its service, and even allowed these
                APIs to be used by competing site.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="great-working-conditions">
            <info>
                <title>Great Working Conditions</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                You should make sure your employees have great working
                conditions.
            </para>
            <section xml:id="conditions--kitchen">
                <info>
                    <title>Kitchen</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    There should be a kitchen with a lot of food, hot and
                    cold beverages, etc.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="conditions--comfortable-offices">
                <info>
                    <title>Comfortable Offices</title>
                </info>

                <para>
                    I don’t necessarily agree that your workers should have
                    spacious offices with doors that close, but they should
                    still be comfortable enough. At one of my workplace, I
                    constantly had to move to let other people out of their
                    seats, and this was unbearable. So don’t do that.
                </para>

                <para>
                    In one job that I fondly remember, every employee had
                    their own spacious cube, with a desk to put a computer and
                    a place to put a few chairs. This was much more like it.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="conditions--best-tools">
                <info>
                    <title>The Best Tools That Money Can Buy</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    This cannot be stressed enough. As <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000043.html">Joel Spolsky notes</link> (based
                    on Steve McConnell) in item No. 9 of the Joel
                    Test, you need to “use the best tools that money can buy”.
                </para>
                <para>
                    If you buy old, broken and/or barely functioning hardware,
                    you’ll spend a lot of time debugging the problems there,
                    which will waste a lot of precious time. And you may
                    lose a lot of reputation and customers due to down-time.
                    <emphasis role="bold">Relying on reliable, high-end
                        hardware</emphasis> is a much
                    better idea.
                </para>
                <para>
                    I’ve been to two workplaces that gave me an old
                    computer with a 40 GB hard-disk. It wasn’t enough at
                    all. At one place, we’ve reached the limit of this
                    hard-disk due to several large source code checkouts,
                    and as a result needed a bigger hard-disk. And the
                    only hard-disks the lab had were 80 GB ones, which were
                    bought because they were the cheapest (per unit, not
                    per capacity). Please, <emphasis role="bold">buy
                        large enough hard-disks</emphasis>.
                </para>
                <para>
                    At the same workplace, I was given a computer with a
                    read-only CD-ROM drive. It was not even a DVD reader
                    I brought a DVD of audio files from home, and could not
                    read it. In this day and age, read/write DVD drives
                    are the standard, and are ultra-cheap.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Sometimes you’ll need <emphasis role="bold">several
                        computers</emphasis>, or a
                    decent <emphasis role="bold">virtual machine
                        emulator</emphasis>, to run
                    alternative operating systems on the same machine.
                </para>

                <para>
                    Make sure your workers have a
                    <emphasis role="bold">high-quality
                        screen</emphasis>. They
                    need to look at it most of the day, and they want it
                    to look nice. A decent 19״ LCD screen nowadays is very
                    cheap and well worth the added productivity.
                </para>

                <para>
                    You also need a
                    <link xlink:href="http://better-scm.shlomifish.org/">state-of-the-art
                        version control system</link> , of which there are
                    currently several high-quality open-source alternatives.
                    Some very costly version control systems have a bad
                    reputation for being extreme troublemakers, while the
                    modern open-source alternatives “just work”.
                </para>

                <para>
                    If there’s a good commercial software application
                    that your employees like to use and can recommend, don’t
                    hesitate to buy it.
                    You’ll also find <link xlink:href="http://safari.oreilly.com/">O’Reilly
                        Safari</link> Licences to be a good idea so your
                    employees can easily look up and read information in many
                    books on-line.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="conditions--sane-working-hours">
                <info>
                    <title>Sane Working Hours</title>
                </info>

                <para>
                    Give your employees sane working hours as
                    <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.igda.org/articles/erobinson_crunch.php">Evan
                        Robinson writes in “Why Crunch Mode Doesn’t Work: 6
                        Lessons”</link>. I.e: 40 hours work-weeks or less.
                    While sometimes asking them to stay late to finish a
                    deadline is acceptable, the so-called “crunch mode” is
                    under-effective and a recipe for disaster.
                </para>

                <para>
                    This feature was
                    <link xlink:href="http://developers.slashdot.org/story/05/06/08/1646234/why-crunch-mode-doesnt-work">covered on Slashdot</link> where
                    there are many useful comments and
                    later on
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.alternet.org/visions/154518/why_we_have_to_go_back_to_a_40-hour_work_week_to_keep_our_sanity/?page=entire">a
                        similar article (“Why We Have to Go Back to a
                        40-Hour Work Week to Keep Our Sanity”)</link>
                    was published in the site <emphasis>AlterNet</emphasis>,
                    and also <link xlink:href="http://developers.slashdot.org/story/12/03/16/1252220/bring-back-the-40-hour-work-week?sdsrc=popbyskid">featured
                    on Slashdot (with many comments)</link>.
            </para>

                <para>
                    This cannot be stressed enough. The more people work, the
                    less their hourly throughput is going to be, until they
                    end up at negative throughput. As a result, overworking
                    workers is dangerous because you're risking introducing
                    bugs and destroying existing work. Furthermore, your
                    workers are going to be much less happy than if they
                    worked less, which is also something you'd like to avoid.
                </para>

            </section>

            <section xml:id="conditions--location">
                <info>
                    <title>Location, Location, Location</title>
                </info>

                <para>
                    Find a good place which is close enough for most people
                    to get to. Make sure your programmers can commute to you
                    easily. Even pay for taxi-cabs out of your own expense,
                    or ask other employees to give them a ride, if
                    there isn’t good public transportation. The money you spend
                    on the cabs is very small compared to the one you would
                    lose by lost productivity, and by frustrations of
                    travelling.
                </para>

            </section>

            <section xml:id="conditions--payed-vacation">

                <info>
                    <title>A Lot of Paid Vacation</title>
                </info>

                <para>
                    Give your workers a lot of paid vacation. Humans are not
                    machines - they need rest and relaxation. The 14 annual
                    vacation days mandated by the Israeli government are a
                    joke. You should give them much more than that.  Joel
                    Spolsky’s company - <link xlink:href="http://www.fogcreek.com/">Fog
                        Creek Software</link> gives 6 weeks of paid
                    vacation, which is much more reasonable.
                </para>

            </section>

            <section xml:id="conditions--strict-firewalls">

                <info>
                    <title>Avoid Over-Strict Firewalls</title>
                </info>

                <para>
                    Some organisations put their intranets behind firewalls
                    that block access to almost all services. It is not
                    uncommon to see only the HTTP and HTTPS ports open for
                    free access.
                </para>

                <para>
                    However, there are many other Internet services that star
                    programmers need in order to be productive. Among them are:
                </para>

                <orderedlist>

                    <listitem>

                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat">Internet
                                Relay Chat</link> and other forms
                            of <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Instant_messaging">Instant
                                Messaging</link>. This allows star programmers
                            to discuss problems and share solutions
                            interactively with their peers, or just to
                            take a break from work and chat.
                        </para>

                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>

                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://www.openssh.org/">SSH - Secure
                                Shell</link> - allows access to remote
                            computers over the network.
                        </para>

                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>

                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BitTorrent_(protocol)">BitTorrent</link> -
                            allows downloading some content that is otherwise
                            not available on the Web, or that its download
                            can be resumed faster.
                        </para>

                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>

                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://samba.anu.edu.au/rsync/">rsync</link> -
                            allows for faster incremental downloading and
                            mirroring.
                        </para>

                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>

                <para>
                    And naturally, malware can easily propagate and
                    survive using HTTP and HTTPS alone, and there are ways
                    that clueful workers can overcome such restrictions.
                </para>

                <para>
                    At one of my workplaces, I was able to chat on the IRC,
                    connect using IM, ssh to everywhere I wanted, etc.
                    without any restriction. It was a liberating feeling
                    and I felt at home there. At a more recent one,
                    I needed to connect to a remote host, and invoke
                    port forwarding in order to talk on the IRC which was
                    annoying and error prone.
                </para>

                <para>
                    So make sure your firewall is not over-zealous and
                    does not prevent legitimate uses.
                </para>

            </section>

            <section xml:id="conditions--salary">
                <info>
                    <title>About the Salary</title>
                </info>

                <para>
                    Competitive Salary? Yes, it’s important, but not
                    absolutely everything. Great programmers won’t work
                    for you for free, but they’ll find many other
                    conditions much more tempting than an over-blown
                    salary. See what <link xlink:href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/homesteading/ar01s19.html">Eric Raymond
                        wrote about it
                        in “Homesteading the Noosphere”</link>, quoting
                    many studies:
                </para>
                <blockquote>

                    <para>
                        Psychologist Theresa Amabile of Brandeis
                        University, cautiously summarizing the results of a
                        1984 study of motivation and reward, observed “It
                        may be that commissioned work will, in general, be
                        less creative than work that is done out of pure
                        interest.”. Amabile goes on to observe that “The
                        more complex the activity, the more it’s hurt by
                        extrinsic reward.” Interestingly, the studies
                        suggest that flat salaries don’t demotivate, but
                        piecework rates and bonuses do.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        Thus, it may be economically smart to give
                        performance bonuses to people who flip burgers or
                        dug ditches, but it’s probably smarter to decouple
                        salary from performance in a programming shop and
                        let people choose their own projects (both trends
                        that the open-source world takes to their logical
                        conclusions).  Indeed, these results suggest that
                        the only time it is a good idea to reward
                        performance in programming is when the programmer
                        is so motivated that he or she would have worked
                        without the reward!
                    </para>
                </blockquote>

           </section>

           <section xml:id="conditions--conclusion">
               <info>
                   <title>Conditions: Conclusion</title>
               </info>

               <para>
                   One final note: you might think to yourself:
                   <emphasis role="bold">“how can I
                       afford all that?”</emphasis>. Well, the answer is that
                   the cost of all
                   these advantages is very small in comparison to your general
                   operation. And they will pay themselves much more as time
                   goes by in the happiness, productivity and loyalty of your
                   workers.
               </para>

               <para>
                   The last thing you want is to lose a competent developer.
                   And all these things will better make sure that
                   he or she will stay with you.
               </para>
           </section>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="pair-programming">
            <info>
                <title>Pair Programming</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                When doing
                <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pair_programming">Pair
                    programming</link>, there are two programmers
                sitting next to a single computer screen and keyboard, with
                one of them actually writing the code, and the other one
                observing and helping. At first glance, it seems like it’s
                a waste of resources: won’t they be under-productive? The
                answer is a “no”.
            </para>
            <para>
                First of all, pair programming increases run-time code
                review, as the “passive” programmer observes what the
                active programmer writes, gives him advice and answers
                his question. Code-review is always a good thing.
                <footnote xml:id="pair-programming-and-code-review"
                    label="CodeReview">
                    <para>
                        Pair programming is still not a substitute for
                        code reviews by people who didn’t directly
                        write the code. It was noted at a blog entry
                        I recall reading somewhere but can no longer find.
                        <emphasis role="bold">TODO: Write more.</emphasis>
                    </para>
                </footnote>
            </para>
            <para>
                Secondly, pair programming causes both programmers to have
                more discipline, and they are less likely to procrastinate
                as the active programmer will bore the watching one.
            </para>
            <para>
                Pair programming is also more fun, because people feel more
                comfortable working in pairs than alone.
            </para>
            <para>
                Finally, pair programming is more productive, because it was
                shown that it yields more output than two individual
                programmers.
            </para>
            <para>
                I had had a very good experience working in pairs back when
                I was an undergraduate student at
                <link xlink:href="http://www.technion.ac.il/">the
                    Technion</link> and can highly recommend it.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="give-employees-freedom">
            <info>
                <title>Give Your Employees the Freedom to Do What They Want</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                If your employee is responsible, he’ll care about his job
                to be productive, even if you don’t watch him. If he isn’t,
                then no amount of watching will make him responsible.
            </para>
            <para>
                You shouldn’t constantly monitor your employees. Instead,
                give them time to clear their mind and do non-coding-related
                activities such as:
            </para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Play computer games.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Browse the web.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Watch videos or listen to netcasts.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Read articles or books.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Work on open-soure software or their own personal
                        projects.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Chat with their co-workers or on-line peers.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Take walks in the neighbourhood, do sports, go to
                        clubs and other activities.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
            <para>
                These tasks and others don’t interfere with the work much,
                and actually contribute to productivity. And along with
                <link linkend="pair-programming">pair programming</link>, you
                can be more certain your programmers will work. Don’t judge
                your employees by how they spend their time at work - instead
                judge them by the overall progress they do in the long run.
            </para>
            <para>
                Moreover, some tasks that your employees do at their
                free time, may eventually bring your company publicity
                and esteem. Part of the reason Joel Spolsky’s
                <link xlink:href="http://www.fogcreek.com/">Fog Creek
                    Software company</link> is so well-known is because
                of the
                <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/">Joel
                    on Software</link> blog, which is one of the
                most-read weblogs about software management. This in turn
                resulted in a lot of publicity to the products of
                Fog Creek.
            </para>
            <para>
                If your employees are productive, you should not really be
                concerned what they are doing on their work time.
                <footnote xml:id="eric-sink-scrabble" label="EricSink">
                    <para>
                        Eric Sink wrote <link xlink:href="http://www.ericsink.com/entries/scrabble_1994.html">a
                            wonderful entry about the tolerance of
                            his former boss</link> on his weblog. (Here’s
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.ericsink.com/entries/ethics.html">an update</link>.)
                    </para>
                </footnote>
                Google allows its employees work on non-work-related-tasks
                20% of the time (while Google still owns the intellectual
                rights to their creations). I would go a step further by
                saying you simply should allow your employees to do as
                much non-work-related leisure as they feel they need to
                on their working hours. Tell them you expect long-term
                results, not 100% productivity-of-time.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="job-ads">
            <info>
                <title>Phrase Your Job Ads in a Unique and Smart Way</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                “3 Years Experience in Perl - Must”,
                “20 Years Experience in PHP - Advantage”,
                “Team Player”, “Independent Thinker”.
                <emphasis role="bold">Boring</emphasis>.
            </para>
            <para>
                Your job ad need to stand out. Take <link
                    xlink:href="http://groups.google.com/group/israelrb/browse_frm/thread/bb11cf1c3ed8e221">this job ad that was posted to the Israeli Ruby mailing
                    list</link> for an excellent example:
            </para>
            <blockquote>
                <para>
                    We are looking for a developer who:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Want a full time, salaried position.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Want to work in a fun, young workplace.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Want to work in an environment that allows them to
                            use (just about) whatever tools they wish to get
                            the job done.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Knows and love Ruby.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Ideally have experience with PHP and Python.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Want to work on large scale Rails/Merb projects
                            that have nothing to do with “the Social Web”.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            Want to drown a puppy every time they hear
                            phrases like “the Social Web”.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
            </blockquote>
            <para>
                See? I also want to write sites that are not necessarily
                “Social Web”, and I also got tired of the “Social Web” and
                its association with Ruby and other similar technologies.
                So this ad has caught my attention.
            </para>
            <para>
                As <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/LordPalmerston.html">Joel
                    on Software notes about experience</link>, the reason
                companies want people with a lot of experience in a certain
                niche, is because they tend to overcome problems they
                encounter more easily and so can help themselves and their
                co-workers with their problem more easily.
                <footnote xml:id="linux-systems" label="LinuxSystemsProgramming">

                    <para>
                        For example, I have a lot of experience working on Linux
                    and developing for it, with Perl and doing mostly
                    Algorithms and Text Processing in C. Recently, however I
                    got a job as a developer for a Linux Server-side C/C++
                    application (dealing with sockets, processes, threads,
                    Unicode and other such advanced problems). While I made a
                    lot of progress, I noticed that I often got stuck on many
                    problems, for which I had no idea how to easily resolve. In
                    this case, my co-worker who had more experience than
                    me in this area, could often help me more.
            </para>
        </footnote>
        </para>

            <para>
                However, as long as you have someone with enough experience,
                then bright people without a lot of experience can still
                prove to be useful and very productive. So don’t demand too
                much from them. As of 2008, there aren’t enough clueful
                developers in Israel for all the workplaces (and I think
                that’s also the case in most other locations around
                the world), and you can’t afford to be too picky.
            </para>
            <para>
                Another tip I can offer to look for employees is to use
                specialised job boards like the <link xlink:href="http://jobs.joelonsoftware.com/">the
                    Joel on Software job-board</link>,
                and <link xlink:href="http://jobs.perl.org/">jobs.perl.org</link>,
                <link xlink:href="http://jobs.thedailywtf.com/1001/browse.aspx">the
                    DailyWTF “Non-WTF” board</link> which highly-qualified and
                niche people follow. Just make sure
                to phrase your ad in a non-boring way, as I noted earlier.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="read-software-management-material">
            <info>
                <title>Read a Lot of Software Management Material</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                It’s impossible to put all the good advice I found regarding
                software management and software engineering on-line
                and off-line, in one document. So I urge you as a manager
                or an employee to read as much different material
                you can find. There’s a lot of good advice out there.
                Socrates said: “I know that I do not know.”, and he
                was right.
            </para>
            <para>
                While it’s easy to dismiss other people as “idiots”
                or what they say as being “stupid”, one should realise that
                even incorrect conclusions or reasoning can bring useful
                insights, and give some food for thought. Sometimes, I find
                some useful insights in rehearsed things or short blog
                entries.
            </para>
            <para>
                If you’re a manager or team-leader, you should make sure
                that you’re not much more clue-less than your programmers
                are, but that has often been the case for me and others.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="listen-to-your-devs">
            <info>
                <title>Listen to Your Developers</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                Which brings us to this: you obviously cannot get every
                aspect of software management right at first. Your programmers
                may eventually become unhappy, and you should make sure they
                can tell you how they feel, and to take note of what they
                say. Otherwise, you’re risking under-productivity or downright
                <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_depression">clinical
                depression</link>.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="software-engineering">
            <info>
                <title>Software Engineering Best Practices</title>
            </info>
            <section xml:id="functional-specs">
                <info>
                    <title>Functional Specs</title>
                </info>

                <para>
                    The first advice I can give is to <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000036.html"><emphasis role="bold">write
                        functional specs</emphasis></link>. In the link, Joel Spolsky
                    explains the motivation and method of writing functional
                    spec. A functional spec describes how the end-user will
                    use and interact with the program. It is not a technical
                    spec which explains how the inner code will work.
                </para>
                <para>
                    From my experience, functional specs are fun to write,
                    reveal many problems in the initial design, and make you
                    think how the program will work on the inside.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Here are three examples for functional specs I wrote:
                </para>
                <orderedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://svn.berlios.de/svnroot/repos/web-cpan/App-Freelancers-Board-Yonathan/trunk/docs/functional-spec/App-Freelancer-Board-Yonathan-functional-spec.txt">Functional
                                Spec for a Freelancers Board</link> (with a
                            Biblical theme).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://svn.berlios.de/svnroot/repos/web-cpan/CPAN-Module-Classification/trunk/docs/functional-spec-for-CPAN-Classification-Proposal.txt">Functional
                                Spec for a better classification of CPAN
                                Modules</link> (with a theme of FOSS world
                            celebrities).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://svn.berlios.de/svnroot/repos/winapt/winapt/trunk/docs/design/functional-spec.txt">Functional Spec
                                for a Windows package management system.</link>
                            (featuring characters from <link xlink:href="http://www.ozyandmillie.org/">Ozy and Millie</link>).
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="automated-tests">
                <info>
                    <title>Automated Tests</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    You should write automated tests such as unit tests,
                    integration tests, system tests, that will run
                    automatically on the code and yield an answer if all
                    of them are successful, or if any of them fail.
                </para>
                <para>
                    There are many good practices for automated testing such
                    as having daily builds or reaching a 100% test
                    coverage. Here are some resources to get you started:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://qa.perl.org/">The Perl
                                Quality Assurance project</link>, also
                            see their wiki.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Software_testing">The Wikipedia
                                page about Software Testing.</link>

                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                    Why are automated tests important? For several important
                    reasons:
                </para>
                <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            They provide a certain kind of executable and
                            machine and human-understandable specification
                            for the program, for new features and for
                            bug reports. By writing a test such as
                            <literal>add(5,6) == 11</literal> both humans
                            and machines can tell that that’s what the “add()”
                            function is supposed to do.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            A test suite with a good test coverage can better
                            ascertain that doing refactoring, adding new
                            features, removing them, or fixing bugs, won’t
                            break anything.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                            When the program breaks, then, without automated
                            tests, one cannot easily determine what exactly is
                            wrong there. On the other hand if you have a lot
                            of tests, with good coverage, you can see which
                            tests fail, and what exactly went wrong.
                        </para>
                    </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
                <para>
                    In short, writing automated tests gives more confidence
                    in the code and in changing it.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Note that having automated tests is not a substitute for
                    having <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000067.html">dedicated
                        software testers</link> (and vice versa). By
                    all means, they are both necessary for any serious
                    operation.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="design-and-planning">
                <info>
                    <title>Design and Planning</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    Most people agree that designing a program, planning
                    it and thinking about it is a good idea. Extreme
                    Programming suggests to have one design meeting every
                    week, which sounds reasonable.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Joel Spolsky
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/NothingIsSimple.html">gives
                        the motivation for designing software in one of
                        his articles</link>, which is a recommended read.
                    He also voices an opinion about over-formal design
                    (with lots of UML diagrams, etc.) that can actually
                    be a disadvantage to a project’s success.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="refactoring">
                <info>
                    <title>Refactoring</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.refactoring.com/">Refactoring</link>
                    is the process of improving the internal quality of
                    the code (from “a big mess” to “squeaky-clean and modular
                    code”), while not changing its external behaviour. This
                    is done for mostly functional and bug-free code, but
                    one which is not as elegant as it could be, so it can be
                    better managed.
                </para>
                <para>
                    “Joel on Software” features two excellent article about
                    the motivation for refactoring: <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000069.html">“Things You Should Never Do,
                        Part I”</link> (why rewriting functional code from
                        scratch is a bad idea), and <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000348.html">“Rub
                        a dub dub”</link> (how and why to do refactoring).
                </para>
                <para>
                    There are many other resources for that on-line, along with
                    many refactoring patterns.
                </para>
                <para>
                    There are many types of refactoring: grand refactoring
                    sessions (= what Joel describes), continuous refactoring
                    (refactoring as you go), “just-in-time refactoring”
                    (refactoring enough to achieve a certain task), etc.
                </para>
                <para>
                    But refactoring is important, makes development faster
                    in the long run (and even in the short-run), and can
                    prevent the code from deteriorating into an ugly,
                    non-functional mess that would be hard to salvage.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="soft-eng-methods-to-avoid">
                <info>
                    <title>Software Engineering Methods to Avoid</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    There are a few software engineering methods that I find
                    pointless, so I’d like to briefly point them out.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The first is the
                    <emphasis role="bold">“Huge-design-up-front”</emphasis>,
                    where an “architect” or even the entire team spend
                    a very long time writing an extremely comprehensive
                    and detailed technical document that specifies
                    in detail how the software will work.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The problem with this approach is that it is a huge
                    waste of time and also it is impossible to design
                    a large project top-down like that. A better way is to
                    involve the entire team in a good design session (a week
                    long at most) while writing some functional specs,
                    diagrams and some other documents, and then to write
                    it incrementally.
                </para>
                <para>
                    A similar fallacy is the <emphasis role="bold">“Mountains
                        of documentation fallacy”</emphasis> of having
                    superfluous
                    commenting, “Literate programming” (see
                    <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming">the Wikipedia article</link>), etc. The problem with
                    this approach is that the extra documentation is often
                    redundant if the code is well written and factored out
                    <footnote xml:id="extract-method" label="ExtractMethod">
                        <para>
                            A good example is that instead of having the
                            following pseudo-code:
                        </para>
                        <programlisting>
                            <![CDATA[
function create_employee(params)
{
    my emp = emp.new();

    emp.set_birth_year(params[year]);

    emp.set_experience_years(param[exp_amount]);

    emp.set_education(params[education]);

    ### Calculate the salary:
    emp.set_salary(emp.calc_education_factor(emp.get_education()) * emp.set_experience_years());

    ### More stuff snipped.

    return emp;
}
]]>
                        </programlisting>
                        <para>
                        Then it would be a good idea to extract the
                        complex <literal>emp.set_salary()</literal> call to
                        a simple <literal>emp.calculate_salary()</literal>
                        method. This
                        <link
                        xlink:href="http://c2.com/cgi/wiki?ExtractMethod">method
                        extraction</link> will make the intention of
                        the code self-documenting (as the method will have
                        a meaningful name) and much more robust for future
                        changes than adding a comment.
                        </para>
                        <para>
                        And this is just a small example.
                        </para>
                    </footnote>
                </para>
                <para>
                Some documentation (especially API documentation such as
                <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plain_Old_Documentation">Perl’s POD</link> or <link xlink:href="http://www.doxygen.org/">Doxygen</link>)
                is good, and you shouldn’t feel too guilty about writing a
                comment for an interesting trick, but too much documentation
                slows things down, and doesn’t help with the design process,
                and eventually may turn out to be misleading or harmful.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Something else I consider a bad idea is
                    <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/You_Ain't_Gonna_Need_It">Overengineering
                    or YAGNI (“You Ain’t Gonna Need It”)</link>. The basic
                    idea is not to implement too many features at once, or
                    over-complicate the design of the code, and instead focus
                    on getting the necessary functionality working.
                </para>
                <para>
                    YAGNI, put aside, I still believe that some
                    forward-planning is good.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="maintaining-two-codebases">
                <info>
                    <title>Maintaining Two Codebases</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    The code-with-accompanied-documentation is somewhat
                    a sub-case of a more general fallacy: the belief that
                    a company can simultaneously maintain two different
                    code-bases (say two code-bases implementing the
                    same functionality in two different languages), while
                    keeping them both synchronised.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The Extreme Programming experts have been warning against
                    it, and it also makes sense that it is hard to do given
                    that programmers, by nature, lack the appropriate
                    discipline to keep maintaining two or more code-bases at
                    once.
                </para>
                <para>
                    One possible solution to this problem
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/FogBugzIII.html">has been
                        illustrated by Fog Creek software</link>. What
                    they did was implement a compiler from a common language,
                    to several target languages. Naturally, this compiler also
                    needs to be maintained and extended, but it is less work
                    and less error-prone than maintaining several different
                    code-bases.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="specialisation">
            <info>
                <title>Don’t Over-Specialise</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                Many workplaces seem to think that it is a good idea
                to make sure every developer is limited to a certain aspect
                of the development process, and will specialise exclusively
                in it. Taken to extreme, however, such a trend is very
                dangerous.
            </para>
            <para>
                Programmers need to have a solid understanding of the entire
                product stuck in their head. Good programmers can also
                benefit from a change of scenery. And naturally, <link
                    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Code_review">reviewing
                    someone else’s code</link>, and criticising it, is also
                always beneficial.
            </para>
            <para>
                Therefore, you should make sure that your workers don’t
                over-specialise. Let them dedicate some time to work on
                what they find interesting, and let them review and
                criticise other people’s work.
            </para>
            <para>
                Once, before I started my undergraduate studies, I worked
                s a developer of a software-based modem (so-called
                “Winmodems”). I was impressed from the atmosphere there,
                and how professional and clueful the managers were. One of
                the things I liked about the job was that while I was
                initially hired as a tester, I eventually was appreciated
                for my eclectic knowledge of different aspects of
                sound, games, modems, Internet, and other fields. So, I was
                given more diverse things to do there, involving many
                aspects of our operation.
            </para>
            <para>
                You should follow suit and involve your star developers in
                as many aspects of your development.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="listen-to-your-customers">
            <info>
                <title>Listen to Your Customers or Users</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                Joel on Software gives <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/customerservice.html">a
                    lot of good advice on having a good customer
                    service</link>. You should listen to
                what your customers (or users) say. Don’t dismiss them.
                Don’t give them annoying canned responses. Open your
                bug-tracker to the world as a web-service. There are many
                web-based, and gratis bug-trackers, such as
                <link xlink:href="http://www.bugzilla.org/">Bugzilla</link>,
                and you should use one of them for better interaction with
                your customers.
            </para>
            <para>
                As Joel indicates, a bug report, email, or a query usually
                indicate a problem in the application: a bug, a missing feature,
                or something that’s not clear enough. Such problems need to
                be fixed in the code.
            </para>
            <para>
                Furthermore, if one or more of your customers are requesting a
                feature, and it seems to be important enough, give a priority
                to implementing it. As a developer from Mercury Interactive (Now part of HP)
                <link xlink:href="http://tech.groups.yahoo.com/group/hackers-il/message/2751">noted</link>
                usually the features requested by the customers, are the
                ones that will yield the largest amount of newer customers,
                not-to-mention will allow keeping customers, if they are
                paying for upgrades or as a “software-as-a-service” model.
            </para>
            <para>
                Joel Spolsky <link xlink:href="http://www.inc.com/magazine/20080401/how-hard-could-it-be-fire-and-motion.html?partner=fogcreek">also
                    notes that good customer service is part of the key
                to a small ISV’s success</link>.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="great-poets-steal">
            <info>
                <title>“Good Poets Borrow. Great Poets Steal.”</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                Originality and “innovation” is not as important as people
                think it is. It is perfectly OK to create a product in
                <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000056.html">a
                    niche which has a lot of existing competition</link>,
                it’s OK to build on other people’s efforts, and it’s OK to
                “borrow” or “steal” (see the quote at the top) ideas from
                your users, competitors and friends.
            </para>
            <para>
                You’re not getting credit for originality - you’re getting
                credit for high-quality products (software, services, support,
                etc. - whatever you do) and especially for revenue and
                profits. See <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000074.html">Joel’s
                    “Converting Capital into Software That Works” for
                more information</link>
            </para>

            <para>
                Another common fallacy is that ideas are the hardest part of
                the production process. However, ideas are very cheap, and
                creative people have far too many good ideas. It’s actually
                harder to develop the idea into a product, to mass-produce it,
                and then to mass-distribute it. Edison was not the first to
                come up with the Electrical Lightbulb, or to develop a working
                prototype, but he was the one to have put up all the effort in
                making it so popular and prevalent. Therefore, he is rightly
                credited as its inventor.
            </para>

            <para>
                Similarly, in the software world, you can often see competing
                products displacing more established competition, or sometimes
                a market where there isn’t a clear winner (e.g:
                <link xlink:href="http://xwinman.org/">window
                    managers and desktop environments for Unix</link>,
                Bug trackers, text editors, etc.)
            </para>

            <para>
                Even making rounder wheels is a good way to earn
                a living and to get respect.<footnote xml:id="ideas-at-the-same-time" label="IdeasSameTime">
                    <para>
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/shlomif-fav.html#same-ideas-as-everybody-else">Barry Jones said</link>
                    </para>
                    <blockquote>
                        <para>
                            If you have the same ideas as everybody else, but
                            have them one week earlier than everyone else -
                            then you will be hailed as a visionary. But if you
                            have them five years earlier, you will be named a
                            lunatic.
                        </para>
                    </blockquote>
                    <para>
                        This illustrates that as technology progresses, people
                        tend to get the same ideas at roughly the same time,
                        when they are mature and the natural logical step
                        forward. It’s unlikely you can avoid it.
                    </para>
                </footnote>
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="study-psychology">
            <info>
                <title>Study Psychology</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                Your co-workers are people. As such they have thoughts,
                feelings, emotions, and desires, which guide them and affect
                them. Learning how people’s psychology works, and how to
                motivate people and help them if they are feeling de-motivated
                - will help an employer be more effective, and make his
                employees more productive.
            </para>
            <para>
                This is also the case for your customers, users, associates
                and friends, who you will surely have to interact with
                , make sure they are happy most of the time, and deal
                with their problems effectively.
            </para>
            <para>
                Here are a few good resources on Psychology:
            </para>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0380810336/ref=nosim/shlomifishhom-20/">Feeling
                            Good: The New Mood Therapy</link> -
                        the best book I’ve read about Psychology. A self-help
                        book of <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_behavioral_therapy">Cognitive-behavioural
                            therapy</link>, this books explains what
                        causes Clinical depressions, and other negative
                        mood swings, and why people behave the way they do.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        It is a stark anti-thesis to Freudian psychology,
                        which makes little sense and is completely not
                        helpful.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/philosophy/guide-to-neo-tech/">The
                            Neo-Tech Discovery</link> - an off-shoot of
                        Ayn Rand’s Objectivism, Neo-Tech is the best idea-system
                        I’ve encountered yet. Note that it is easy to both
                        dismiss Neo-Tech as a stupid cult, or to hugely
                        mis-understand it at first. So when reading Neo-Tech
                        go over the material (preferably without skipping, but
                        possibly while taking breaks), and then let it sink
                        for a while.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Note that as of May 2008, the old hyperlinks to
                        the Neo-Tech site lead to redirects or PHP errors.
                        You can still find the old pages
                        on <link xlink:href="http://www.archive.org/">the web
                            archive</link>, and I hope they’ll get fixed.
                        In any case, it may be a good idea to order
                        “The Neo-Tech Discovery” book. (It is not available
                        in book stores).
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0465067107/ref=nosim/shlomifishhom-20/">The Design of Everyday Things</link> - this
                        book is a must read to everyone doing user-interface
                        design. It explains how frustrating it is to use many
                        everyday  objects (and, by inflection, software and
                        software devices), and how to design them right.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/071672328X/ref=nosim/shlomifishhom-20/">Helplessness:
                            On Depression, Development and Death</link> -
                        I haven’t read this book yet, but it was recommended
                        on <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/navLinks/fog0000000262.html">the
                            <emphasis>Joel on Software</emphasis> book
                            reviews</link>,
                        which I found to be of value. It is
                        also written from the Cognitive-Behavioural Psychology
                        viewpoint.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
            <para>
                Naturally, becoming a more psychologically-capable
                person is a process. No one is fully friendly, tactful,
                helpful, and considerate at all times. But one must always
                aspire to be more.
            </para>
            <para>
                For example, at one of the workplaces I had, whenever I told
                my boss that I didn’t finish what he asked for, but instead
                found out something else of importance or made some other
                progress he said “So what you’re saying is that you didn’t
                achieve anything.”. This is a classical case of the
                <emphasis role="bold">“All or Nothing Thinking”</emphasis>
                cognitive error, which is given in “Feeling Good” as a
                possible primary cause of depression.
            </para>
            <para>
                This attitude caused me to think and feel that nothing I
                could do, would possibly please him, and that he was
                demotivating on purpose. This was one of the reasons
                that caused me to assume a
                <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypomania">variation
                    on clinical depression called “Hypomania” (= below-Mania)</link>,
                which in turn made me under-productive.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="success-and-failure-stories">
            <info>
                <title>Read Success and Failure Stories</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                One of the many quotes featured at the signature
                of a friend of mine is <quote>Learn from mistakes of others;
                    you won’t live long enough to make them all
                    yourself</quote>. It is important to
                read success and failure stories of what people did,
                what mistakes they performed and what are their conclusions.
            </para>
            <para>
                I believe we can learn more from the failures of ourselves
                and others, than we can learn from successes. That’s because
                in a success, almost every aspect was done right, while in
                a failure one can look back and say where things went wrong.
            </para>
            <para>
                You can find many such stories on the Internet, and sometimes
                you’ll hear about them in news sites, blogs, and various
                forums.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="essential-software">
            <info>
                <title>Essential Organisational Software to Have</title>
            </info>
            <section xml:id="essential-software--wiki">
                <info>
                    <title>A Wiki to Prevent
                        the “Knowledge in the Ether” Anti-Pattern</title>
                </info>
            <para>
                One of the anti-patterns I encountered in previous workplaces
                is that of <link
                    xlink:href="http://use.perl.org/~Shlomi+Fish/journal/33013">the
                    “Knowledge in the Ether”</link>. Quoting from my
                original post:
            </para>
            <blockquote>
                <para>
                    One anti-pattern I noted in a previous workplace was what I
                    called “Knowledge in the Ether”: most of the instructions
                    for getting the application up and running, and a lot of
                    the collective knowledge were not written down in a
                    collective place. TDDPirate said he was familiar with it
                    and called it the <link
                        xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oral_Torah">“Oral
                        Torah”</link> syndrome.
                </para>
                <para>
                    The solution for this is simple: set up a wiki for the
                    company, and instruct people to write a note there whenever
                    they need to explain to someone how to do it (or give a
                    link to a previous note), <emphasis role="bold">instead
                        of</emphasis> guiding him how to do
                    it. While this requires some discipline and getting used
                    to, it can also be done after the fact.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Obviously the amount of knowledge in people’s head and in
                    the Ether can never be completely eliminated. But it should
                    be kept down to a minimum.
                </para>
            </blockquote>

            <para>
                There was also a comment there that said that if one encounters
                a repetitive task, they should write a script to do that. And
                it’s a good idea to keep good README files, comments, etc. and
                to use a standard building procedure, or prepare
                distribution-level packages for the program.
            </para>

            <para>
                Nevertheless, a workplace should encourage its employees to
                note down every useful knowledge and procedure. My friend once
                told me that in his previous workplace they kept a
                knowledge-base as a group of Microsoft Word documents stored
                inside a Visual SourceSafe repository. As a result, people
                felt it was too complicated to update and maintain them.
                Eventually, he set up an instance of <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.mediawiki.org/">MediaWiki</link>
                there, which proved to be much more convenient, accessible
                and quick.
            </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="essential-software--bug-tracker">
            <info>
                <title>A Bug-Tracker</title>
            </info>

            <para>
                Another essential program to use is a good web-based <link
                    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bugtracker"><emphasis role="bold">bug-tracker</emphasis></link>.
                Joel Spolsky has <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000029.html">an
                    article about the motivation and strategy
                    for bug-tracking</link>, which is well worth reading.
            </para>

            <para>
                The reason you need it to be web-based is so that it
                would be accessible from all operating systems, so it can
                be exposed to the outside and so you wouldn’t need to install
                a client on all machines. Microsoft’s internal bug tracking
                system is not web-based (for legacy reasons) and they’ve been
                criticised for the fact that Internet Explorer, unlike
                the Mozilla-based browsers, does not have a publicly
                available bug-tracker.
            </para>

            <para>
                Furthermore, in a previous workplace of mine, I was stationed
                on a Linux workstation (which was the deployment platform
                and what I like working on), and found that I couldn’t
                interact with our bug-tracker, which only
                had a windows client. Its more recent version already
                had a web-interface, but they wouldn’t upgrade for fear of
                breaking the other people’s workflow. This indicates another
                problem in not having a standards-compliant web-interface that
                can run on most browsers.
            </para>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="essential-software--vcs">
            <info>
                <title>Version Control Software</title>
            </info>
            <para>
                A good team should have a good version control server
                and clients available to every developer. I originally started
                the <link xlink:href="http://better-scm.shlomifish.org/">
                    “Better SCM” site</link> as a way to concentrate the material
                for the various alternative available, after I realised
                CVS has become inadequate for most needs.
            </para>
            <para>
                My rule of the thumb for choosing a version control system
                is the following: “When in doubt - use <link
                    xlink:href="http://better-scm.shlomifish.org/subversion/">Subversion</link>”.
                See
                <link xlink:href="http://blog.red-bean.com/sussman/?p=79">Ben
                    Collins-Sussman’s article “Version Control and ‘the 80%’”</link>
                for some of the motivation for this statement. Another one
                is that from my impression most of the new breed “Distributed
                Version Control Systems” tend to have catches for the unwary
                and other things that don’t exactly work as expected, and
                sometimes have poor portability to Microsoft Windows -
                a fact which is often a deal-breaker.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="essential-software--build-and-config">
            <info>
                <title>Building, Configuration and Packaging</title>
            </info>

            <para>
                In this day and age, you’d probably expect the new system
                to be packaged for the target platforms (of which there
                can be many), to be capable of being configured according
                to the constraints of the platform and according to various
                limitations and to properly be able to be built incrementally
                and tested.
            </para>

            <para>
                If you’re not convinced, refer to the <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.onlamp.com/pub/a/onlamp/2004/04/08/disaster_recovery.html">Robert
                    Jones’ OnLAMP.com
                    article on “Planning for Disaster Recovery on LAMP Systems”</link>, and
                What Joel Spolsky says in <link
                    xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000043.html">the
                    Joel Test</link> about “Making a build in one step”, and about having daily builds.
            </para>

            <para>
                So you need a good building, configuration and packaging
                system. I <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/computers/high-quality-software/rev2/#easy_to_compile_and_install">covered
                    such systems in an earlier article</link>,
                and also maintain <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/open-source/resources/software-tools/">a list of links to some prominent
                    ones and to other more comprehensive
                    lists</link>, so you have a high-quality selection.
            </para>

            <para>
                But you need to use something, and preferably something
                common, standardised, well-tested and high-quality.
            </para>

        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="which-technology">
        <info>
            <title>Choose Your Technology Carefully</title>
        </info>
            <para>
                So which technology should you choose? I’m not going
                to give a direct answer, and often there are many factors
                that make one more appropriate in certain cases than others.
                Joel Spolsky <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/items/2006/09/01.html">attempted
                    to answer this question</link>, but ended up falling into
                many common misconceptions and prejudices (while still making
                a few good points). He also focused exclusively on
                web-development.
            </para>
            <para>
                I won’t repeat this mistake here, but instead give some
                general guidelines.
            </para>
            <section xml:id="tech-foss-and-portability">
                <info>
                    <title>Is it Open-source and/or Portable?</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    One huge advantage to a technology is that it will be
                    open-source and available on several operating
                    systems, including most UNIXes and Windows
                    32-bit, and on many CPU architectures. While, often
                    you’ll encounter many platform-specific bugs or
                    libraries or programs that work properly only on
                    certain configurations (which is expected), you should
                    still have the choice of being able to rely on the
                    technology being present.
                </para>
                <para>
                    For example, Microsoft’s <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Visual_Basic">Visual
                        Basic</link> was a closed-source and Windows 32-bit
                    and x86 specific programming language, which had
                    proven to be very popular. However, Microsoft decided
                    to discontinue it completely, and as a result, many
                    of the applications developed for it can no longer
                    be maintained into the future, and important bugs in
                    Visual Basic will not get fixed.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="tech-expect-unexpected">
                <info>
                    <title>Expect some Unexpected Problems</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.faqs.org/docs/artu/ch16s01.html">Eric
                        Raymond’s “Tale of J. Random Newbie”</link> is
                    illustrative of the many problems programmers encounter
                    in highly-proprietary environments. However,
                    even if you’re using proven, mature,
                    well-documented and functional technology, you are
                    likely to encounter bugs.
                </para>
                <para>
                    I like Perl a lot, and have recently found some bugs
                    or even crashes in Perl code, which I’ve been trying to
                    isolate and report. Perl is otherwise very good and
                    reliable, but advanced users, or even intermediate
                    ones are likely to discover many edge cases.
                </para>
                <para>
                    You should make sure you have the capability to isolate,
                    report and possibly send a fix to such a technological
                    problem, and get a prompt fix. This often depends on
                    having good support from the technology vendor or
                    developer.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="tech-power">
                <info>
                    <title>The Technology’s Power</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    Various technologies and
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/Platforms.html">development
                        platforms</link>, vary in their power and cost. As
                    opposed to the possible misconception of “If you want
                    something good, you’ll have to pay more.”, often cheaper,
                    or even gratis (or open-source) solutions are more
                    powerful (not to mention more reliable and faster) than
                    their more costly counterparts.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Often, however, the really good solutions will be an
                    overkill. Most experts I’ve talked with agreed that
                    the <link xlink:href="http://www.oracle.com/database/index.html">
                        Oracle Database</link> is the most powerful on the
                    market and “years ahead of anything else out there”.
                    However, most run-of-the-mill web applications won’t
                    make use of even a small percentage of its advanced
                    features, enough to justify using it instead of, say,
                    the open-source and gratis
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.postgresql.org/">PostgreSQL</link>.
                </para>
                <para>
                    For many problem domains, Oracle would make the most
                    sense, but it’s still not very useful in the general
                    case.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="tech-habits">
                <info>
                    <title>Habits</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    It makes sense to
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/LordPalmerston.html">choose
                        a technology which you know very well</link>, so
                    you can overcome problems more quickly. However, smart
                    programmers can learn different technologies very quickly.
                    As Spolsky <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/ThePerilsofJavaSchools.html">notes</link>:
                </para>
                <blockquote>
                    <para>
                        The recruiters-who-use-grep, by the way, are ridiculed
                        here, and for good reason. I have never met anyone who
                        can do Scheme, Haskell, and C pointers who can’t pick
                        up Java in two days, and create better Java code than
                        people with five years of experience in Java, but try
                        explaining that to the average HR drone.
                    </para>
                </blockquote>
                <para>
                    If you expect that you
                    <link linkend="hire-the-best-developers">will
                        hire the best developers, as I pointed
                        earlier</link>, then they should probably be
                    able to pick up something new fairly quickly. If, on
                    the other hand, you’re going to hire bad programmers,
                    then you’re likely to be screwed - even if they have
                    extensive experience with their native technology.
                </para>
                <para>
                    So you should choose the best technology - not the one
                    for which you expect to find the most “experts”.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="tech-reliability-and-reputation">
                <info>
                    <title>Reliability and Reputation</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    Often a technology will get a bad reputation as being
                    “quirky”, “hard-to-get-right”, “buggy”, “unreliable”,
                    etc. This for example, has been the case <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/open-source/anti/mysql/">against
                        MySQL</link>,
                    <link xlink:href="http://www.google.com/search?q=php%20sucks">against
                        PHP</link>,
                    against Sendmail,
                    and against other technologies. From my experience, such
                    common criticisms often have a lot of substance,
                    and should be evaluated, especially if there are
                    equally affordable technologies, but such of a better
                    reputation.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="tech-maturity-and-mindshare">
                <info>
                    <title>Maturity, Mindshare and Distance from the
                        Mainstream</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    Maturity, Mind-share and distance from the Mainstream are
                    three factors that, like it or not, also affect the
                    choice of language. Immature technologies tend to have
                    many non-discoverable, or well-publicised quirks and
                    bugs. Technologies without a good mind-share have fewer
                    people to consult about problems one encounter. And
                    the less mainstream a technology is, the less it tends
                    to be polished or to have essential features, tools
                    and APIs, that developers of more mainstream technologies
                    take for granted.
                </para>
                <para>
                    As a result, such factors should be weighed in, when
                    choosing a technology.
                </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="tech-case-study">
                <info>
                    <title>Case Study</title>
                </info>
                <para>
                    I once went to a job interview in downtown Tel-Aviv,
                    which went very well. Then I received a phone call from
                    them that they want me to come and install Fedora Linux
                    on the computer. I did that, and next thing I knew, I was
                    given other tasks.
                </para>
                <para>
                    I was instructed to write a mail-processing framework
                    in PHP. Now since I know and love Perl, I know there
                    are many fine modules for doing that on <link xlink:href="http://perl-begin.org/topics/cpan/">CPAN (= The
                        Comprensive Perl Archive Network)</link>, but there
                    was little of subtantial quality for PHP. At a certain
                    time I needed to register at a site, to download the
                    latest version of a PHP library, that was open-source
                    software, because the download required authentication
                    . There didn’t seem to be anything better.
                </para>
                <para>
                    I was told that they would prefer to write everything
                    in PHP, because they expected to hire only PHP programmers,
                    possibly without any Perl experience.
                </para>
                <para>
                    That wasn’t all. They also decided against using <link
                        xlink:href="http://www.postfix.org/">Postfix</link>,
                    which is a modern, high-performance and open-source
                    SMTP server, and instead preferred the old
                    Sendmail SMTP server which has a far worse reputation,
                    and an arcane configuration system.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Furthermore, they also decided to use MySQL instead of
                    PostgreSQL, and we ran into a PHP misbehaviour (which
                    was fixable given a lot of PHP know-how) that made us have
                    to restart the connection to the server after every
                    request. Both MySQL and Sendmail were chosen from
                    political reasons.
                </para>
                <para>
                    With my PHP code barely working and prune to many errors,
                    I decided to quit after about a month, out of being
                    appalled by the bad code craftmanship I had achieved
                    there. Make sure you don’t repeat such a mistake.
                </para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="excellent-customer-support">
        <info>
            <title>Provide an Excellent Customer Support</title>
        </info>
        <para>
            Joel Spolsky wrote a
            <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/customerservice.html">feature
                titled “Seven steps to remarkable customer service”</link>,
            which is very insightful and inspiring. Among other things, Spolsky
            says there that every support request needs to be fixed twice:
            first of all by providing a fix or a workaround for the customer,
            and secondly by implementing a permanent fix in the product,
            the web-site or whatever, to prevent your establishment
            from ever getting such requests again.
        </para>
        <para>
            In addition to what Spolsky says there, I should note that you
            should provide help in as many channels as possible: from
            telephone to E-mail to
            <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Relay_Chat">IRC
                (Internet Relay Chat)</link> to providing your own web forums
            and mailing lists for help, etc. In order to prevent
            over-engineering and unnecessary forward-planning I would
            recommend implementing them when there turns out to be a demand
            for them, and to allow your establishment to grow
            organically. As <link xlink:href="http://catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/cathedral-bazaar/ar01s10.html">Eric
                Raymond notes in “Necessary Preconditions for the Bazaar
                Style”</link> (part of his the “Cathedral and the Bazaar” essay)
            it is necessary for the first released version of a successful
            open-source project to be good enough for people to run it,
            play with it, comment on it and find it useful. Similarly, when
            creating a commercial product, one should create customer service
            channels incrementally as they are needed.
        </para>

        <para>
            A particularly bad example of an awful tech support incident
            is <link xlink:href="http://community.livejournal.com/shlomif_hsite/11327.html">the
                suspension of my former Google AdSense account</link>. On April,
            2009, I was informed that my Google AdSense account was disabled
            because it caused a “significant risk to Google’s AdWords
            advertisers”, and from then on I could not log in to my account
            to get help. After I filled and submitted an appeal form, I
            received no reply after a month. Another appeal I sent did not
            get any response either. I next tried the Google AdSense support
            forum and received some replies from people who were not Google
            employees, that did not seem like a likely cause for an account
            termination, and no reply from an AdSense employee. After I talked
            with a few Google employees I know trying to reach someone in
            AdSense, one of them told me they did not know how to contact
            anyone in AdSense so they’ll likely going to be of little
            assistance. (Which is a big red flag in itself, indicating that
            Google has become too disparate and inefficient.)
        </para>

        <para>
            A somewhat better, but still bad incident was with the <link
                xlink:href="http://sharethis.com/">ShareThis.com button</link>
            that I installed in my site. After they started using Google
            Analytics in their re-usable widget (which I didn’t want), I wrote a
            support request and was replied with a laconic E-mail that only
            said: <quote>At this time, there is no way to disable our widget
                from accessing Google Analytics.</quote>. The problem with this
            is that they are likely to receive the same complaint from other
            users like me, and so will have to reply times and again, instead
            of fixing the underlying problem, like Spolsky suggested.
            I myself have decided to move away from ShareThis and others
            are likely to follow suit.
        </para>

        <para>
            And for a change, I was provided a good support by
            <link xlink:href="http://github.com/">Github</link>, which is
            a popular software-development hub. At one point, I got an
            announcement that my own copy of a formerly public version control
            repository was deleted, because the now private repository has
            been deleted as well. I did not want it and so went on the github
            IRC channel, and asked for help. I was told it was probably
            a bug and was asked to file a support request, which <link
                xlink:href="http://support.github.com/discussions/repos/2359-public-fork-of-a-formerly-public-repository-was-deleted-without-my-consent">I
                did</link>. There it was acknowledged that this was a bug,
            and I was offered a workaround that worked.
        </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="weekly-reports">
        <info>
            <title>Weekly Reports and Other Ways to Keep Track of Your Employees</title>
        </info>
        <para>
            Often your employees will run into problems and may be too shy
            or not have enough initiative to communicate them to you. If kept
            unchecked, this may lead to frustration, feelings of being trapped
            or worse. Here are some effective ways I found to avoid such
            issues, based on my experience from some of my previous
            workplaces.
        </para>
        <para>
            The first is to ask every employer to submit
            <emphasis role="bold">a weekly report</emphasis>:
            of what they have accomplished that week, what they plan to
            finish the next week, which problems they have run into, and what
            help they think they need. This report can be sent to their
            manager or supervisor, but they should feel free to send a carbon
            copy to their peers.
        </para>
        <para>
            Another method that I came up with, is to have an interactive
            multi-way Internet-based channel/“chat-room” where all the team’s
            employees can talk and chat. This can be implemented using
            a dedicated <link xlink:href="http://perl-begin.org/irc/">IRC
                (= Internet Relay Chat)</link>, using
            <link xlink:href="http://xmpp.org/">the more modern XMPP
                protocol</link>, and possibly using such dedicated proprietary
            solutions such as
            <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IBM_Workplace">the
                now disbanded “IBM Workplace”</link>. By chatting online about
            their work (and other stuff) and keeping logs of the conversations,
            one can get a feel for what the employees are feeling.
        </para>
        <para>
            Finally, it is a good idea to try to ask your employees once in
            a while what they feel or if they’ve run into any problems. Often,
            a different person can provide a fresh perspective on how to things
            and come up with creative solutions for how to solve their
            problems.
        </para>
        <para>
            Naturally, I’m not suggesting going to extremes such as
            monitoring your employees every move (as Joel Spolsky
            notes in <link
                xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/TwoStories.html">his
                “Two Stories” (about Microsoft and Juno) essay</link>),
            much less installing
            <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Keystroke_logging">keystroke
                loggers</link> or otherwise violating your employees’ privacy.
            But it would be a good idea to keep abreast of the problems they
            run into and see how you can solve them.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="conclusion">
        <info>
            <title>Conclusion</title>
        </info>
        <para>
            Not all the possible advice on how to manage a workplace was
            covered here. I refer you to the links at the beginning and
            inside the document for more reading. You should read them and
            be enlightened.
        </para>
        <para>
            The workplace I’m talking about is a workplace that aims to
            employ great programmers to work on great projects, which
            your developers will love to do. It’s not meant for a sweat-shop
            or one of those companies working on all these low-quality
            applications for internal-use, especially those that are
            developed by or for large organisations.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you want to hire the top developers, you should aim for
            a top environment and very good conditions.
        </para>
        <para>
            I don’t intend this document to be dogma, but rather to provoke
            clear thinking of the matter. A lot of bright programmers I’ve
            talked with about the vision of a perfect workplace, have claimed
            that this is an non-achievable fantasy, and that all
            employers are much more clueless than that. However, while
            perfection can never be achieved, I’ve seen my share of good
            workplaces, and benevolent and clueful employers, and I think many
            of them are enlightened enough to improve according to my
            suggestions.
        </para>
        <para>
            It’s not necessary for a programmer to be a wage slave - they need
            to be treated much better than that, if their employer
            wants them to be productive and happy. I hope this essay
            explained how.
        </para>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="thanks">

        <info>
            <title>Thanks</title>
        </info>

        <para>
            Thanks to
            <link xlink:href="http://jnw.name/">firespeaker</link> for going over
            an early version of this article and providing some corrections.
        </para>

    </section>
</article>    <!-- End of the article -->
