<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="index" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>Putting Cards on the Table (2019-2020)</title>
<authorgroup>
<author>
<personname>
<firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
<surname>Fish</surname>
</personname>
<affiliation>
<address>
<email>shlomif@shlomifish.org</email>
<uri type="homepage" xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/">Shlomi Fish's Homepage</uri>
</address>
</affiliation>
</author>
</authorgroup>
<copyright>
<year>2019</year>
<holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
</copyright>
<legalnotice xml:id="main_legal_notice">
<para>
<!--Creative Commons License-->
This work is licensed under the <link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial 3.0 Licence</link> (or at your option a greater version of it).
<!--/Creative Commons License-->
</para>
</legalnotice>
<revhistory>
<revision>
<revnumber>2014-08-24</revnumber>
<date>24 August 2014</date>
<authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
<revremark>
Convert to DocBook 5/XML.
</revremark>
</revision>
</revhistory>
</info>

<section xml:id="intro">

<info><title>Introduction</title></info>

<para>
This essay aims to present a summary of a snapshot as of 2019 of my personal
philosophy and ideology, titled
<link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/me/rindolf/#rindolfism">Rindolfism</link>,
which is dynamic and subject to change.
</para>

<para>
It largely builds upon a previous essay titled <link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/philosophy/putting-all-cards-on-the-table-2013/">“Putting all the Cards on the Table (2013)”</link>
</para>

<para>
I am really tired of having truly intellectual people like me "speak in
riddles" and be somewhat dishonest, so I'd like to put as many of the cards I
have now on the table. There will likely be more into the future, and moreover,
honesty is a process and a person should strive to become more honest as time
goes by.
</para>

</section>



<section xml:id="do_and_let_do__live_and_let_live">
<info>
<title>"Live and let live; do and let do"</title>
</info>

<para>
While it had earlier occurrences, I derive this piece of wisdom from <link
xlink:href="http://shlomifishswiki.branchable.com/Saladin_Style/">Saladin</link>,
a Muslim king and conqueror of Kurdish descent who is legendary for being one
of the most effective warriors, and one ofthe most noble and merciful people in
history.
</para>

<para>
During Saladin's time <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Palestine_(region)">Palestine</link>
which is also known as "The Land of Israel" or "The Holy Land" was ruled and
terrorised by the <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Knights_Templar">Knights
Templar</link>. These were Christian conquerors originating from Europe, who
were psychotic, psychopathological, vicious, sadistic, and vandalist, who would
have put <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nazi_Germany">the
Nazis</link> much less today's <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Al-Qaeda">Al-Qaeda</link> or <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Islamic_State_of_Iraq_and_the_Levant">ISIL</link>
to shame, and harmed the civilians in Palestine and were feared by them.
</para>

<para>
Saladin acquired a large army of loyal warriors, who all joined him by choice,
had superior swords to those of the Knights Templar, and lighter armour, and he
set out to release Palestine from the Knights fortress by fortress.  But the
most amazing thing is that he told the knights something like that:
</para>

<blockquote>

<para>

You can fight me or you can surrender. The choice is yours. Do what you want,
you don't have to do what you think you must. If you choose to surrender, I
will spare your life, disarm you and let you walk to Christian-controlled
territory. If you choose to fight, I will try my best not to kill or harm you,
and then swear you not to fight me any more, and let you walk to
Christian-controlled territory.

</para>

<para>

I trust you will make the right decision and entrust you with power.
Whatever your choice will be, I'll accept it.

</para>

</blockquote>

<para>
While some knights were probably killed, many of them survived and became
happy, sane, and while ostensibly Christian, unwilling to fight Saladin.  Even
if their religious leaders told them to return, Saladin told them he is OK with
the oath breaking and said he'll fight them again. This caused his Knights
Templar opponents to fight extremely poorly, and be quickly disarmed.
Following that, they learned their lesson, and would not fight Saladin again.
</para>

<para>
By letting people do what they want, they will likely do the best thing
they can do. This is management by not managing and parenting by not
parenting, which is and always was the best way.
</para>

</section>

        <section xml:id="big-minded-vs-small-minded">
        <info>
        <title>Big minded ("Rosh gadol") vs. Small minded ("Rosh qatan")</title>
        </info>
        <para>
        The Israeli military was small and as there was a lot of work to do
        to properly secure the Israeli civilians it coined the terms
        <link xlink:href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2004/12/06/news-45/">Rosh
        gadol ("big minded") and Rosh qatan ("small minded")</link>
        to encourage the soldiers to take initiative and try to perform their
        jobs as well as possible, regardless of the fact they were paid little.
        </para>
        <para>
        This extends to non-military work, government work, and voluntary work
        or hobbies and endeavours: if you care about something, do it as well
        as possible and give it enough time as needed. It will get easier and
        faster in time.
        </para>

        <para>
        For instance, a vendor on a candy store or an icecream parlour, should
        try to greet the customers, be friendly to them, offer recommendations
        to them if they ask, accept business cards with their personal web
        sites or social media presence and visit them, and generally treat
        every customer like royalty.
        </para>

        <para>
        If you do this, you'll likely get more returning customers, bigger tips,
        bigger bonuses and raises, and you may be able to land a better job
        based on a warm recommendation from your superiors and coworkers.
        </para>

        <para>
        The opposite is just following orders blindly, "I just work here"
        attitude, which is no different from the Nazis'
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Superior_orders">Superior
        orders - "I was only following orders"</link> which leads to laziness,
        stagnation, vandalism and sadism, just like the German Nazis in World
        War II, or the Knights Templar in Saladin's time.
        </para>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="amateurs">
        <info>
        <title>Amateurs vs. Professionals</title>
        </info>
        <para>
        <link
        xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/show.cgi?id=paul-graham-what-ameteur-meant">"Amateur"
        used to mean someone who worked for the love of it</link>. Such people
        often produce better results than those <link
        xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bJrqpR_7VSo">who do it only
        for money or even a lot of money</link>
        </para>

        <para>
        If you care enough about a task, invest the time to do it well.
        It should get quicker and easier and the results will be better and
        more "professional" in due time.
        </para>

<para>
In the book <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Three_Musketeers">The
Three Musketeers</link>, Dumas tells the story of how d’Artagnan who is a young
swordsman without much of an official training, from a remote region of France,
eventually becomes the best fighter in France. This is despite the fact that
his peers, Athos, Porthos, and Aramis, have much more experience and training.
</para>

<para>
It may seem farfetched, but before the industrialisation of the Far East,
and the way the West interpreted martial arts, with the coloured belts and
all, there were regional masters of these arts, who practised them as much as
they could and honed their skills. However, despite all that, they never ruled
out that they would one day fight against someone who never faught before,
and lose.
</para>

<para>
It took me more than a year to write <link
xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/TheEnemy/">The Enemy and How I
Helped to Fight it</link> which was my first real story, but it took me about
two weeks to write <link
xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/Summerschool-at-the-NSA/"><emphasis>Summerschool
at the NSA</emphasis></link>. This is whereas the screenplay for the film
Spaceballs took <link
xlink:href="https://thelaughbutton.com/mel-brooks/24-lesser-known-facts-spaceballs/">"only" six months to write</link>.
</para>

<para>
Similarly, it took Bob Dylan less than 20 minutes to write <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blowin%27_in_the_Wind">"Blowin' in
the Wind"</link> which is considered a masterpiece, but he likely wrote many
lesser songs before that.
</para>
</section>

        <section xml:id="hacking-heroism">

        <info>
        <title>Hacking and Heroism vs. Conformism and Tragedy</title>
        </info>

        <para>
        As you may have read, <link
        xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/philosophy/putting-all-cards-on-the-table-2013/#david_and_goliath">David
        who fought Goliath was a hacker</link> and it was modernised in <link
        xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=anEuw8F8cpE">the famous
        scene from Indiana Jones</link> where Indy shoots a master swordsman
        using a gun instead of struggling with him. Hacking or heroism involves
        breaking or bending as many invisible rules as possible and not
        accepting your "fate" (which is usually death) and this applies both to
        fiction and to real life.
        </para>

        <para>
        The opposite of hacking is conformism where you accept all the
        normative rules of society, fear your own shadow, and stagnate and die,
        possibly by <link
        xlink:href="https://studybible.info/ABP_Strongs/Judges%2016:30">taking
        many innocent people's lives with you</link>.
        </para>

        <para>
        As a result, eccentricity and "craziness" are the road to a happy life,
        not conformism as widely believed.
        </para>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="great-hackers">

        <info>
        <title>Great Hackers</title>
        </info>

        <para>
        A great hacker is an action hero that is aware enough of the essence of
        hacking to become a greater and greater hacker, despite whatever
        limitations he or she may have, and despite whatever setbacks they
        may run into.
        </para>

        <para>
        Note that some great hackers were clearly fictional (e.g:
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yoda">Yoda</link>,
        <link xlink:href="https://www.geekwire.com/2011/top-10-reasons-darth-vader-amazing-project-manager/">Darth Vader</link>,
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milady_de_Winter">Milady de-Winter</link>,
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Miss_Piggy">Miss Piggy</link>,
        or even <link xlink:href="https://mlp.fandom.com/wiki/Fluttershy">Fluttershy</link> ),
        some were female (e.g: <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah_Bernhardt">Sarah Bernhardt</link>
        , <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand">Ayn Rand</link>, and
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_Swift">Taylor Swift</link>)
        and some were underage (most notably <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samantha_Smith">Samantha Smith</link>, <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shirley_Temple">Shirley Temple</link>,
        and <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macaulay_Culkin">Macaulay Culkin</link> ).
        </para>

        <para>
        So don't let anything stop you.
        </para>

        <para>
        Even our period's canonical "anti-geek", <link
        xlink:href="https://bigbangtheory.fandom.com/wiki/Penny">Penny</link>
        from the popular sitcom <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Big_Bang_Theory">The Big Bang Theory</link>, is a wonderful great
        hacker, as evident by her constant "hacks" (or <link
        xlink:href="https://buffyfanfiction.fandom.com/wiki/Selinaverse#Dispelling_in_the_Selinaverse">"dispelling"</link>)
        of the rules and prejudice of the show's more stigmatic geeks.
        </para>
        <footnote xml:id="beauty_and_the_geek">
        <para>
        While it is wrong to <link
        xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour.html#pbride_philosophers">look
        down on reality show contestants</link> (and more recently - YouTubers)
        who, like older forms of entertainers / philosophers, are seeking
        recognition and fame, the show <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Beauty_and_the_Geek">Beauty and the Geek</link> was doomed
        to failure because not only are most attractive girls increasingly
        attracted to geeks, but they are increasingly quite geeky
        themselves.
        </para>

        <para>
        As funny as the
        <link
        xlink:href="http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/002892.html">"Math
        is hard. Let's go shopping!"</link> meme is, you can be a geek
        even if you are not too good at maths, and even shopping is a skill
        that can be honed.
        </para>
        </footnote>

        <section xml:id="fox-in-the-hens-coop">
        <info>
        <title>The Fox in the Chickens Coop</title>
        </info>

        <para>
        Despite common belief what happens when you put a great hacker (whether
        male or female) in a secluded place with many minor hackers or
        conformists, is not one crushed great hacker, but rather many great
        hackers, who spend time effort and conscious thought on satisfying
        their customers, peers and superiors. That is the "fox in a chickens'
        coop" motif as exemplified in <link
        xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joseph_(Genesis)">the story
        of Joseph in prison in the Bible</link>, and that of <link
        xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milady_de_Winter">Milady de
        Winter in "The Three Musketeers"</link>.  and In <link
        xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/Summerschool-at-the-NSA/">my
        "Summerschool at the NSA" screenplay</link>, a fictionalised <link
        xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/bits/facts/Summer-Glau/">Summer
        Glau</link> (the actress who is notable for being featured in <link
        xlink:href="https://xkcd.com/406/">xkcd: Venting</link> ) is the fox
        (pardon the pun) who devours the hens of the fictionalised NSA.
        </para>

        <para>
        I, Shlomi Fish, have done the same in real life in a top security
        Israeli psychiatric ward where I was hospitalised for being non
        normative, and for doing some foolish stuff. It worked surprisingly
        well, and I've used the collected wisdom of Moses→Saladin→Ayn Rand→the
        Beatles→Sesame Street→web 2.0 blogs and sites→My Little Pony / Taylor
        Swift and my own intuition and trial and error.
        </para>


<para>
It took me about 6-to-8 weeks, and I suffered from the conditions of the
hospital, but otherwise was able to hone my skills in benevolent psychological
warfare, and also started writing some essays with my limited computing
resources there.
</para>

        </section>

        </section>

        <section xml:id="hacker-monarchs">

        <info>

        <title>The Hacker Kings / Hacker Queens / Kings of Kings / King Messiahs / Best of the Best of the Best / Hacker Monarchs</title>
        </info>

        <para>
        Traditionally in history some great hackers have become so powerful
        that they took over the direction of the world and became a singular
        source of greatness. This is even though some of them were clearly
        or presumably fictional.
        </para>

        <para>
        In <link xlink:href="https://memory-alpha.fandom.com/wiki/Grand_Nagus">the article about the Grand Nagus in Star Trek DS9</link>
        , Quark is quoted as saying  «Oh believe me, the Nagus has the greatest
        business mind in the entire Ferengi Alliance, always thinking ten,
        sometimes twenty steps ahead of everyone else.» and this is similar for a hacker
        monarch who is often ahead of the curve.
        </para>

        <para>
Some examples for Hacker Monarchs are:
</para>

        <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moses">Moses</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyrus_the_Great">Cyrus the Great</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socrates">Socrates</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plato">Plato</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Aristotle">Aristotle</link> (believed to have been a band of philosophers with a central poster boy figure)
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/So-Who-The-Hell-Is-Qoheleth/">Qoheleth / Ecclesiastes</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        Muhammad
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="http://shlomifishswiki.branchable.com/Saladin_Style/">Saladin</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leonardo_da_Vinci">Leonardo da Vinci</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Galileo_Galilei">Galileo Galilei</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isaac_Newton">Isaac Newton</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cardinal_Richelieu">Cardinal Richelieu</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/American_Revolution">The American Revolutionaries</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexandre_Dumas">Alexandre Dumas</link> (pere)
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jules_Verne">Jules Verne</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Walt_Disney">Walt Disney</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ayn_Rand">Ayn Rand</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Beatles">The Beatles</link>
        </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>
        <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesame_Street">Sesame Street</link> /
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jim_Henson">Jim Henson</link> /
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Muppets">The Muppets</link>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Samantha_Smith">Samantha Smith</link>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/bits/facts/Larry-Wall/">Larry Wall</link> /
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Stallman">Richard Stallman</link> /
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds">Linus Torvalds</link>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
The fictional <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jean-Luc_Picard">Jean-Luc Picard</link>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
The fictional <link xlink:href="https://buffy.fandom.com/wiki/Buffy_Summers">Buffy Summers</link>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/">Shlomi Fish</link> aided by
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joel_Spolsky">Joel Spolsky</link> /
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eric_S._Raymond">Eric S. Raymond</link> /
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paul_Graham_(programmer)">Paul Graham (programmer)</link> /
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lawrence_Lessig">Lawrence Lessig</link> and others.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/bits/facts/Summer-Glau/">Summer Glau</link>
and <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xkcd">Xkcd</link>
</para>
</listitem>

</orderedlist>

<para>
Following the <link
xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/me/rindolf/#update_long_live_us_hacker_monarchs">Summer
Glau "termination"</link>, it was believed that there now can be several
simultaneous hacker monarchs, and that people can try to become ones while not
dethroning (or <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sic_transit_gloria_mundi">sic transit
gloria mundi</link>) the previous hacker monarchs. <quote>We don’t die. We multiply.</quote>
</para>

<para>
Note that even a hacker monarch may be fallible. Socrates almost got himself
killed several times until he willingly drank the poison. Plato and Aristotle
said equally blasphemous things, but learned from Socrates' fate and worked on
a better delivery so both died as highly reverred and respected. The same story
repeated itself with Galileo and Isaac Newton.
</para>

<para>
Many Hacker Monarchs were two steps forward and one step back, like the fact
Ayn Rand was anti-Open and anti-Amateur and <link
xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/show.cgi?id=neo-tech-selfishness">confused
selfishness with rational self growth</link>. So if you have a criticism
against even the greatest hackers, voice it - we <link
xlink:href="http://shlomifishswiki.branchable.com/Encourage_criticism_and_try_to_get_offended/">can
only benefit from it</link>.  Also see <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Emperor%27s_New_Clothes">The
Emperor's New Clothes</link> .
</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="make-your-own-kind-of-music">

<info>
<title>Make your own kind of music / Take your qualities to your advantage</title>
</info>

<para>
Similar to the <link
xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SbSM02_1k34">Mama Cass Elliot song
"make your own kind of music"</link> or its <link
xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xG0wi1m-89o">Lady Gaga
modernisation "Born This Way" </link> , I have given an interpretation of <link
xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/Buffy/A-Few-Good-Slayers/ongoing-text.html#faith-s-childhood">Captain
Nemo (= "nobody" in Latin) </link> in Jules Verne's novel <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Twenty_Thousand_Leagues_Under_the_Sea">20,000
Leagues Under the Sea</link> , whom people keep finding interesting for what he
believes are superficial reasons. But these reasons are part of what makes us
who we are.
</para>

<para xml:id="Cimorelli-ren">
The YouTuber band <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cimorelli">Cimorelli</link> has used
the fact that they are six sisters (along with some male brothers) in a large
Roman Catholic family, a fact which has received a lot of hatred from
environmentalists, psychologists and the media, to their advantage, and as a
gimmick. As a result, they published many videos of them covering hit songs,
some original songs, and have been live performing and collaborating with other
singers and entertainers.
    </para>

    <para>
    Naturally, they are not the only YouTube success story. But if you
    get an opportunity, seize it. Were you invited to give a talk? Go
    for it. Even if you were invited from the "wrong" reason, you will
    pave the road for future lecturers. A sociology student invited
    you to talk to them about your work as an open source / open content
    creator? Go for it. You thought of a new <link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/bits/facts/">Chuck Norris/etc. factoid</link>? Write it
    down and share it on social media and chat. Someone asked you out
    and you like them and are single? Go for it. You have an idea for a
    nice video, story, screenplay, song, etc. Execute it.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="time-is-much-more-important-than-money">
    <info>
    <title> Time &gt;&gt; Money</title>
    </info>
    <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://twitter.com/shlomif/status/1175578541292957696">This tweet reads:</link>
    <blockquote>
    <para>
    If you meet <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_Swift">Taylor Swift</link> on the street, have a pleasant conversation,
    and you need some money and ask her for some, she'll
    tell you: Sure, I do <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PayPal">PayPal</link> but not <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bitcoin">Bitcoin</link> because I value my time too much. How much do you want?"
    </para>
    <para>
    "How much is too much?"
    </para>
    <para>
    "Oh, try me."
    </para>
    </blockquote>
    </para>

    <para>
    There are likely many <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonprofit_organization">Nonprofit
    organizations</link> with millions of dollars in the bank and not enough
    volunteers' time to do anything with it.
    </para>

    <para>
    If we take <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah_Michelle_Gellar">Sarah
    Michelle Gellar (SMG)</link> for example, she went from donating money,
    back when she played <link
    xlink:href="https://buffy.fandom.com/wiki/Buffy_Summers">Buffy</link> into
    dedicating time for worthwhile causes after that.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="one-tin-soldier">

    <info>
    <title>&quot;One Tin Soldier&quot; and the senselessness of destruction</title>
    </info>

    <para>
    I discovered the song <link
    xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cTBx-hHf4BE">"One Tin
    Soldier"</link> - an anti war song from 1969, by accident through <link
    xlink:href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/pachelbel-rant">Rob Paravonian's
    Pachelbel Rant</link>. I found it saddening and touching.
    </para>

    <para>
    While I like the song as is, I wish for <link
    xlink:href="#Cimorelli-ren">Cimorelli</link> who are known for their upbeat
    and energetic music to cover it. But like <link
    xlink:href="http://shlomifishswiki.branchable.com/Self-Sufficiency/">Hillel
    the Elder noted:</link> <quote>If I am not for myself, who will be?</quote>
    so I plan to record it myself using my poor man's tools, while emulating
    Cimorelli's style: <link xlink:href="https://ffmpeg.org">ffmpeg</link>, my
    web cam, and <link
    xlink:href="https://www.audacityteam.org">audacity</link> all running on a
    <link xlink:href="https://duckduckgo.com/desktop_Linux?ia=web">desktop
    Linux</link> system.
    </para>

    <para>
    The song indicates that any destruction of lives, costly equipment
    or buildings, or even anti-spam measures, and removal/censorship
    of web or social media resources is self-defeating and wrong.
    </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="meaning-of-able-competent">

    <info>
    <title>What does able and competent imply?</title>
    </info>

    <para>
    Karl Marx famously <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/From_each_according_to_his_ability,_to_each_according_to_his_needs">remarked</link>
    <blockquote>
    <para>
    From each according to his ability, to each according to his needs
    </para>
    </blockquote>
    </para>
    <para>
    However, this is wrong because we should encourage people to be
    more able and more competent, and be less needy. So assuming we
    wish people to be more able, how do we measure it?
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    The first measure of ability is <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Money">Money</link> - the more
    money you have the more goods you can
    afford and the more free time you have to do creative works.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    The second measure of ability is <link
    xlink:href="https://twitter.com/shlomif/status/1175430272130650112">Fame</link>,
    the more people heard about
    you the more places will invite you to be present and even pay you
    for your time.

    </para>

    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    The third measure is "luck" which is which opportunities you seize. The
    media went out of its way to present <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paris_Hilton">Paris
    Hilton</link>, who was the canonical "alpha female" in the world throughout
    many years between 2000 and 2014, as incompetent, talentless, stupid, and
    lucky to have been a heiress by birth. However, despite that, she was the
    opposite of most of these. Moreover, if she utilised her initial state to
    her own advantage, then all the power to her.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    In today's Internet's social media, one can get a cheaper
    indication of some these, using views, upvotes,
    likes, "karma", reposts, replies, etc.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Naturally, abilities can refer to your various artistic
    , craftsmanship, sports, social, and intellectual skills.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    </orderedlist>

    <para>
    Now here is something interesting: there is a strong correlation between
    how able you are and how sexually desirable you are to
    members-of-the-appropriate-sexes (MOTAS) (who may still be attracted to you
    whether or not you or they are in a relationship.).
    </para>
    <para>
    Furthermore, <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fitness_(biology)">fitness in
    biology</link> in humans corresponds more to sexual attractiveness than to
    <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Physical_fitness">physical
    fitness</link>. In the United Kingdom, the adjective "fit" started meaning
    "sexy", "hot", "attractive" or "desirable" including such MOTAS who are not
    too athletic.
    </para>

    <section xml:id="sexiness-as-competence">
    <info>
    <title>Sexiness as Competence</title>
    </info>
    <para>
    Some people may still think that sexual attractiveness is indicative of
    incompetence and bad form, but it is the opposite. Back when
    I referred a deaf friend of mine to the video <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=21uXcvD5lPs">Daily
    Gradvice</link> (tongue-in-cheek sex/love/etc. advice by <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grace_Helbig">Grace Helbig</link>)
    he complained that the quality of the subtitles there was like "her butt
    before she cleans it up". I took offence for that because I knew
    she was a wonderful lady and that was because she was so sexy and
    sexualised, not despite that.
    </para>

<footnote>
    <para>
    The end of the story is that I told my friend that I will try to prepare
    better subtitles for use by him and others. While his original
    insulting delayed that, I eventually yielded <link
    xlink:href="https://github.com/shlomif/subtitles-for-dailygrace-on-youtube">functional
    subtitles</link> for the video, which my deaf friend was able to use (and
    can be used by everyone else).
    </para>
    </footnote>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="Taylor_Swift">

    <info>
    <title>Taylor Swift</title>
    </info>

    <para>
    We were <link
    xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/show.cgi?id=sharp-gnu--think-big">discussing</link>
    Apple's <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Swift_(programming_language)">Swift
    language</link> the other day on the <link
    xlink:href="irc://irc.freenode.net/#gnu">#gnu</link> chat room on freenode
    when I told someone there that he should charge 300 USD/hour for Swift
    projects because he disliked them so much. I also said the high fee may
    yield <link
    xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/show.cgi?id=joel-camels-rubber-duckies-11">a
    higher demand</link>.  Then I had a browser window open with the top
    Twitter accounts and <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_Swift">Taylor Swift</link>
    was there and I noted she likely charges more than 300 USD/hour for her
    live shows. He told me that she shared her name with that language, and I
    noted that she should sue Apple for trademark violations of the supposed
    "Swift" trademark - and win.  I joked that if "Apple sued Taylor Swift for
    violation of their Apple Swift language's trademark they will spend all
    their money in the bank on litigation and still lose.". Ha ha only serious.
    </para>
    <para>
    I then realised that Ms. Swift has become a <link
    xlink:href="#hacker-monarchs">Hacker Queen</link> by that time. While I
    think her face is good eye candy, she is not that beautiful in my opinion
    (but I think she looks <link
    xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IdneKLhsWOQ">much better with
    black hair</link> than with her trademark blonde hair). Nevertheless, there
    are many things we can learn from her.
        </para>

        <para>
        First of all is that she exemplifies the <link
        xlink:href="#amateurs">amateur model</link>, because she does stuff for
        fun, rather than for money.
        </para>

        <para>
        Her videos despite often being popular probably do not offset their
        production value in ads, but they are good publicity, provide fodder
        for remixes, parodies and covers, and are fun enough to produce so she
        can afford to offset the cost. She doesn't work for money or even for a
        shitload of money. She works for fun.
        </para>
        <para>
        Moreover, Taylor is an unapologetic <link
        xlink:href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/attention_whore">"attention
        whore"</link> who often spends large amounts of money or even also time
        in activities that will make her look like a better person	or more
        well known.
        </para>
    <para>
    Otherwise, Taylor Swift is a great philanthropist who likely <link
    xlink:href="https://twitter.com/shlomif/status/1175578541292957696">also
    donates to friendly individuals</link> and realises that one should <link
    xlink:href="https://biblehub.com/ecclesiastes/11-1.htm">"cast your bread
    upon the waters"</link> to quote the wonderful Biblical scroll of <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ecclesiastes">Ecclesiastes</link>.
    </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="Chuck_Norris">

    <info>
    <title>Chuck Norris</title>
    </info>

    <para>
    My <link
    xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/philosophy/putting-all-cards-on-the-table-2013/#chuck_norris">previous
    analysis of Chuck Norris and the Chuck Norris factoids</link> turned out to
    not be the last word on the subject. It is well known than Norris took the
    facts to his advantage, and as a result became the most prominent actor in
    Hollywood (which I call "the Alpha Male"). However, shortly afterward, the
    factoids seem to have fallen out of favour, and shortly after that, Norris
    announced that he retired from acting.
    </para>

    <para>
    Now, I still added factoids about <link
    xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/bits/facts/">other things to
    my collection</link>. Then one day in 2019, I was chatting on the #gnu chat
    room on <link xlink:href="https://freenode.net/">freenode</link> and after
    giving someone some advice came by with a new factoid which I uttered
    there: <quote>If Chuck Norris gives you some advice, and you do not follow
    it, he'll survive. However, you likely won't.</quote>, and to my surprise
    my fellow to the conversation, told me it was funny.  Some days later I
    spent some time with my sister's husband, who is an artist and a film
    maker, and showed him some of the software applications and web services as
    well my own software or text works, which I was familiar with as a <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux">Linux (or rather
    "GNU/Linux")</link> user and developer. Just when he and my sister were
    going away, I told him I had some factoids on my site about Chuck
    Norris/etc., and he told me he was a big fan of those.
    </para>

    <para>
    So what has happened?
    </para>

    <para>
    What I think happened is that Norris started playing (and fighting) in
    roles he liked, even if he didn't get paid or got paid relatively little,
    or was paid after the fact.  He became a happy <link
    xlink:href="#amateurs">amateur</link> rather than an increasingly unhappy
    professional. I won't be surprised if he has agreed to appear at local
    schools' plays, and/or playing roles that were seemingly unlike his
    traditional Hollywood roles just because he liked them.
    </para>

    <para>
    As a result of that, I believe Chuck Norris, both himself and
    the fictionalised Chuck Norris Facts image, has become a
    new Hacker Monarch. Well Done!
    </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="fear-is-path-to-dark-side">

    <info>
    <title>"Fear is the path to the dark side"</title>
    </info>

    <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://starwars.fandom.com/wiki/Yoda">Master Yoda</link>
    is a <link xlink:href="#great-hackers">great
    hacker</link> despite being fictional, and we can learn a lot from what
    <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kFnFr-DOPf8">he said
    about being unnecessarily paranoid:</link>
    </para>

<blockquote>

<para>

Fear is the path to the dark side, fear leads to anger, anger leads to hate,
hate leads to suffering. And I sense much fear in you.

</para>

</blockquote>

<para>
When one is irrationally paranoid, he will become careless which may cause him
to lose property (including data) or even his life.
</para>

<para>
Following the <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Snowden">Snowden
findings</link>, some people decided to go to great lengths to avoid the NSA,
CIA, or FBI knowing about their private lives, and online services such as
Google or Facebook "fingerprinting" them.
</para>

<para>
However, do you honestly think the NSA/etc. cares enough about you to harm you?
In my <link
xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/SummerNSA/">#SummerNSA</link>
effort I have said many unkind things about <link
xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/bits/facts/NSA/">an idolised
version of the NSA</link>, and nothing happened to me, my homesite, and my
other online writings / blogging.  (and I announced <link
xlink:href="https://www.reddit.com/r/xkcd/comments/1bignr/xkcdinspired_screenplay_starring_summer_glau_as/">the
"Summerschool at the NSA" informal screenplay</link> on reddit some months
before the Snowden findings of fact.
</para>

<para>
On freenode, a chat friend told me he was glad that Google has his gmail.com
email because it means someone has them, and it won't get lost like his
previous E-mail got lost in a hard disk failure.
</para>

<para>
I keep most of my important digital data in public repositories on <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GitHub">GitHub</link> and other "code
sharing" sites because to quote <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds">Linus
Torvalds</link>: “Only wimps use tape backup. Real men just upload their
important stuff on FTP and let the rest of the world mirror it.”. Nowadays, one
should <link
xlink:href="https://better-scm.shlomifish.org/docs/this-site-is-irrelevant/">use
git as a version control system</link> most of the time, but the point is that
one must <link
xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/philosophy/putting-all-cards-on-the-table-2013/#publish_or_perish">publish
or perish</link>.
</para>

<para>
(Note that there is also <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Drive">Google Drive</link> and
similar services, which is more friendly to
laymen, has a web interface and has coarser grained revision history.)
</para>

<para>
My <link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/me/contact-me/">contact
info</link> is publicly available, and I actually wish for more people -
of any sex/gender, ethnicity, talents and interest, race, nationality, etc.
- to contact me and chat in any plausible medium.
</para>

<para>
So please do not be paranoid and overly possessive of your crown jewels.
</para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="hakuna-matata">

    <info>
    <title>Hakuna Matata - no worries and no problems</title>
    </info>

    <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hakuna_matata">Hakuna
    matata</link> is a Swahili phrase, which after it was introduced in <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hakuna_Matata_(song)">a
    song</link> in the Disney film <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Lion_King">The Lion
    King</link> came to mean both "no worries" and "no problem".
    </para>

    <para>
    Some people came up with <link
    xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/computers/open-source/foss-licences-wars/#strong-copyleft-and-threats-to-foss">elaborate
    hypothetical scenarios</link> where using the more restrictive <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GNU_General_Public_License">GPL
    licence</link> will be advantageous instead of <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Permissive_software_license">permissive
    software licences</link> which I prefer to use for most of the <link
    xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/open-source/projects/">software</link>
    which I originated. However, I was non-plused by them and said I will be
    “OK with it”. People did not violate my trust, because I entrusted them
    with the power to do so, which made them feel empowered - not despite it.
    </para>

    <para>
    I believe that if the great <link
    xlink:href="http://shlomifishswiki.branchable.com/Saladin_Style/">Saladin</link>
    was alive today and was a developer of open source software (which <link
    xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour.html#if_ayn_rand_was_born_in_the_1990s">is
    not as farfetched as it sounds</link>), then he too would prefer using
    permissive licences when he could help it.
    </para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="benevolent-psychological-warfare">

    <info>
    <title>Benevolent Psychological Warfare</title>
    </info>

<para>
Benevolent psychological warfare was practiced by Saladin, but was enhanced
by greater and greater action heroes / hackers throughout the ages: including
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sesame_Street">Sesame Street</link>,
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Beatles">The Beatles</link>,
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_2.0">web 2.0 bloggers / online
writers and online entertainers</link>,
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/My_Little_Pony:_Friendship_is_Magic">My Little Pony: Friendship is Magic</link>,
and <link xlink:href="#YouTube">YouTube videos</link>.
</para>

<para>
The good news is that it is easy to practice, and can even be applied by people
who are not in a position of power. And it can be summarised by the famous
adage
<link xlink:href="https://mygeekwisdom.com/2011/09/12/be-excellent-to-each-other/">"Be excellent to each other"</link>.
</para>

<para>
If you interact with a fellow person, shake his hand. Expect
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pygmalion_effect">everyone
to improve and become better</link> (= the Pygmalion effect as
opposed to <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Golem_effect">the Golem effect</link>) and act accordingly.
</para>

<para>
Thank someone for doing something you like. But be honest and tell someone
if you dislike some action he took, or one of their works/creations (even
if you feel they are your superior).
</para>

<para>
Express interest in the other person. Ask them "What's up?", "What's new?",
etc. If he says "nothing much" tell them <link
xlink:href="https://twitter.com/shlomif/status/635904227890458624">they should
try to be less boring than that</link>.
</para>

<para>
I recall that during <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2018_FIFA_World_Cup_Final">the 2018
FIFA World Cup Final</link>, the <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kolinda_Grabar-Kitarovi%C4%87">Croatian
president</link>, who is a woman, was so sweet and hugged all the (male)
players of both teams: her native country, Croatia — and France — which won the
match.
</para>

<para>
Similarly, <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Elizabeth_II">Queen
Elizabeth II</link> has reportedly recently <link
xlink:href="https://www.manchestereveningnews.co.uk/news/greater-manchester-news/guest-honour-queen-leaves-couple-685253">actually
attended</link> a wedding to which a British couple invited her as a
joke.<footnote><para>To quote <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Peter_Ustinov">Peter Ustinov</link>:
«Comedy is simply a funny way of being serious».</para></footnote>
</para>

<para>
Sometimes people may refuse to interact with you, in that case say: «OK, no
problem, have a nice day!»
</para>

<para>
It is also a good idea to compliment your friends and acquaintances, of
whatever sex, for their looks. I recall telling a gorgeous young woman who
came to visit one of the fellow patients in the hospital: "You are
beautiful", and she thanked me for that, and noted that nobody had told her
that in several years. (Which made me sad.)
</para>

<section xml:id="dont-be-afraid-to-ask-for-help">

<info>
<title>Don’t be afraid to ask for help</title>
</info>

<para>
One important thing to note is that we all have our limitations and we
are not good at everything. As a result, it is important that we sometimes
ask other people for help, despite whatever <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feudalism">Feudalism</link>-like take
on “independence” there
may be. For example, I prefer not to cook complex meals myself, because cooking
and learning to cook would be a grand <link xlink:href="#time-is-much-more-important-than-money">waste of time</link> for me and I'd produce mediocre at best
results.
</para>

<para>
For some inspiration you may wish to listen to the Beatles' songs
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Help!_(song)">"Help!"</link>
and <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/With_a_Little_Help_from_My_Friends">"With
a Little Help from My Friends"</link>.
</para>
</section>

    <section xml:id="pick-up-art">

        <info>
        <title>Thoughts about how to Approach a MOTAS</title>
        </info>

        <para>
        "Be excellent to each other" and being honest has implications with
        respect to how a man or a woman should approach a member of the
        appropriate sex (or <link
        xlink:href="http://www.catb.org/jargon/html/M/MOTAS.html">MOTAS</link>).
        If you are interested in testing the waters for a long-term
        relationship, then a good strategy will be to simply say: <quote>Hi, I
        like you and think you are
        beautiful/handsome/cute/hot/sexy/gorgeous/etc. What do you say we go on
        a date?</quote> Either he or she will agree, or you have wasted much
        less time.
        </para>

        <para>
        Note that girls should feel free to approach guys this way too.  In my
        <link
        xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/stories/">stories</link>,
        I have tried to encourage women to become more sexually assertive, but
        it seems that most Israeli girls did not get the memo, and are still
        shy and playing it hard to get.  <footnote><para>It is possible my site
        has not been as popular in Israel as it could be because it is written
        almost entirely in English and because I have not been too active on
        social media that is popular in Israel such as Facebook, Instagram, and
        WhatsApp.  </para></footnote>
        </para>

        <para>
        What if you are interested in a one off sexual intercourse? Nothing
        wrong with that, and you can learn about how to do it from Jazz from
        The Fresh Prince of Bel-Air: <link
        xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KcD7hvH0Wk8">"let's go get
        some barbecue and get busy"</link>. Or as DAILY GRADVICE put it for a
        girl trying to seduce a guy: <link
        xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=21uXcvD5lPs">"I want you to
        sail your dick ship into my lady port."</link>.
        </para>

        <para>
        Naturally, it doesn't have to be these exact words, but the point
        stands: be honest, sincere, and candid, cut to the chase and don't play
        games.
        </para>


    </section>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="YouTube">

    <info>
    <title>YouTube</title>
    </info>

    <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/">YouTube</link> is a video
    sharing site which you've probably heard of. While there are many
    official videos by signed artists or by the film owners' copyrights,
    there is also a huge ecosystem of original "direct-to-YouTube" art
    created by the so called "YouTubers". They upload anything from bootleg
    videos of songs, to technical tutorials, to low cost covers (often just
        a man or a woman singing and playing a guitar, a piano or even an electric
        organ or A cappella), to parodies, to lyric videos, to live recordings
    of any musicians or comedians.
    </para>
    <para>
    Now, some people still look down on YouTubers thinking that covers can never
    be better than the original, but having been introduced to the world of
    YouTube covers, I can often prove them wrong:
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n6KAGqjdmsk">Tiffany Alvord’s cover
    of Hurt Me Tomorrow by K'NAAN</link>
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=d2RZXeQc5HU">Jess Greenberg’s
    cover of "Highway to Hell" by AC/DC</link> (somewhat NSFW- "boobs")
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=n5HexLIqWY8">Alex Boye and
    Mom Bloggers United Africanised Cover of Katy Perry’s Roar</link>
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/Files/files/video/Me%20Singing%20%22I%20Will%20Always%20Love%20You%22%20by%20Whitney%20Houston-CBdmpvPa73g.mp4">Christina Grimmie's (RIP)
    karoake cover of Whitney Houston (also RIP)’s "I Will Always Love You"</link>
    </para>
    </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
    Naturally, there is a lot of junk on YouTube - <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sturgeon's_law">Sturgeon's law
    ("ninety percent of anything is crap")</link> is still true, and that may include
    <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCc6rd10fdTTa8IBAdau_Cww">my own
    YouTube channel</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
    One problem with YouTube is that many videos have been removed, or
    censored, or
    disappeared, or blocked in certain regions (often by automated
        filters). Some people like me try to use
    <link xlink:href="https://rg3.github.io/youtube-dl/">youtube-dl</link>
    or similar downloaders to download every video that we like from
    YouTube, and while some die hard copyright puritans have looked
    down on that, I still support that as a way to battle censorship.
    <footnote>
    <para>
    Someone told me in a chat, that he believed that Google (who owns
        YouTube) will do a DMCA takedown for GitHub to censor youtube-dl,
    but even if they were stupid enough to do that (which I doubt), it
    would not stop youtube-dl, whose open source public domain source
    code has thousands of git clones and forks.
    </para>
    </footnote>
    </para>
    <para>
    While I do not condone the <link
    xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YouTube_headquarters_shooting">recent
    YouTube shooting</link> (by a woman no less), I believe that YouTube has
    brought it upon themselves by the aggressive and irrational content
    filtering and removal, that many YouTube creators and users have been
    witnessing.
    </para>

<para>
I believe that signed artists and creators (or the somewhat more professional
ones) should <emphasis role="bold">emulate YouTubers</emphasis> and start indie
channels where they post regular collaborations with other YouTubers: from the
better known to the obscure.
</para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="amateur-modelled-commerce">

    <info>
    <title>Amateur-modelled commerce</title>
    </info>

    <para>
    Capitalism has been getting a bad reputation since Karl Marx published
    his book <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Das_Kapital">Das Kapital</link>
    or as Neo-Tech put it:
    </para>

    <blockquote>

<para>
The dictionary definition of capitalism is: An economic system characterized by
private ownership of capital goods and by investments that are determined by
private decision rather than by state control. Prices, production and
distribution of goods are determined by a free market.
</para>
…
<para>
But most writers and commentators put dishonest altruistic-platonistic
connotations on the meaning of capitalism: A system of exploitation of the weak
by the strong -- devoid of love and good will. A system in which unwanted goods
and services are pushed onto consumers through clever, deceptive advertising
for the sole purpose of profits and greed. Capitalism dominates most Western
governments. Capitalism, big business, and fascism are synonymous.
</para>

    </blockquote>

<para>
I am no longer a libertarian purist, but I still think Capitalism and
liberalism are the best economic system and political system respectively.
</para>

<para>
That put aside, here are some thoughts about a more <link xlink:href="#amateurs">amateur</link> take on commerce that we can consider:
</para>

<orderedlist>

<listitem>

<para>
I once attended an Israeli <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LiveJournal">LiveJournal</link>-ers
meetup (back when LiveJournal was more popular outside Russia) which took place
in a vegetarian Indian restaurant. Now it allowed one to eat as much as they
want from the buffet and pay as much (or as little) as they want.
</para>

<para>
Now, I ate some of the food there which was pretty good, and decided to pay 70
<link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Israeli_new_shekel">ILS</link>
whereas I recall that at a time a hamburger meal at a decent restaurant costed
between 40 ILS and 50 ILS. Why? Because I appreciated their trust and felt
generous.
</para>

</listitem>

<listitem>
<para>

Creators of digital media (or "content") may opt to initially release their
works under relatively restrictive licences such as <link
xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Creative
Commons CC-by-nc-sa</link> or <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Affero_General_Public_License">the
Affero GPL</link>, and either sell commercial or proprietary exceptions to the
licence.  Alternatively, they can ask for money to put it under a less
restrictive licence such as <link
xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">CC-by</link> , <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIT_License">the MIT licence</link> ,
or even <link
xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Creative_Commons_license#Zero_/_public_domain">CC0
/ public domain</link>.
</para>
</listitem>

</orderedlist>
<para>

https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/computers/web/models-for-commerce/

https://github.com/nayafia/lemonade-stand

my commissions - https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/show.cgi?id=shlomif-multiply-by-pi ; charge 50 USD / hour and do not charge if the customer is
unhappy.

https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/joel-on-software.html#joel-camels-rubber-duckies-1

<link xlink:href="https://github.com/shlomif/dosbox/commit/50a6334e3713d8647553aa8d1809c0243633cb60">both FOSS and got paid.</link>
</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="people-can-change">

    <info>
    <title>People Can Change; Companies and countries and communities too</title>
    </info>

    </section>
    <section xml:id="four-kinds-of-fools">

    <info>
    <title>Four kinds of fools: avoiding prejudice</title>
    </info>

<para>
<link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/show.cgi?id=two-kinds-of-fools">https://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/show.cgi?id=two-kinds-of-fools</link>
</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="encouraging-and-handling-criticism">
    <info>
    <title>Criticism</title>
    </info>
    <para>
    <link xlink:href="http://shlomifishswiki.branchable.com/Encourage_criticism_and_try_to_get_offended/">Encourage criticism and try to get offended</link>
    <link xlink:href="http://shlomifishswiki.branchable.com/Never_Try_to_Please_Everyone/">Never Try to Please Everyone</link>
    <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/If%E2%80%94">"If—" by Rudyard Kipling</link>
    </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="forgiveness">

    <info>
    <title>Forgiveness</title>
    </info>
        <para>
        Saladin forgave the Knights Templar for vandalism and murder, so you
        can forgive someone who offended you.
        </para>
        <para>
        Lao Tsu noted in <link
        xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tao_Te_Ching">Tao Te
        Ching</link> that <quote>Those kind, be kind to them; Those unkind, be
        kind to them also.</quote> and there is also the aphorism
        <quote>keep your friends close and enemies closer.</quote>
        from <link xlink:href="https://www.quora.com/Who-said-Keep-your-friends-close-and-your-enemies-closer">the Godfather part II</link>.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="managing-your-memory">

    <info>
    <title>Managing Your Memory</title>
    </info>

<para>
<link xlink:href="http://unarmed.shlomifish.org/1991.html">Sherlock Holmes
about Awk</link>
</para>

    </section>
</article>
