<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="index" xml:lang="en">
<info>
<title>About Supporting Older Releases of perl5 For CPAN Distributions</title>
<date>2025-12-24</date>
<authorgroup>
<author>
<personname>
<firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
<surname>Fish</surname>
</personname>
<affiliation>
<address>
<email>shlomif@shlomifish.org</email>
<uri type="homepage" xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/">Shlomi Fish’s Homepage</uri>
</address>
</affiliation>
</author>
</authorgroup>
<copyright>
<year>2025</year>
<holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
</copyright>
<legalnotice xml:id="main_legal_notice">
<para>
<!--Creative Commons License-->
This work is licensed under the <link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License (CC-by)</link> (or at your option any greater version of it).
</para>
</legalnotice>
</info>

<section xml:id="_tldr_summary">
<info>
<title>TL;DR Summary</title>
</info>
<para>Due to several reasons, I am setting a minimal version of perl5 - 5.12.0
or even higher - for <emphasis role="strong">some</emphasis> of my <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CPAN">CPAN</link>
distributions (not all). You should either upgrade your perl5, or
alternatively pay me to support older releases of perl5.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="_motivation">
<info>
<title>Motivation</title>
</info>
<para>I hesitate to lower the supported version of perl because that may increase the maintenance burden (CPAN Testers / etc.). You should upgrade to a newer version of perl because 5.10 is very old (last released in August 2009 - <link xlink:href="http://use.perl.org/use.perl.org/articles/09/08/25/0556226.shtml">reference</link> ), is unmaintained and possibly broken and there&#8217;s already perl 5.28.x . There&#8217;s some discussion of dedicating time to doing such transitions and upgrades here - <link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/psychology/changing-the-seldon-plan/">Changing the Seldon plan</link> .</para>
<para>If you cannot afford to upgrade the system&#8217;s perl, you can try using <link xlink:href="https://perlbrew.pl/">perlbrew</link> or similar tools. Often, using the system perl directly is not recommended anyway.</para>
<para>I hesitate to lower the requirement to 5.10, and then to 5.8 or possibly even lower. 5.12 is already generous enough. Someone told me that <link xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds">Linus Torvalds</link> once said that his main responsibility as the chief maintainer of the Linux kernel project is to "Say no". This is one case where I wish to do exactly that.</para>
<para>I added a "use 5.012;" statement so Dist::Zilla can make the Kwalitee / CPANTS (see <link xlink:href="https://cpants.cpanauthors.org/">https://cpants.cpanauthors.org/</link> ) metrics better (minimum perl version). Reducing it further would have meant that I&#8217;d have to: 1. Risk test failures for 5.8 and 5.10. 2. Risk having to support end users with these old perl versions. All this is something I don&#8217;t want to do as a precaution. Also see <link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/humour/fortunes/tinic.html#hamakor-discs-mozilla-1.1-1">the joke thread about using version 1.1 of the Mozilla browser</link>. You really should upgrade to a newer perl5.</para>
<para>To quote <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/user/JennaMarbles">Jenna Marbles</link> in <link xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ROZjaxT_0Hw">this video</link>, which I found really funny and has some NSFW monologue, but SFW imagery: "Fuck that!".</para>
<section xml:id="_supporting_organisations_with_strict_policies">
<info>
<title>Supporting Organisations With Strict Policies</title>
</info>
<para><link xlink:href="https://metacpan.org/author/PWBENNETT">Paul Bennett</link> writes in <link xlink:href="https://www.mail-archive.com/module-authors@perl.org/msg10638.html">this mailing list post</link> :</para>

<blockquote>
<para>
I have faced this question head-on with some of my modules.
</para>
<para>
My take is that there are many, many corporations version-locked to specific
"enterprise-grade" Linux distributions, and stuck with system Perls maybe as
old as 5.10, and potentially stuck with security policies that make solutions
like perlbrew difficult.
</para>
<para>
I try (when I can), therefore, to keep at least one version of my modules on
CPAN that will run on 5.10 (5.8.8 sometimes), even if the default / latest CPAN
version needs something newer for full functionality or higher performance or
greater readability, or whatever.
</para>
<para>
I may be alone in this, also, but whenever I clean up my PAUSE distributions ,
I try to leave the $v.0 and the latest $v.$last versions of every module, for
every major version $v of that module. This is in case anyone has a module (on
or off CPAN) that has some kind of version locking in their dependencies.
</para>
</blockquote>

<para>Well, I don&#8217;t have a lot of sympathy for organisations with non-productive
policies like that, but I suppose that if they really need that, then they can
afford to pay me for my time and trouble, or to implement any of the other
possible solutions.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="_paying_respect_to_the_perl5_porters">
<info>
<title>Paying respect to the perl5-porters</title>
</info>
<para>The <link xlink:href="https://lists.perl.org/list/perl5-porters.html">perl5-porters</link> actively
work to release new versions of the perl5 runtime with bug fixes (including
for security bugs), new features, new automated tests, new optimisations,
and other improvements, all while breaking as little backward compatibility as
possible and while handling the human part of the process, such as handling
bug reports, complaints, and discussion. Since the release of perl 5.12.0, a
new stable version of perl5 was released yearly every May or close to it.</para>
<para>They deserve a lot of appreciation, and I hereby admit that I love them all.
♥♥♥! Thanks!</para>
<para>Many perl5 and CPAN contributors went to great effort to create open source
solutions such as perlbrew or <link xlink:href="https://metacpan.org/pod/local::lib">local::lib</link> to facilitate using an up-to-date
version of perl5, so there is little excuse to avoid updating.</para>
<para>As a result, while you are free to make use of older perl5 releases (while
risking suffering from many potential bugs), I think it is unfair if you
complain that CPAN authors like me set the minimum bar higher than
5.8.x/5.10.x. If you really need my distributions to work on your
old perl5 releases, then please implement one of the suggestions below.</para>
</section>
</section>

<section xml:id="_the_payment_terms">
<info>
<title>The payment terms</title>
</info>
<para>I request a payment of 100 USD per year per distribution, to make me support
perl versions 5.8.x-or-above — not just for you — for everybody. At the end of the year,
if I don&#8217;t get a term renewal, I may continue to support the older versions,
or I may not.</para>
<para>Note that you may opt to be credited as supporters of the distribution, in its
documentation.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="_alternative_options_to_paying">
<info>
<title>Alternative Options To Paying</title>
</info>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>Use perlbrew</para>
<para>See <link xlink:href="https://perlbrew.pl/">perlbrew</link> .</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Apply a downstream patch.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Fork it under a different name.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Stop using it.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Or patch the reverse dependencies to use something else.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Take over PAUSE maintainership.</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>

<section xml:id="_references">
<info>
<title>References</title>
</info>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<link xlink:href="https://github.com/shlomif/perl-XML-SemanticDiff/issues/3">GitHub discussion</link>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<link xlink:href="https://www.nntp.perl.org/group/perl.module-authors/2018/08/msg10944.html">module-authors discussion</link>
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<link xlink:href="https://www.shlomifish.org/philosophy/psychology/changing-the-seldon-plan/">What does "if it ain&#8217;t broke, don&#8217;t fix it" really mean?</link>
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="_contact">
<info>
<title>Contact</title>
</info>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para><link xlink:href="https://metacpan.org/author/SHLOMIF">https://metacpan.org/author/SHLOMIF</link></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/me/contact-me/">http://www.shlomifish.org/me/contact-me/</link></para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para><link xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/meta/donate/">http://www.shlomifish.org/meta/donate/</link></para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
</article>
