<!-- Converted by db4-upgrade version 1.0 -->

<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0" xml:id="index"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    
    <info>
        <title>"Usability" of the Perl Online World for Newcomers</title>

        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <personname>
                    <firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
                    <surname>Fish</surname>
                </personname>
                <affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <email>shlomif@shlomifish.org</email>
                        <uri type="homepage" xlink:href="http://www.shlomifish.org/">Shlomi Fish's Homepage</uri>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
        </authorgroup>
        <copyright>
            <year>2003</year>
            <holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
        </copyright>
        <legalnotice xml:id="main_legal_notice">
            <para>
                This document is copyrighted by Shlomi Fish under the terms
                of the Open Publication License version 2.0 or greater, or 
                alternatively under the 
                <link xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution Unported License version 3.0</link> (or at your option any greater version of it).
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>540</revnumber>
                <date>2003-04-18</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Removed a paragraph that is less than accurate, added
                    a link to ESR's CatB, and refactored a few things.
                </revremark>
            </revision>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>536</revnumber>
                <date>2003-04-16</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Made the criticism against the inavailability of the 
                    O'Reilly core Perl documentation less blunt, and added
                    a suggestion for the www.perl.com site. Fixed some
                    typos.
                </revremark>
            </revision>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>535</revnumber>
                <date>2003-04-16</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    First Advogato Version.
                </revremark>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>

    </info>
    <section xml:id="me_as_a_perl_newbie">
        <info><title>Me as a Perl Newbie</title></info>

        <para>
            "Shlomi, it takes 10 years to learn UNIX. I want you to learn it 
            in a month". My future supervisor in a web publishing house I 
            switched jobs to, told me that and It'll be a cold day in hell 
            before I forget this quote. He also showed me Perl, telling me I
            can write a TCP/IP client in 5 lines and a TCP server in 10, which
            sounded very impressive and intriguing. So I set out to learn 
            UNIX and Perl.
        </para>

        <para>
            When I got to work I did not know UNIX as much as he could hope for,
            but with some help from the people around there I managed to get by.
            The year was 1996, it was the start of the Internet Boom and 
            everybody and his mother wanted a web-site. Perl 5 was there, and
            it was practically the only thing you could use on UNIX to write 
            CGI scripts, without completely losing your mind.
        </para>

        <para>
            I only had a Windows 3.11 at home, and so started learning Perl
            from all the POD documents cramped into one Acrobat Reader file.
            "On dry", as they say in Israel, without actually running it. I 
            understood some of it as it reminded me of C and BASIC which I knew 
            quite well. But still there were all these references to sed, awk,
            UNIX shells, and other things I did not know. Generally, they 
            assumed you knew what they were talking about.
        </para>
        <para>
            I started working there, and was able to get by with my little 
            knowledge of Perl and UNIX which accumulated quite quickly. I 
            remember asking my supervisor what regular expressions where all 
            about and he told me: "they are a mechanism to find patterns in 
            text". That was the enlightenment that made me able to use them
            on a regular basis.
        </para>
        <para>
            I fell in love with both UNIX and Perl. I was not much of a UNIX 
            guru and wrote what I now write in shell in Perl, and simply kept
            asking my supervisor (who was then a true UNIX guru even in today's
            standards), questions about how to do things. But I got by.
        </para>
        <para>
            Since then, with some breaks, I extended my knowledge of both Perl 
            and UNIX. (I was thrilled to find ActivePerl and use Perl 
            effectively on Win32 as well). Gradually, I learned about Modules 
            and Objects in Perl and then a lot of tips and shortcuts, and now
            use it very often. Even in the Technion, where I now study 
            Electrical Engineering, Perl proved to be a life saver. It is my
            favourite language by far, and would not replace it with anything 
            else.
        </para>
        <para>
            That's my story. Now let's move to the story of Mel Jones (short
            for Melissa but might as well be Melvin), a Perl newbie who wishes
            to get hold of Perl. When thinking about the usability of computer
            systems, it is helpful to think about a few imaginary figures,
            which one is almost certain there are many similar that exist in
            real-life. Mel is one of them, but as you'll see later she won't be
            the only one.
        </para>
        <para>
            Before I start let me say that I am indebted to Larry Wall, Tom
            Christiansen and all the other people who contributed to Perl
            and brought Perl so far. I did not come to bury Perl or the Perl 
            world in this article. I simply came to pass some constructive
            criticism and suggestions to further aid its public acceptance. 
            Perl is the nicest language I've seen so far, and I would highly
            recommend anyone to learn it.
        </para>
        <para>
            (I am also grateful to the Python, Ruby, Tcl, PHP, etc. crew for
            working on languages which can provide a viable alternative to 
            Perl in some cases and by some people. By all means, Perl is not
            suitable for anyone and for any purpose and I always appreciate a
            healthy competition.)
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="story_of_mel">
        <info><title>The Story of Mel</title></info>
        
        <para>
            Who is Mel? She may be an experienced C programmer, or has some
            working knowledge with Visual Basic, JavaScript or ASP. In any
            case, she does not know Python, Ruby, Lisp, Tcl or PHP. (such
            people will usually have little problem learning Perl). Mel got a
            new job: be it as a system administrator, CGI programmer,
            Bio-informatics engineer, hardware designer, QA engineer or
            whatever. She wishes to do something that seems awfully hard with
            what she already knows, asks around and receive a simple answer
            "Perl would be perfect for it. And it is spelled P.E.R.L" 
        </para>
        <para>
            So Mel goes on looking for this strange and perfect language 
            called "perl" (without the 'a'). Where does she go first?
            <link xlink:href="http://www.google.com/">Google</link>? Most probably. 
            What does she discover? www.perl.com is the first hit. An 
            overcrowded site with a lot of O'Reillyisms with several articles
            that are way over her head. Perl Mongers is the second hit. She
            reads on - groups of Perl users - goodie. Now if she knows how to 
            use E-mail (she may or may not have such a good net-wisdom), she 
            may have hit the jackpot, because most Perl monger groups are very 
            friendly to newbies. Then she discovers CPAN (Mel 
            says: "What is it and why do I need it?"). ActiveState (a 
            commercial site which may or may not scare her) and Use Perl, which 
            is a nice site for Perl News, but she is naturally interested in 
            the Perl's status quo.
        </para>
        <para>
            She refines her query: "learn perl", "begin perl", "perl newbie"
            or "perl beginners". The concentrated site for perl beginners is
            <link xlink:href="http://learn.perl.org/">learn.perl.org</link>. It 
            contains some reviews of books (which Mel may not have time to
            read), a free online book (again, same issue) and no links to 
            tutorials whatsoever. IMHO, the site's visual side is also very 
            lacking and she may come to believe it is a sub-standard site as
            a result.
        </para>
        <para>
            OK. Maybe Mel was given the Llama book on the first day of her job
            as a gesture from her employer. Maybe this employer has these books
            online on his intranet for everybody to see. (there are also
            illegal or unfirewalled mirrors of these books, but let's suppose
            Mel is a lawful citizen who respects copyrights.) The question
            still stands: why do you need a book to learn Perl? Why can't you
            learn it from the Internet alone? Why kill trees, when you can
            simply transfer electrons from place to place to study it?
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the_situation_today">
        <info><title>The Situation Today</title></info>
        
        <para>
            When Larry Wall and others started hacking on Perl 5 (which was a
            complete rewrite and complete re-design of the defunct perl4), they
            expected it to be used for system administration tasks, for text
            processing and maybe to automate a few network tasks. The Internet
            Boom wanted otherwise, and several other technological explosions
            saw in Perl a suitable language for its tasks. Nowadays, Perl (and
            similar languages such as Python, PHP, Ruby or Tcl) are used for
            tasks as diverse as the computer world itself. Server-side-
            scripting, Bio-informatics, System Administration, Text Processing,
            System Tools, Graphical User-Interface, Computational Programming,
            Quality Assurance, automating Internet services (for good or worse)
            and even real-world applications and Games, are all written in
            Perl, Python and everything else. Some Killer apps of this kind
            include: Slash (the back-end of Slashdot), SourceForge/GForge,
            Bugzilla, Zope, PySol, The Mandrake Linux System Tools and
            Installer, <link xlink:href="http://www.frozen-bubble.org/">Frozen Bubble</link> (;-)), SpamAssassin, and many other things
            I don't recall or forgot about momentarily. Furthermore, a lot of
            code of such languages is used internally and not exposed to the
            world, and plays a large role behind the scenes.
        </para>
        <!-- To do: hyperlink -->
        <para>
            They are still often referred to as "scripting languages", but this
            term can no longer accurately describe them. While a Java-obsessed
            friend of mine asked me to give him an example for a proprietary 
            application of a large codebase that is written in Perl, and I
            could only think of open-source ones, it is definitely enterprise
            ready, and not a toy language for hackers anymore.
        </para>
        <para>
            Now, let's go back to Mel. She needs to learn Perl. But she might
            as well have been told to learn PHP, Python, Visual Basic or
            whatever. My problem is I think she would have a much harder time
            with Perl than with the others. No, it's not because Perl is a
            harder <emphasis>language</emphasis> than the others. I don't think
            it is. It's because the resources available online are inadequate
            or may scare her. And as <link xlink:href="http://www.perl.com/pub/a/2001/05/29/tides.html">Casey
                West noted in a previous attempt at correcting the
                situation</link>, the Perl community is relatively hostile to
            newbies and does not put up with them as much as those that are
            friendly would hope.
        </para>
        <para>
            Here is what I think are the problems with it:
        </para>
        <section xml:id="concentration_of_effort">
            <info><title>Concentration of Effort and Elitism</title></info>
            
            <para>
                I did my best to help newbies welcome in Perl. I actually like 
                beginners, and have a lot of patience to them, because I know
                no one is born with an innate knowledge of Perl, UNIX or 
                whatever. I often work in the Technion farms and whenever 
                I overhear that someone has a problem my ears become pointed, 
                and I cry "do you need help?" And then show him how to do 
                something that for me may be perfectly obvious. Seriously. I 
                simply enjoy doing that. 
            </para>
            <para>
                I also took some proactive effort in the direction. I wrote the
                <link xlink:href="http://vipe.technion.ac.il/~shlomif/lecture/Perl/Newbies/">Perl
                    for Perl Newbies</link> lecture series for the Haifa Linux
                Club. I wrote them
                with absolute beginners in mind, and decided to teach a very
                small subset of Perl step by step, with assumption that people
                will read the man pages afterwards. (and be able to understand
                them better then).                
            </para>
            <para>
                Lately, out of frustration with the learn.perl.org site, I started
                working on <link xlink:href="http://perl-begin.berlios.de/">my 
                    own version of a Perl beginners site</link>. Now here is where
                things went a bit wrong in my opinion. However, I don't want
                to defame anyone so I'll summarize. Both the 
                <link xlink:href="http://use.perl.org/">use.perl.org</link>'s editor 
                and a very prominent Perl figure that stumbled upon the site,
                believed that I should merge my work with learn.perl.org. At
                first, I thought it was a good idea, but then discover I 
                am unable to contact the learn.perl.org workers and that 
                their mailing lists was closed for subcription.
            </para>
            <para>
                Regardless, what's wrong with two Perl beginners site on the
                Internet? If I feel that learn.perl.org is inadequate, why
                should my effort be frowned upon? If we take PHP or Visual
                Basic for example, than everyone and his mother have a PHP
                portal where users can post questions (sometimes without
                subscribring), receive answers, read tutorials and see code
                snippets. Same for Visual Basic, despite the fact that it is
                proprietary. I want the same for Perl! I don't want a couple of
                concentrated perl.org and perl.com and oreillynet.com sites. I
                want a real network of independant sites!
            </para>
            <para>
                It also demonstrates the Perl community's elitism. I don't know
                how it came into being. For example, when I log into EF-Net,
                the channel #perl displays a long title that reads something
                like: "Not a Helpdesk! No CGI/WWW/Net::IRC/FAQ.". OK, there's
                also #perlhelp where such questions are accepted. But here are
                two facts from a user interface designer point of view:
            </para>
            <para>
                <orderedlist inheritnum="ignore" continuation="restarts">
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                        People are not going to read the title. In a user 
                        interface, you are lucky if people read anything at 
                        all. (including: "Delete and Expunge 'My most 
                        important work'?")
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>
                        Newbies by nature will try #perl if they log into a 
                        random IRC server. And they don't want to get flamed
                        for being off-topic there.
                    </para>
                    </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
            </para>
            <para>
                In short, this is a bad UI design. If the Perl gurus so desire
                not to be disturbed by newbie questions, they should move to 
                #perlgurus or #perlelite or #perlcafe or whatever. But they
                should not make claim for #perl.
            </para>
            <para>
                In another IRC network, I (not a newbie by far) was kicked
                because I pasted a URL and said the word CGI. (there's a nasty
                pattern bot there). Some other time, I was kicked out of
                #perlhelp, because I said the built-in function hex() converts
                numbers from hexadecimal to decimal, while a moderator believed
                it converts them <emphasis>to</emphasis> hexadecimal. 
                Naturally I was right (Run
                perldoc -f hex), but still instead of arguing with me, he
                kicked me out. Why should a bit of disinformation hurt if there
                are enough good people to correct it on the IRC as well? And
                Newbies can learn a lot from such discussions.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="lack_of_adequate_resources">
            <info><title>Lack of Adequate Online Resources</title></info>
            
            <para>
                Let's face it: at the moment, there aren't too many good Perl
                tutorials online. Many people who ask trivial questions are
                being conveyed something like "Read the Llama Book, the Camel 
                Book, the Black Panther book, the Perl Cookbook, and then 
                you'll know how to convert a file to lowercase." Maybe I'm 
                exagerrating a little, but it seems people are so content with
                the books that they don't seem to think people who don't want 
                them, cannot afford to buy them, or don't have time for them,
                are worthy of learning Perl.
            </para>
            <para>
                I don't have anything against people trying to make money off 
                Perl by selling books. But these people are the same people 
                who are the Perl project leaders, and so are responsible to 
                make sure Perl is well-documented. If people get frustrated
                learning Perl, and become unhappy with it, they will criticize
                "Perl". Not the Perl documentation. Not the Perl community.
                Not even the Perl leaders. <emphasis>"Perl"</emphasis>.
                If Larry Wall et al. care enough about Perl, they should make
                sure it has good online documentation. They don't have to do 
                it themselves, as a simple call for action by a very prominent
                Perl figure will do. (in accordance to Eric Raymond's 
                <link xlink:href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/cathedral-bazaar/">"The Cathedral and the Bazaar"</link>)
            </para>
            <para>
                If we take a look at Python or PHP for instance, then they 
                have excellent online documentation, which is very useful for 
                most if not all newbies. No need to read a book or take a 
                course. Just surf the Internet on your ADSL connection, install
                a few things on your Windows machine, and presto! You know PHP 
                or Python or Ruby. I seriously doubt if it can be done with 
                Perl with the same ease.
            </para>
            <para>
                I am grateful for Simon Cozens for making his "Beginning Perl"
                book online for free. I did not take a thorough look at the 
                book, but it is more encompassing than anything I've seen. But 
                even one book is not enough. People still want step by step 
                tutorials and things they can cut and paste code out of and 
                tinker it to do something. 
            </para>
            <para>
                When are books that cover a Technology something that I find
                legitimate? When they are not absolutely needed. I learned
                the Perl DBI by reading the man page and the online site and
                asking a few questions. Some people do not like man pages too
                much and would rather buy a book that covers Perl DBI. That's
                OK, and there may be a few fine points of working with DBI that
                I missed with what I call my "bottom-up learning".
            </para>
            <para>
                Such books need not be available online if their authors so
                much don't desire. However, Perl is very hard to learn from
                public electronic resources alone. I believe there may even
                be a clash of interests because the core Perl people also
                write them and so may not have enough motivation to improve
                the online documentation. Making them public will resolve that.
            </para>
            <para>
                That aside, I also believe that making it available online will
                not dent their sales much. I still would like to buy the Camel
                Book (which I borrowed from the local Perl Mongers library),
                and loved regardless if it's online so I can read it at bed
                time and stuff. And I generally have no problems using a
                computer book or tutorial.
            </para>
            <section xml:id="lack_of_adequate_mailing_lists">
                <info><title>Lack of Adequate Mailing Lists</title></info>
                
            <para>
                Then there are the mailing lists. I think (but am not sure) 
                that most Perl Mongers mailing lists will gladly accept 
                questions from newbies and answer them kindly. I know this is
                the case for <link xlink:href="http://www.perl.org.il/">Israel.PM</link>. 
                As a general rule
                Perl Mongers should make sure that the newbies mailing list 
                would be the first list they see on the site, or try to 
                subscribe to. Again, good user-interface design.
            </para>
            <para>
                The Perl Beginners list In my opinion is a bit useless. It is 
                very high volume, and usually whenever one considers
                replying to a question, it receives three replies by the time
                he finished composing it. I was also subscribed and it was
                too high volume to be effective for me as a "guru". I believe
                newbies will not be able to handle such volumes either. Unless
                they can configure their mail readers to filter only their own
                threads, which I'm not sure they can. Perl can do that, but
                they need to know it first.
            </para>
            <para>
                Like I said earlier, I think distributism is the key to our
                success here. Just like there are many scientific journals with
                very similar names and themes, (sometimes, "Physics A",
                "Physics B", "Physics C" etc), so there should be several
                international Perl beginners sites, each with his own mailing
                list for beginners. Gurus will subscribe to one or more sites
                and answer questions there, and newbies won't have to
                excessively use their delete button. Gradually, each such
                community will have a different atmosphere, and we will get a
                more diversified Perl world. (we all agree that diversity is
                good, right? If you don't you should program in Python)
            </para>
        </section>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="substandard_standard_doc">
            <info><title>Substandard Standard Documentation</title></info>
            
            <para>
                Let's face it, the man pages (or perl*.pod), which are the 
                definitive resource on the exact behaviour of Perl are very 
                bad. Maybe they were OK for expert Perl 4 or Tcl hackers, or 
                those that knew UNIX shells, sed and awk well. But nowadays 
                we can expect people to come even without knowledge of the 
                DOS or Windows command line, much less UNIX wizardry. 
            </para>
            <para>
                Perl is not and cannot be a "point-and-click-no-think"
                language. I'm not going to fall into the trap of trying to make
                it so. Even the lamest GUI kiddie eventually learns to
                invoke a text editor and write some glue code for whatever he
                needs to get a web-site or whatever working. Perl is much too
                powerful, to be something like ASP, where you can write wizards
                to perform most common tasks. In Perl, you can in one script,
                write a full application. This is something that while perhaps 
                possible in ASP, it was not intended to do.
            </para>
            <para>
                Still, the fear of writing code and thinking in terms of 
                variables, functions, objects, modules and other abstractions
                is not something that for people above a certain age is easy 
                to overcome. Visual Basic for Applications is one of the things
                I like most in Excel, but most people don't know it, and most
                books don't teach it. Why? Because it involves actual coding 
                and people don't like that. Ironically, it's very useful, too.
            </para>
            <para>
                Now, a documentation should guide a newbie step by step
                and explains: what is a variable? what is a scalar? what is a 
                number? what is a string? how they convert into each other? 
                What is an array and what it is good for? Same for hash, 
                object, etc. All these things may have different semantics
                in Perl than in most other languages. And all these things
                need to be explained clearly and reasonably, without depending
                on an analogy to tools that are way over Mel's head at her
                current position.
            </para>
            <para>
                I don't want this knowledge to be hidden from the world in some
                proprietary O'Reilly books. I did my best to remedy it, and
                Simon Cozens did even more. I think the reason people think
                Perl is such a poor language to learn or even for complete
                beginners, is not because of the syntax and semantics
                themselves, but because of its poor documentation. That put
                aside, I think publishers making their books available online,
                will only help them sell more books (assuming these books are
                good, of course).  Otherwise it's similar to buying an
                apartment without seeing it first.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="too_much_hubris">
            <info><title>Too Much Hubris</title></info>
            
            <para>
                Hubris is one of the three great virtues of the programmer
                according to Larry Wall. But he <link xlink:href="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/opensources/book/larry.html">also noted in "Open Sources"</link>
                that humility was a good quality as well. Don't get me wrong
                some projects have much more hubris than Perl: Python and Linux
                come to mind. I'm not saying all Pythoneers or Linuxers are
                hubris-ful. But a small minority is too loud, and there's
                a similar case in Perl to a lesser extent.
            </para>
            <para>
                What do I mean by hubris? "Perl is the greatest language since
                sliced bread. It has unparalleled text processing and data
                strucutres support. It is object-oriented, supports functional
                programming and any other programming paradigm very well. It's
                perfect for almost any task, from powering web-sites to writing
                GUI to writing games. It's practically LISP with in-fix 
                notation, and runs on almost any platform imaginable..." 
            </para>
            <para>
                You get the drift? Why I think it's bad? Because most
                people don't like communities with this sales pitch. When 
                recommending Perl to someone, you should discuss one advantage
                at a time, not overload him with a lot of information. When
                people see a lot of information they think there's something
                fishy about this.
            </para>
            <para>
                Let's take a look at a language with just the right amount of
                hubris: Visual Basic. Right, a language that Microsoft has 
                released several versions of, each adding major things, but 
                is still inferior to perl 5.000. A language whose code can 
                only be deployed on Windows. A language that is many times 
                useless without a whole slew of OCX or OLE components that
                are freely available at best. Still, Microsoft and the other
                VB community do not claim it's the greatest language on earth.
                "I take your word that Perl/Python/Ruby/LISP/whatever is much
                superior. VB is stupid, but cute and it gets the job done."
                That's the attitude we should have: Perl gets the job done.
                Granted, many different jobs. But as far as Mel is concerned
                it only gets her job done and not the entire world's ones.
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="the_threat">
        <info><title>What's the threat?</title></info>
        
        <para>
            You can often hear opinions or wonderings in the vein of: will PHP
            kill Perl? Will Python kill Perl? Will Java kill Perl? Will FooLang
            kill Perl? I don't think anyone of them can hope to. I don't think 
            Perl will completely eliminate any of them either, but I think 
            Perl's status is secured.
        </para>
        <para>
            Perl is too syntactically and semantically rich a language to be 
            abandoned by all its loving users in such a haste. CPAN is also
            a big plus for Perl, which while being a purely technical mechanism
            makes Perl more suitable for some tasks than most of its other 
            competitors. I hope to see equivalents in other languages, but it 
            will take some time and a lot of work from some very determined 
            individuals to get it up.
        </para>
        <para>
            The Perl Culture has extended way beyond its use. From perl poetry
            to Perl golf, to the talks by Larry Wall and other of the very
            interesting Perl personalities. The Perl community is alive and
            kicking and proud of being such. While some people abandon it for
            Python, Ruby or whatever, most of them still think Perl is a nice
            language, and don't abandon it or completely or completely 
            antagonize it. The beauty of the Perl culture is that it's about 
            using the right tool for the job whether in Perl or not.
        </para>
        <para>
            We all know 80% of the users use 20% of the features of a given
            program. However, as <link xlink:href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/fog0000000020.html">Joel
                Spolsky identified</link> they often use a differnet set of
            features. Perl's feature-set is huge, but you can survive with
            knowing maybe 10% or even less of it. Moreover, you can gradually
            learn more and more features and keep learning new ones. Perhaps
            only the three authors of Programming Perl know the entire feature
            set, and I believe even they are actively unaware of some obscure
            details of it. However, one always feels he's getting closer to
            100%.
        </para>
        <para>
            The problem is that Mel is not concerned with any of it. She just
            wants to write a program. This program may just as effectively be
            written with Python or Ruby or PHP. And we should be concerned with
            her writing it in Perl, because otherwise, it will take her more 
            time to get to learn Perl. As much as I care about the quality of
            Perl programmers (which is actually quite good) I also think we 
            should evangelize it to many people who'll find it useful. 
        </para>
        <para>
            Moreover, I don't like Mel becoming one of those characters who say:
            "Perl? This horrible language? I'm using PHP/Python/Ruby/Java. It's 
            much better than Perl." I don't think there's a way to exactly 
            measure which language is "better". Some languages are better in
            some regards and for some purposes than others. But Perl is much
            more than a language. It's a culture and a philosophy.
        </para>
        <para>
            Perl has a lot of potential for Mel. Alternatively, it has such for
            Joanna Simpson, a CEO of a Fortune 500 firm who is trying to
            ship her automobile-company's new car model. I think we should
            even try to teach Joanna Perl, because not only will she learn how
            great a language it is, but it may actually be useful for her in
            her day for day work. Otherwise, she would tell Robert, her
            secretary, to sort all the files into several directories a week
            from now, which can otherwise be done with a 10-liner Perl script.
            This will leave Robert enough time to answer phone calls and play
            <link xlink:href="http://www.frozen-bubble.org/">Frozen Bubble</link> 
            (which is written in Perl) in between: things that Perl or any 
            other software cannot do for him.
        </para>
        <para>
            Perl should be everywhere. Let's not ruin the day for Mel, Joanna 
            or Robert by a bad attitude. Remember that at a time, we were not
            much more educated than them. Not even old time UNIX gurus like
            Ken Thompson or Larry Wall can claim that, because UNIX and Perl 
            developed based on input by many people and everyone was always 
            surprised by new developments. While the effort was concentrated,
            the ideas flowed from everywhere.
        </para>
        <para>
            Furthermore helping newbies is <emphasis>fun</emphasis> and makes
            you feel good. You don't have a moral obligation to do so, but I
            believe you'll find helping someone even with a trivial question
            even more enjoyable then getting help for something that bothered
            you. That's how the open-source world works.
        </para>
        <para>
            You may eventually find yourself in a similar situation in
            something else entirely, and may need help by people who are more
            expert than you are.  During my Electrical Engineering studies I
            studied things that were much less straightforward to me than
            either Perl or UNIX (which I don't consider easy either), and
            sometimes the help of the lecturers, the T.A.'s or fellow students
            proved crucial to understanding them. Moreover, explaining
            something to someone who grasps it much less than you, is the
            best way of learning (even better than actually experiencing with
            something yourself).  That's because when teaching someone, you
            have to think how to convey it using more basic knowledge in a
            strucutured way, and so understand it much better.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="what_should_be_done">
        <info><title>What we should do about it?</title></info>
        
        <para>
            Until now it has been a long rant with some sprinkled advice in
            between. Now let's get to the real action. Here is what I think
            should be done, in no particular order.
        </para>
        <section xml:id="what_should_establish_something">
            <info><title>Independant Activitity</title></info>
            
            <para>
                Establish your own Perl beginners site/portal/mailing 
                list/web forum/etc. learn.perl.org is not enough and
                neither is what I'm going to do. We need more and as
                many as possible.
            </para>
            <para>
                Note that if you feel that there isn't enough traffic
                or that you should merge with some other site - it's
                OK and you can do so. As always reason and experience
                are your best guidelines as there isn't a precise rulebook
                for surviving in real life.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="what_should_perl_guru">
            <info><title>Become your biggest Perl Guru</title></info>
            
            <para>
                Remember that the biggest Perl guru is 
                <emphasis>you</emphasis>. Not Larry Wall or Tom
                Christiansen or Damian Conway or whoever. That's 
                because none of them can dictate to you how to work
                with Perl, solve problems with it or with something 
                else, etc. As much as I appreciate their efforts at
                making Perl better and more usable, I don't think 
                they have or should have a monopoly on where Perl is 
                going to. The world is your oyster.
            </para>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="what_should_help_newbies">
            <info><title>Treat Beginners Nicely and Help Them</title></info>
            
            <para>
                Be kind to newbies, answer them accurately, don't 
                confuse them and try to use Perl that is as simple
                and non-idiomatic as possible (e.g: for the file's 
                lowercasing example, don't use Tie::File, and prefer
                lc() over tr///).
            </para>
            <para>
                If you don't have the time to write the entire code
                for the beginner - politely tell him you can't
                help him at this point or whenever. Else, try to 
                actually write some code which would be as clear
                and commented as possible. Don't expect beginners
                to like Perl Golf snippets. They may mistake them
                for line noise. ;-)
            </para>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="what_should_ui_design">
                <info><title>Think about Usability Issues</title></info>
                
                    <para>
                        Think about the User-Interface Design of the System. 
                        What will the user assume? What would be the first
                        thing he'll do? What is he going to notice? What
                        is he going to ignore? What is he going to do
                        mechanically? These are all questions that
                        are as pertinent to IRC networks, programming 
                        languages or web-sites as they are to Microsoft Word.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        I gave the IRC channels examples of bad UI design. OK,
                        gurus, once upon a time there weren't too many newbies 
                        around. But if you don't want to completely reject them,
                        it is a better idea to move to a different channel.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        I believe the Perl Monks site also suffers from such a 
                        lacking design. First of all - its name. Do you 
                        honestly expect someone to be a Perl "monk" and live
                        in a Perl "monastry"? (I'm Jewish, an Atheist, and 
                        very sexually liberated for God's sake!) Secondly,
                        the site's design is unattrative, overcrowded and 
                        confusing. I remember I was reluctant from 
                        participating there, and had troubles understaning
                        what it was all about.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Web forums should involve no registration whatsoever 
                        (just fill in the name and E-mail), and not use too 
                        fancy a markup syntax, at least not by default. I 
                        actually saw a forum (not particularily Perl-related) 
                        where markups were placed in brackets, and I wanted to 
                        paste some Haskell code... I could not understand how 
                        to do it, no matter what I tried .
                    </para>
                </section>

                <section xml:id="what_should_create_resources">
                    <info><title>Create Archives of Perl Code and Documentation</title></info>
                        

                    <para>
                        Publish some of your Perl code online. Establish a 
                        Wiki. Don't ask anybody for permission - just do it.
                        There will be chaos first, but order will emerge out 
                        of it eventually. And if not, Google and friends will 
                        like us better. ;-)
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Rik van Riel of the Linux Kernel fame, told me and some
                        IRC folks about a system which was written for internal
                        use by Connectiva (his former workplace), that uses a
                        <link xlink:href="http://dmoz.org/">DMoz</link>-like
                        category tree, where Slashdot-like comments are added.
                        This sound like a nice integration of a few ideas. The
                        Connectiva code is written in PHP and is not ready for
                        release.  Nevertheless, I think tweaking <link xlink:href="http://www.slashcode.com/">Slash</link> to do
                        just that should not be too hard, and may prove as a
                        useful alternative or a complement to Wikis.
                    </para>
                </section>
                <section xml:id="what_should_charge_money_say_no">
                    <info><title>Don't be afraid to charge money or say no</title></info>
                    
                    <para>
                        Let's suppose that despite all the positive changes and
                        having a book nearby, Mel feels she needs a face to face
                        guidance. She asks around her workplace, and discovers
                        a fellow worker, by the name of Rachel Southern (
                        actually a character in a story I'm writing who fits 
                        perfectly here) is a first-class perl guru. Rachel has
                        been programming since she was 14, knows UNIX, Perl
                        and many other languages well, and is a very nice, 
                        sociable person. So Mel asks Rachel if she can tutor
                        her in Perl.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Rachel, however, being the expert that she is, is busy
                        with work, and prefers to spend her weekends relaxing,
                        socializing (online and in real life), and hacking on 
                        open-source projects. Moreover, she lives very far
                        from Mel's apartment. So she tells Mel that if she 
                        wishes to go to Mel's apartment on a Saturday or a 
                        Sunday, and tutor her with Perl (or UNIX in general),
                        Mel would have to pay her a substantial amount of money
                        per hour. Mel accepts, as she realizes the help she'll 
                        get out of Rachel, will help her in her work, which in
                        turn will be very well worth the money.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Was Rachel "greedy" or "unfriendly" in asking for 
                        money? No. I was told a technician in Israel
                        charges $50 an hour. Many lawyers and other 
                        professionals will charge much 
                        more. The time of compotent persons is 
                        the most precious resource on our planet (except 
                        perhaps for human rationality), and Rachel has no
                        selfish interest to spend so much time helping Melissa.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        I was criticizing the fact that books costed money and
                        were not available online only because the reproduction
                        of books in Electronic form is zero. But a time a 
                        person spends helping another one is priceless. Now,
                        if Mel lived in the same block as Rachel, or otherwise
                        they were very good friends, then Rachel could have 
                        chosen to reject the payment. (My friend and I lost 
                        track of how even we are regarding the pizzas we ate
                        and we could not care less about this fact).
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        It is true that Richard Stallman (RMS) travels around
                        the world visiting various free software user groups,
                        at the cost of the travelling expenses alone. He have
                        also consistently answered the E-mails of me and
                        everyone else I know, and is available by phone most
                        of the time.
                        However, Stallman's purpose in life is propagating free
                        software and he is the spiritual father of the free
                        software and open source movement. As such, he accepts
                        the fact that he has become a saint and does not charge
                        money for that. As he once told me and some other
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.iglu.org.il/">IGLU</link>'ers:
                        "Advocacy is everything I do".
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Most of us, however, are trying to make the best use 
                        of our time, including getting the bills payed or 
                        contributing to free software. As such, our time is
                        precious enough so a substantial amount of it that is
                        used to help a less capable peer will cost money. It 
                        does not mean that spending some time for writing a 
                        straightforward ten-liner for someone should, though. 
                        (in that case, there's usually no way to acquire the 
                        money in the first place)
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        There's a limit to anything. I remember that once
                        I hanged on the IRC, and someone there showed me a
                        bot he or his clique wrote in mIRC-script and wanted
                        to convert to Perl. The bot was a bit complex, so
                        I told him I did not want to convert it, as I had
                        no selfish interest in getting it ported. I suggested
                        him to learn Perl and do the porting himself. He
                        understood. I'm not sure the bot was ever ported, but 
                        the Gods help only those that help themselves.
                    </para>

                </section>
                <section xml:id="what_should_revamp_of_existing">
                    <info><title>Revamp of the existing resources</title></info>
                    
                    <para>
                        Like I noted earlier, I believe many of the existing
                        resources, while being perfectly fine for veterans
                        may scare away newbies. www.perl.com is crowded with
                        too many links, too much content, and too much 
                        oreillynetism. Since it is the first hit on Google, it
                        should be a decent page where newbies can easily find
                        their way in. Something like 
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.python.org/">the Python 
                            Homepage</link> or 
                        <link xlink:href="http://www.php.net/">PHP's</link>. Plain,
                        simple and effective. (note that I don't have a problem
                        with the O'Reilly Net format as a general rule, it's 
                        just not suitable for newbies who may have never heard
                        of O'Reilly or do not have the time to put up with it.)
                        The Python.org site, for instance, contains just the 
                        right links for a newbies and nothing more. It has
                        a rather cheesy site, but it is much more usable than 
                        www.perl.com. The latter has links to a host of 
                        other O'Reilly sites (what for), some articles that are
                        way over Melissa's head, no explanation of what Perl is
                        all about, links to many O'Reilly books (again: why?), 
                        and is generally overcrowded with information. This is
                        not a community site. It is practically a blunt 
                        promotion of everything O'Reilly!
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        www.perl.com as it is can be renamed as 
                        perl.oreilly.com or whatever. But otherwise, O'Reilly
                        should not make a claim for the homesite of the Perl
                        language and Perl community as they are not the only
                        player in the game.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Also, I kindly ask the authors and publishers of the 
                        core Perl books to place them online. If a
                        book teaches you advanced things that you can learn on
                        your own, that do not absolutely require a book (like 
                        Damian Conway's "Object Oriented Perl"), then putting
                        it online would not be necessary, but still a nice 
                        gesture. However, it cannot be said on "Programming 
                        Perl" (the Camel Book), "Learning Perl" (the 
                        Llama Book), the Perl Cookbook, or "Advanced Perl". 
                        I could not care less however, for "Perl for Oracle 
                        DBAs", because it's highly specialized and of no 
                        interest to Melissa or Robert. Rachel can easily learn
                        it on her own should the need arise, and Joanna's 
                        knowledge of Perl should not extend to this 
                        speciality.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        There are other popular sites or resources, that 
                        may seem quite hostile to newbies. Perl Monks is one.
                        use.perl.org should actually be quite good. Its 
                        standard Slashdot-like seemingly-underground look can 
                        actually appeal to newbies who wish to keep up to date
                        with Perl news. What the editors should do is answer 
                        newbie submissions themselves should there be such,
                        and <emphasis>only then</emphasis> tell them that it's
                        the wrong place to ask. Remember, people don't read 
                        Submission Guidelines or whatever, and even I act 
                        mechanically on many web-sites. (don't you?)
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        Generally, if one of the new resources would be better
                        than the existing ones, then it would eventually 
                        supercede it. Yahoo and AltaVista were superceded to 
                        most extents by the much superior and more 
                        user and community friendly Google and Mozilla 
                        Directory, and we should not fear a healthy 
                        competition either. We should not concentrate our 
                        efforts, because we will also reduce the number of 
                        people doing them in the first place. And as Eric 
                        Raymond noted in "The Cathedral and the Bazaar", in a 
                        distributed Bazaar model, the output grows linearily 
                        to the number of people involved.
                    </para>
                    <para>
                        While the Perl's source code was maintained in a very 
                        much Bazaar-like way, the Perl Community has been
                        relatively Cathedral like looking for a selected small
                        number of shrines. Let's change that.
                    </para>
                </section>
            </section>
            <section xml:id="conclusion">
                <info><title>Conclusion</title></info>
                
                <para>
                    Perl is going strong and will continue to grow in the 
                    nearby future. However, many beginners are deterred from
                    becoming part of the Perl world, or understanding it,
                    out of several defects in the online Perl community and
                    resources.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Perl proves to be a gateway to UNIX for many people. Many 
                    people who start to use a UNIX-compatible system (like 
                    Linux or Solaris) write their shell-scripts in Perl, and
                    later on actually learn shell programming. Many Windows 
                    people who used Perl for Win32, find the UNIX concept much
                    more desirable afterwards. Perl is a reflection of UNIX in
                    all so many ways, and I'd hate for someone to get scared
                    of UNIX as a result of getting scared of Perl too.
                </para>
                <para>
                    You often hear people complaining at Perl's briefness,
                    TIMTOWDIness, difficulty to learn, "inconsistency", "ugly
                    syntax", complexity, in-fix notation, size, dollar signs,
                    insuitability for large codebases, etc. All these "issues"
                    are very much marginal if not completely false in getting
                    it into public acceptance.  In fact it is a sign that it
                    has a culture that not all people can accept, which is
                    good, because not all people are the same in such ammoral
                    issues as choice of programming language.
                </para>
                <para>
                    However, what can deter someone from learning Perl is 
                    a lack of good support and aid from an online community,
                    which may be the only connection he has to this virtual
                    world called "Perl". Let's change it. Let's make sure
                    Melissa will be practically sucked into the Perl world,
                    as any community happy to receive a shining, new, 
                    interesting member.
                </para>
            </section>
</article>
