<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="product-syndication.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE comparison SYSTEM "product-syndication.dtd">
<!--
;;; To do:
* Add rellink’s.
;;; To add:
* Postfix TDG
* Refactoring by Fowler.
* The Pragmatic Programmer - From Journeyman to Master.
* The Algorithm Design Manual.
* chromatic’s Modern Perl Book.
* xUnit Test Patterns.
* Kent Beck’s Test Driven Development by Example
* The reviews I did on the Perl Mongers site.

    In the future:
    * CSS TDG
    * DNS & BIND.

-->
<product-syndication>
    <data>
        <cat id="books">
            <title>Shlomi Fish’s Non-Fiction Book Reviews</title>
            <desc appendtoc="1">
<p>
This is a list of books I have read and hereby review. At the moment, it is
focused on non-fiction, but I hope to add fiction later on in a different
section.
</p>

<p>
So if you’re looking for a good book to read, and are desperate enough to
take my advice (☺), look no further than here. Happy reading!
</p>

            </desc>
            <cat id="most_influential_non_fiction">
                <title>My Most Influential Books (in Chronological Order)</title>
                <desc>
                    <p>
                        This is a list of the four or so books that I found
                        the most influential on my thinking. It is given here
                        in the chronological order in which I read them.
                    </p>
                </desc>
                <prod id="innumeracy">
                    <title>Innumeracy - Mathematical Illiteracy and its Consequences</title>
                    <isbn>0809058405</isbn>
                    <creator type="author">John Allen Paulus</creator>
                    <desc>
<p>
This is a great book about how the fact that people don’t understand
Mathematics or don’t apply it well leads to various side-effects, such as
believing in superstition, irrational fears, or mis-approximations.
</p>
</desc>
                </prod>
                <prod id="neo_tech_discovery">
                    <title>The Neo-Tech Discovery by Frank R. Wallace and others</title>
                    <isbn disable="1" />
                    <desc>
<p>
This book is not available in book stores, but I believe it may be ordered by
mail order by requesting a catalogue
<a href="http://www.neo-tech.com/">from the Neo-Tech site</a>. It is also
available online as <a href="http://www.neo-tech.com/neotech/advantages/">the
Neo-Tech Advantages</a> and the
<a href="http://www.neo-tech.com/neotech/discovery/">the Selected Portions
from the Neo-Tech Discovery</a>.
</p>
<p>
This is the most influential book I ever read. Neo-Tech is an extension and
re-organization of
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Objectivist_philosophy">Ayn
Rand’s Objectivism</a>, that also integrates
Psychology, Business Practices, Science and other fields. After reading and
integrating this book, one can throw away all the mental garbage that prevents
growth, and no longer be influenced by various fallacies you constantly hear
and believe in.
</p>
<p>
Reading this document will make your mind think more clearly about the facts
of human existence, and remove any unnecessary guilt you have.
</p>
</desc>
                </prod>
                <prod id="feeling_good">
                    <title>Feeling Good: The New Mood Therapy</title>
                    <isbn>0380810336</isbn>
                    <creator type="author">David D. Burns</creator>
                    <desc>
<p>
This is a field guide to cognitive Psychology. It explains how our conscious
thoughts cause unnecessary mood swings, including depressions and euphorias.
It also gives practical measurements to correct one’s cognitive process, raise
one’s self-esteem, handle criticism, and recover from unnecessary mood swings.
</p>
<p>
This book can also help people maintain a good self-esteem, and understand
why people have mood swings. It is a very good anti-thesis to the traditional
Freudian or similar psychology that is very misleading. A highly recommended
read!
</p>
                    </desc>
                </prod>
                <prod id="cathedral_bazaar">
                    <title>The Cathedral &amp; The Bazaar: Musings on Linux and Open Source by an Accidental Revolutionary</title>
                    <isbn>0596001088</isbn>
                    <creator type="author">Eric S. Raymond</creator>
                    <desc>
<p>
<a href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/">This book is
also available online</a> on
<a href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/">Raymond’s Site</a>.
</p>
<p>
This book is a set of very mind-revolving essays about the Free and Open
Source Software world - their culture, conventions, customs; organizational,
cultural and economical conventions - and by inflection on Free/Open Culture
in general. It is a must read for every person living in the 21st century.
</p>
                    </desc>
                </prod>
            </cat>
            <cat id="other_non_fiction">
                <title>Other Book Reviews</title>
                <desc>
                    <p>
                        These are other books I am reviewing.
                        (in no particular order).
                    </p>
                </desc>
                <cat id="non_technical_books">
                    <title>Non-Technical Books</title>
                    <prod id="bicameral_mind">
                        <title>The Origin of Consciousness in the Breakdown of
                            the Bicameral Mind</title>
                        <isbn>0618057072</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Julian Jaynes</creator>
                        <desc>
<p>
This book presents a theory on the evolution of human consciousness that sounds
fantastic at first, but that the author backs with a lot of evidence.
Essentially, consciousness (or rather “sentience”) is a learned layer that is
not necessary for normal operation. Furthermore, all humans up to around
1300 BC were completely void of consciousness, when they developed it out
of necessity, starting at the Near East.
</p>
<p>
The book kept me entertained, and enlightened me.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>

                    <prod id="mythical_man_month">
                        <title>The Mythical Man-Month: Essays on Software Engineering</title>
                        <isbn>0201835959</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Frederick P.  Brooks</creator>
                        <desc>

                    <p>
                    This book, written over 20 years ago, by the project manager of IBM’s OS/360
                    is one of the classic texts on software engineering, and for a very good
                    reason. It still feels very fresh now, and supplies a lot of insights about
                    how to manage a software project. It will also prove of interest to managers
                    of other teams (that do not necessarily work on software).
                    </p>
                    <p>
                    The 20th anniversary edition, contains some later essays and conclusions by
                    the same author.
                    </p>


                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="design_of_everyday_things">
                        <title>The Design of Everyday Things</title>
                        <isbn>0465067107</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Donald A. Norman</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    A great book about designing for usability. Instead of covering software, it
                    covers everyday things like doors, taps or phones , and why or why not they
                    make sense. This book is amusing, insightful and makes a very good read.


                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="guns_germs_and_steel">
                        <title>Guns, Germs and Steel: The Fates of Human Societies</title>
                        <isbn>0393061310</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Jared Diamond</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    This books tries to answer the question of why did different human societies
                    evolve differently. It demonstrates that geography and bio-geography played
                    a big role in shaping the destinies of people in different places on our
                    planet. This book contains many interesting anecdotes, a wonderful theme, and
                    is a pleasure to read. Highly recommended.


                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="penguin_book_of_puzzles">
                        <title>The Penguin Book of Curious and Interesting Puzzles</title>
                        <isbn>0140148752</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">David Wells</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>
                    This book provides a wonderful collection of puzzles,
                    and brain-teasers, outlining their history, and various
                    interesting facts about them. It provides solutions at
                    the end.
                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="hackers_and_painters">
                        <title>Hackers and Painters: Big Ideas from the Computer Age</title>
                        <isbn>0596006624</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Paul Graham</creator>
                        <desc>
<p>
This is a collection of essays which appeared on
<a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/">the personal site Paul Graham</a>.
I highly enjoyed reading his essays and learned a lot from them. There
are some issues with his style of writing, and with some of his conclusions,
but as a whole, they are highly recommended.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="mathematics_and_humor">
                        <title>Mathematics and Humor: A Study of the Logic of Humor</title>
                        <isbn>0226650251</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">John Allen Paulos</creator>
                        <desc>
<p>
In this book, John Allen Paulos analyses some of the mathematics behind
humour, and what makes us laugh. A recommended read.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="I_think_therefore_I_laugh">
                        <title>I Think, Therefore I Laugh</title>
                        <isbn>0231119151</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">John Allen Paulos</creator>
                        <desc>
<p>
This book starts by quoting <a
href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_Wittgenstein">Wittgenstein</a>
that <q>A serious and good philosophical work could be written consisting
entirely of jokes</q>. This book goes on to demonstrate how such concepts
as logic, mathematics, science, and language are problematic and how
misapplying them can yield funny results.
</p>

<p>
This book features <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Groucho_Marx">Groucho
Marx</a>, as well as a host of imaginary placeholder characters such as
George, Waldo and Martha. I read it several times, and enjoyed it every time
I did.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="beyond_numeracy">
                        <title>Beyond Numeracy</title>
                        <isbn>067973807X</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">John Allen Paulos</creator>
                        <desc>
<p>
This book explains a little out of many subjects of mathematics, in
a very engaging way. I bought it and enjoyed it.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>

                </cat>
                <cat id="technical_books">
                    <title>Technical Books</title>
                    <prod id="programming_perl">
                        <title>Programming Perl</title>
                        <isbn>0596000278</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Larry Wall et al</creator>
                        <desc>

                    <p>
                    This is the canonical reference to the <a href="http://www.perl.org/">Perl
                    programming language</a> by some of its best and best-known experts. It covers
                    the entire Perl language as of perl-5.6.1, with any nuance and any
                    fine point being mentioned. Furthermore, it is a very entertaining read: the
                    style is lightweight and easy, and it is one of the funniest technical books
                    I’ve ever read.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                    Note that programmers who don’t know how to program Perl at all yet, cannot use it
                    in order to learn the language. Instead, it is
                    recommended, that they first learn Perl and only then
                    read “Programming Perl”. For learning Perl, see
                    <a href="http://perl-begin.org/">the Perl Beginners’
                        Site</a>. (Thanks to “infidel” from Freenode for
                    suggesting this.)
                    </p>


                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="computation_structures">
                        <title>Computation Structures</title>
                        <isbn>0262231395</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Stephen A. Ward &amp; Robert H. Halstead</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    A great book about logic design and how to construct a computer from very
                    basic elements. Also covers some layers above the digital circuits level,
                    but this material did not particularly interest me. I studied using this
                    book in two of my <a href="http://www.technion.ac.il/">Technion</a> courses,
                    and can highly recommend it.


                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="sicp">
                        <title>Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</title>
                        <isbn>0262011530</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Harold Abelson &amp; Gerald Jay Sussman</creator>
                        <desc>

                    <p>
                    An excellent book that teaches the basics of good software design using the
                    Scheme programming language. Introduces very interesting techniques, and
                    demonstrates how they can be useful for real-life tasks. I took two courses
                    in the Technion based on this book, and they also were very enlightening.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                    The text of this book and other related resources
                    <a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/">are available online on its site</a>.
                    </p>


                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="ui_design_for_programmers">
                        <title>User Interface Design for Programmers</title>
                        <isbn>1893115941</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Joel Spolsky</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    I really liked <a
                        href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/uibook/chapters/fog0000000057.html">the
                        online version of the book</a> when I read it on Joel’s
                    site, and the printed version contains several additional
                    chapters. This book is very funny, very enlightening, with
                    many screenshots and diagrams. It’s a must for anyone doing
                    GUI or Web design. Highly recommended.
                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="refactoring">
                        <title>Refactoring - Improving The Design of
                            Existing Code</title>
                        <isbn>0201485672</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Martin Fowler</creator>
                        <desc>
                            <p>

                                <a href="http://www.refactoring.com/">Refactoring</a>
                                is improving the internal design of a
                                code without changing its external
                                behaviour. This book is the definitive
                                guide to refactoring, at least in
                                object-oriented systems.
                            </p>

                            <p>

                                The first chapters of the book are rather
                                general. They introduce the motivation
                                for refactoring, why it is good, and why
                                it actually speeds up development.
                                Also, they also give a list of “bad smells” in the code that indicate that
                                a refactoring is needed (like
                                duplicate code or magic numbers). I found
                                the bad smells part to be the most
                                illuminating part of the book.

                            </p>

                            <p>
                                The middle part of the book which is its
                                lion’s share is a catalogue of various
                                refactorings. These are things like extracting
                                a method, creating a superclass, eliminating
                                inheritance, or creating one. The author
                                explains there each refactoring, when to do
                                it, the steps for performing it most safely,
                                and then usually gives an example of how to do
                                it. I found the catalogue a bit tedious to read,
                                but interesting nonetheless. It taught me some
                                new techniques that I was not previously aware
                                of.
                            </p>

                            <p>
                                The final chapters wrap up the book, and are
                                also interesting to read. They consist of an
                                essay by William Opdyke (who wrote a very
                                early research paper on refactoring) titled
                                “Refactoring, Reuse and Reality”, a chapter
                                about <a
                                    href="http://www.refactoring.com/tools.html">Refactoring
                                    Tools</a>, and a short summarising chapter
                                by Kent Beck.
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                The book smells a bit of hype: Java is used as
                                the example language (albeit its use
                                there is quite justified); there are
                                many UML diagrams (which were at first
                                confusing to me due to the many kind
                                of arrows they have); and there are
                                references of several of the so-called
                                Design Patterns. (from the Gang of
                                Four book and otherwise). But they
                                don’t detract much from an otherwise
                                good book.
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                The book can also
                                be used as a reference to look for
                                refactorings or see how can they be
                                performed well. I think this book has
                                made me more conscious of how I
                                refactor and write code, and I try to
                                refactor in a way that will minimize
                                the errors caused by it. I’m also now
                                more aware of the “two hats”, as
                                Fowler puts it, of either refactoring
                                code or adding new features.
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                To sum, this is a very good and
                                important book to read, especially for
                                beginning programmers. I’m just not
                                sure it justifies the $54.00 list
                                price. This price is too high for
                                a book of this scope.
                            </p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="art_of_unix_programming">
                        <title>The Art of UNIX Programming</title>
                        <isbn>0131429019</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Eric S. Raymond</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    A very nice book about the elements and know-how of planning and implementing
                    UNIX software. You can read
                    <a href="http://wiki.perl.org.il/index.php/Book_Review_-_The_Art_of_Unix_Programming_-_reviewed_by_Shlomi_Fish">a
                    more detailed review and critique</a> of this book by me, and also <a href="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/taoup/">read it online</a>.


                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="qmail_handbook">
                        <title>The qmail Handbook</title>
                        <isbn>1893115402</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Dave Sill</creator>
                        <desc>

                    <p>
                    A very good book about the <a href="http://qmail.org/">qmail mail
                    server</a>. Introduces the fundamental concepts of the server, and then
                    instructs how to operate it, and configure other software for it. One thing
                    to note about this book is that it convinced me that I should avoid using
                    qmail unless it’s already installed and has a configuration. qmail has a very
                    problematic license, lacks most necessary features out of the box, is no
                    longer maintained, has a very problematic creator and copyright owner, etc.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                    If you’re going to install a new mail server, take a look at
                    <a href="http://www.postfix.org/">Postfix</a>,
                    <a href="http://www.exim.org/">Exim</a>,
                    <a href="http://www.courier-mta.org/">Courier</a> or whatever. These are
                    open-source, are actively developed, and lack all of the aforementioned
                    problems. “The qmail Handbook”, however, is useful for those who need to
                    administer existing qmail configurations, or migrate them to a different
                    implementation. You can also take a look at
                    <a href="http://www.lifewithqmail.org/">Life with qmail</a> which is a guide
                    to qmail, by the same author.
                    </p>


                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="svg_programming">
                        <title>SVG Programming - The Graphical Web</title>
                        <isbn>1590590198</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Kurt Cagle</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    A great book about <a href="http://www.w3.org/Graphics/SVG/">SVG</a>
                    (= Scalable Vector Graphics), the emerging standard for vector graphics,
                    animation and interactive applets on the web. It explains the standard step
                    by step, with many nuances covered. The final chapters cover some advanced
                    techniques. Highly recommended.


                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="mastering_algos_with_perl">
                        <title>Mastering Algorithms with Perl</title>
                        <isbn>1565923987</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">John Macdonald, Jon Orwant and Jarkko Hietaniemi</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    I took a course about algorithms in <a
                        href="http://www.technion.ac.il/">the Technion</a>
                    before reading this book, and yet found this book to be
                    very interesting. This books covers a lot of different
                    fields and topics, each one with its own algorithms and
                    each can give you a taste of what this field does. This is
                    one of the best books I read in the O’Reilly series of Perl
                    books, but it’s not specifically about Perl. Highly
                    Recommended for Programmers.

                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="porting_unix_software">
                        <title>Porting UNIX Software</title>
                        <isbn>1565921267</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Greg Lehey</creator>
                        <desc>

                    <p>
                    When I started working in a Web Design company, UNIX systems were all we had
                    and the only thing we liked in order to give our clients a presence on the
                    Internet. However, we used a plethora of UNIXes: IRIX, SunOS 4.1.3, FreeBSD,
                    Linux, and there are many more flavours of UNIX out there. So I naturally
                    wondered what was the difference between them.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                    A co-worker recommended that in order to better understand what’s involved I
                    should read this book, and so I bought it from a local Israeli book store. I
                    did not regret buying it - this book is simply superb. Some chapters (such as
                    the one about handling terminal I/O) are of little interest to most
                    programmers, but as a general rule this book gives a lot of essential
                    information about how to write portable software.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                    Many Windows programmers write code and test it on their local machine, and
                    think it will be perfectly acceptable this way. But Windows is only one OS,
                    and the x86’s is only one processor architecture. In the UNIX world, there are
                    plenty of other operating systems and processor architectures. Often many
                    subtle problems can occur because of lack of knowledge of UNIX concepts.
                    </p>


                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="perl_journal_vol_1">
                        <title>Computer Science &amp; Perl Programming: Best of The Perl Journal</title>
                        <isbn>0596003102</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Various</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    The first installment in the series of three books containing a collection of
                    articles from “the Perl Journal”. Very nice book, with interesting articles.
                    You can <a href="http://www.perl.org.il/books/0596003102.html">read my review
                    of it</a> to the Perl mongers.


                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="perl_journal_vol_3">
                        <title>Games, Diversions &amp; Perl Culture: Best of the Perl Journal</title>
                        <isbn>0596003129</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Various</creator>
                        <desc>
                    <p>

                    The third installment in the series of three books containing a collection of
                    articles from “the Perl Journal”. As a whole it is very entertaining and
                    enlightening. You can <a href="http://www.perl.org.il/books/0596003129.html">read my review of it</a> to the Perl mongers.


                    </p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="higher_order_perl">
                        <title>Higher Order Perl: Transforming Programs with Programs</title>
                        <isbn>1558607013</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Mark Jason Dominus</creator>
                        <desc>

                    <p>
                    “Higher Order Perl” is both enjoyable and accessible. Mark Jason Dominus
                    demonstrates some techniques that originated from the LISP world and shows how
                    to implement them in Perl, and how they can be put into good use. I learned a
                    lot from this book: how currying, iterators and streams can be useful, how a
                    recursive descent parser can be implemented, and many other things.
                    </p>
                    <p>
                    Also see <a href="http://www.perl.org.il/books/1558607013.html">my review on
                    the Israeli Perl Mongers site</a>.
                    </p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>

                    <prod id="perl_hacks">
                        <title>Perl Hacks</title>
                        <isbn>0596526741</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">chromatic, with Damian Conway
                            and Curtis “Ovid” Poe</creator>
                        <desc>

<p>
I received this book as a token of appreciation for my contributions to
<a href="http://perladvent.pm.org/2006/">the 2006 Perl Advent Calendar</a>.
It’s the first book I read as part of the
<a href="http://www.oreilly.com/store/series/hacks.csp">O’Reilly Hacks’ series
of books</a>, and it proved to be a light yet informative and entertaining
read.
</p>

<p>
The book covers various useful “hacks” or small tricks that allow one to
achieve a lot of cool tasks when working with Perl. These tricks are unorthodox
and stretch the limit of one’s Perl knowledge. Since they require an advanced
knowledge and understanding of Perl, I would recommend this book only for Perl
experts. Some of the B:: using modules were even too high-level for me to
understand how they worked internally. However, I understood the purpose of the
code in all cases, even if I didn’t understand the code itself.
</p>

<p>
So it is a recommended read for people who’ve worked with Perl a lot,
and wish to learn many new and useful tricks. Perl Hacks for Perl hackers,
indeed!
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="perl_best_practices">
                        <title>Perl Best Practices</title>
                        <isbn>0596001738</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Damian Conway</creator>
                        <desc>

<p>
Once upon a time, someone I talked with on IRC suggested I create and publicise
a wishlist on Amazon.com so people can buy me gifts. I did so, and after a few
months someone ordered me both this book and  <a
href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/ASIN/0345348036/ref=nosim/shlomifishhom-20/">the
book “The Princess Bride”</a> (which I have read since then and also liked).
</p>

<p>
“Perl Best Practices” generated a lot of buzz in the Perl world, and so I had
some good expectations. And happily the book has indeed fulfilled them. Perl
Best Practices enumerates and explains the practice and rationale behind 256
best practices of Perl, that according to the author will result in better,
more maintainable code.
</p>

<p>
I naturally didn’t fully agree with everything that was suggested there, but
even so found it as a good food for thought. The book is highly recommended for
anyone to read and become a better and more self-conscious Perl programmer.
</p>

<p>
After speaking with the guy who bought me this book on email he gave another
best practice that was absent (and not-practised) from the book: sort your
pattern modifiers alphabetically (I.e: <tt>/egix</tt> instead of <tt>/gxie</tt>
so they can later be searched for.
</p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="joel_on_software">
                        <title>Joel on Software: And on Diverse and
                        Occasionally Related Matters That Will Prove of
                        Interest to Software Developers, Designers, and
                        Managers, and to Those Who, Whether by Good Fortune or
                        Ill Luck, Work with Them in Some Capacity</title>
                        <isbn>1590593898</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Joel Spolsky</creator>
                        <desc>

<p>
This book is a collection of essays Joel Spolsky published on his
<a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/"><i>Joel on Software</i> site</a>. Joel
is an excellent writer, writing in a humorous and accessible way
and providing many insights. I enjoyed reading his site, so I believe the
book will definitely be very nice too.
</p>

<p>
Joel writes about software management from his experience working for several
companies, from his vast knowledge, and more recently from starting his own
software shop. I learned a lot from the articles on his site, and found them
useful in my day-to-day work as a software developer.
</p>

<p>
I don’t always fully agree with everything Joel says, but even then, he
provides a lot of useful food for thought.
</p>

                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="pragmatic_programmer">
                        <title>The Pragmatic Programmer: From
                        Journeyman to Master</title>
                        <isbn>020161622X</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Andrew Hunt &amp; David
                            Thomas</creator>
                        <desc>

<p>
I heard of this book from several sources (including
<a href="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/navLinks/fog0000000262.html">the
Joel on Software Book Recommendations’ page</a>), and it was very much
esteemed, so I decided to buy it. After fully reading it, I dare say that
I found it relatively disappointing and unfulfilling, especially in
consideration of the great expectations I had from it.
</p>

<p>
This book covers a series of best practices for a programmer or a team
to become better and more capable. While it had some good points, they
were in generally lost in the large amount of individual advice given.
I still think many people may enjoy this book better than I did, but I
personally found it lacking.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="extreme_programming_explained">
                        <title>Extreme Programming Explained</title>
                        <isbn>0201616416</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Kent Beck</creator>
                        <desc>

<p>
I heard a lot about <a href="http://www.extremeprogramming.org/">Extreme
Programming</a> from my friends and associates, and especially from an
Israeli Perl Monger who is very enthusiastic about it. So I decided
to buy this book and see for myself if the fuss was justified.
</p>

<p>
I ended up really liking this book, and it did not disappoint me. It’s short,
provides an accessible read, is written well, and it piques one’s interest.
</p>

<p>
Extreme Programming (XP) aims to explain how to run a good software
development team in an organisation. By focusing on the values of XP, the
proposed methods (work in pairs, write unit tests, have the customers on
site, etc.), and illustrating with many useful stories and diagrams, this
book makes for a very good read. Highly recommended.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="mastering_perl">
                        <title>Mastering Perl</title>
                        <isbn>0596527241</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">brian d foy</creator>
                        <desc>
<p>
Mastering Perl is the third book in the installment of O’Reilly’s three
books which introduce Perl to people who are not familiar with. I haven’t
read <i>Learning Perl</i> and <i>Intermediate Perl</i>, which are the first two
installments of the series, because I felt that I already knew most of
the material that they are going to cover. Now, brian has written
<i>Mastering Perl</i> with the help of the community, by maintaining its
sources in a version control repository, and that’s how I ended up finally
reading it in 2009.
</p>

<p>
As a proficient Perl programmer who has been working with it since
1996, and have <a href="http://search.cpan.org/~shlomif/">several
modules on CPAN</a> and some other open-source Perl projects, I should note
that the book did not teach me too many new things. However, I found it to be
well-written, mildly entertaining at times, and generally accurate. The
coverage of some of the technologies there is somewhat out-of-date, but
hopefully this will be fixed in later editions. So I can recommend this
book to beginning programmers who already know the material in the previous
two books in the series.
</p>

<p>
One fact to note is that the book focuses on generic Perl technologies that
are useful for all types of programs, rather than on particular uses for
Perl (e.g: web-development or database programming). As a result of it, I
found the book to be of less interest to me, but naturally, this approach
has its merit as it is good for all Perl programmers.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="tdd_by_example">
                        <title>Test Driven Development by Example</title>
                        <isbn>0321146530</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Kent Beck</creator>
                        <desc>
                            <p>
                                I was disappointed after I started reading an earlier book about
                                <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Test-driven_development">“Test
                                    Driven Development” (TDD)</a>
                                that I have bought (here's
<a href="http://mail.perl.org.il/pipermail/perl/2010-April/010909.html">my
earlier review and a recommendation against it</a>)
but I decided
to give the TDD sub-series of the Extreme Programming books another chance with
the more elementary book in question. This time, the book met my expectations
and I can recommend it.
</p>

<p>
First of all, Beck's book is relatively short and small, as opposed to the
<i>xUnit Test Patterns</i> book. It is also interesting, entertaining and full
of insights. It is divided into three sections:
</p>

<ul>
    <li>
        <p>
            In the first: a sample financial TDD project is developed in Java, with
instructions on how to proceed every way. The standard “add-failing-test; get
it to pass; refactor;” cycle is described there with a TODO list as a tool.
This was the best section, in my opinion.
</p>
</li>
<li>
    <p>In the second section, Beck bootstraps an xUnit framework in Python
        starting from nothing (and compares it to doing brain surgery on yourself.).</p>
</li>

<li>
    <p>
In the third section, he briefly discusses various TDD patterns. I admit I
did not pay enough attention there because I read the book before going to
sleep when I was tired, and want to go over it again.
</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>
So I can recommend this book for all people who want to learn how to do TDD
better. Mr. Beck kinda aims for the high ideal of TDD and I often deviate from
it, which I think is OK.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="programming_pearls">
                        <title>Programming Pearls</title>
                        <isbn>0201657880</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Jon Bentley</creator>
                        <desc>
<p>
I've heard this book mentioned in several places before buying it and reading
it and it did not disappoint me. This book is really great, with
interesting coverage of interesting programming and computer science-related
topics. It has an extensive discussion of optimising code, which I
appreciated, being very interested in it (see:
<a href="http://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Optimizing_Code_for_Speed">my essay
about it</a> ), and lots of other
interesting stuff. The second edition was updated for modern times, and feels
quite fresh.
</p>

<p>
Bentley mentions in the book that he has written a book called "Writing
Efficient Programs" which is now out-of-print with some techniques for
optimising code. I was saddened to hear that it is indeed out-of-print,
because I would like to read it. He does give a summary of the book in an
appendix,
though.
</p>

<p>
The book contains many exercises, most of which I’ve mentally thought about,
but did not actually solve using the computer. Otherwise, I enjoyed
reading this book and can wholeheartedly recommend it.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                    <prod id="more_programming_pearls">
                        <title>More Programming Pearls: Confessions of a Coder</title>
                        <isbn>0201118890</isbn>
                        <creator type="author">Jon Bentley</creator>
                        <desc>
<p>
A fellow Perl programmer bought me this book as a birthday present from my
Amazon.com wishlist because I put it there out of wishing to read the follow-up
to the previous book in the series which I enjoyed. However, this book failed
to meet my expectations, and I found it disappointing.
</p>

<p>
It does not have the same focus on topics that interest me and instead
contains
many different topics. While not being completely bad, it fails to live up
to the promise of the previous book, and I cannot really recommend it. The
book is also showing its age.
</p>

<p>
The book page on Amazon.com used to contain a single 3-star review for
<i>More Programming Pearls</i> which kinda summarises my feelings.
</p>
                        </desc>
                    </prod>
                </cat>
            </cat>
        </cat>
    </data>
</product-syndication>
