<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"/usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"[
]>
<!-- -->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!-- -->
<!-- $Log$ -->
<!-- -->
<!-- General reminders: -->

<article id="index">
    <articleinfo>
        <title>A Solution to the Israeli-Palestinian Conflict</title>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
                <surname>Fish</surname>
                <affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <email>shlomif@shlomifish.org</email>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <copyright>
             <year>2004</year>
            <holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
        </copyright>
      <legalnotice id="main_legal_notice">
            <!-- Ci vis pacem -->
            <para>
                <!-- belum. ;-) -->
                This document is copyrighted by Shlomi Fish
                under the
                <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">Creative
                    Commons Attribution License version 2.0</ulink> (or at
                your option a greater version).
            </para>
        </legalnotice>

        <revhistory>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>1095</revnumber>
                <date>16 July 2004</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Started working on this document after forking the template
                    of an older one.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>1319</revnumber>
                <date>17 November 2004</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    The document is finished. Spell-checked. Now to get
                    reviews.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

            <revision>
                <revnumber>4885</revnumber>
                <date>5 June 2011</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Convert double and single quotes to unicode.
                </revremark>
            </revision>

        </revhistory>
    </articleinfo>

<section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        The Israeli-Palestinian conflict is probably the single gravest
        problem in Israeli external politics, at present. (and naturally
        of Palestinian external politics) So far its solution eluded the
        minds of most politicians of both sides. This article will propose
        just that, for both sides.
    </para>
    <para>
        One editorial note: “Palestinians” in the context of this article
        are the Palestinian Arabs who live in the west-bank and Gaza. I do
        not refer by it to the other members of the Palestinian people living
        outside the occupied territories. (unless explicitly said otherwise)
    </para>
    <para>
        (Note that this article is based on <ulink url="http://www.advogato.org/person/shlomif/diary.html?start=197">an older and
            unofficial essay</ulink>
        that the author of these line wrote <ulink url="http://www.advogato.org/person/shlomif/">in his online
            diary</ulink>. Its content is still relevant, but otherwise
        superseded by this essay.
        )
    </para>
    <!-- TODO : write more things in the introduction. (?) -->
</section>
<section id="status_quo">
    <title>Analysis of the Current Situation</title>
    <para>
        Before we begin proposing a solution let’s enumerate the various
        elements of the current situation, be they problematic or not, and
        explain what’s wrong with them.
    </para>
    <para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">A Partial Palestinian Autonomy
                        in the West Bank and Gaza</emphasis> - there’s a
                    Palestinian governing body that controls a large part
                    of the occupied territories directly, and affects the
                    rest of the Palestinians. It is headed by the Palestinian
                    Liberation Organization (or the PLO for short).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Many Israeli Settlements in the
                        Occupied Territories</emphasis> - there are many
                    such settlements, each contain several settlers, and
                    they are all heavily protected by the Israeli armed
                    forces.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Palestinian Terrorists perform
                        many acts of terror against Israelis</emphasis>.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Israeli Soldiers and Settlers
                        are killing many Palestinians.</emphasis>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Israel supplies relief to
                    the Palestinians so they can survive.</emphasis>
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Israeli soldiers are protecting
                        the Jewish settlements</emphasis>. This is a huge
                    consumption of resources to the Israeli military.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">The Israelis are Blaming
                        the Palestinians</emphasis>. Most Israelis believe that
                    the Palestinians are responsible for the current situation.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">The Palestinians blame the
                        Israelis</emphasis>. I don’t know that for sure but
                    it seems logical to assume this.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>
</section>
<section id="ethical_logical_facts">
    <title>Some Ethical and Logical Facts (and their Implications)</title>
    <para>
        This section will cover several logical and ethical principles that
        are necessary for formulating a proper solution. It will explain why
        they hold and also briefly cover their implications.
    </para>
    <section id="right_to_settle">
        <title>The Right to Live Everywhere</title>
        <para>
            A Person has a basic right to live everywhere he chooses and can
            support himself. Depriving a person of his home or banishing him
            is immoral, because you put a gun against his head and ask him
            to leave against his will.
        </para>
        <para>
            There are many implications to this. One of them is that the
            Palestinians should be allowed to live in the territories as well
            as Israelis in Israel. Furthermore, the Jewish settlers should be
            allowed to stay in the settlements, if they can allow their own
            protection.
        </para>
        <para>
            There is a claim that one can deprive members of different people
            from the right to inhabit a certain land because the ancestors
            used to live there. This claim does not hold. Any person can settle
            anywhere he pleases. This ends the Zionist claim that
            Palestine belongs to the Jews. Or the Palestinian claim that they
            are the rightful owners of the Palestine.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="force_protect">
        <title>No Person can Force Another to Protect Himself</title>
        <para>
            On the other hand, forcing a person to protect someone against
            his will is immoral. This is simply because it goes against the
            free will of the person who does the protection. (you put a gun
            against a person’s head and tell him “Protect someone else!”).
        </para>
        <para>
            The implications of this are that Israeli soldiers who at
            the moment are, against their will, protecting settlements
            should not be required to do this.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="right_to_bear_arms">
        <title>Right to Bear Arms</title>
        <para>
            It should be noted that a person has a basic right to bear arms,
            and carry weapons. Again, this is part of the freedom of the
            individual.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="blaming_others_for_ones_problems">
        <title>Blaming Others for One’s Own Problems</title>
        <para>
            A person or group of persons who routinely blame their own
            problems on others are behaving irrationally. By all means, every
            group should take responsibility for its own problems.
        </para>
        <para>
            It is evident that the Palestinians blame the Israelis for their
            problems and vice versa and that’s not good.
        </para>
    </section>
    <!--
        TODO: Add about government discrimination.
    -->
</section>
<section id="israel_short_term_solution">
    <title>Israel’s Short-Term Solution to the Problem</title>
    <para>
        This is a short-term solution to the problem. However, Israel has
        many other constitutional problems that make a permanent resolution
        problematic. They will be discussed in the next section.
    </para>
    <para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Israeli soldiers should be given a choice of whether
                    or not to protect the settlements. A soldier may decide
                    against protecting the settlements at any time. This is
                    in accordance with the fact that no-one can force a
                    different person to protect someone.
                </para>
                <para>
                    Those soldiers who will opt out of protecting the
                    settlements will serve in the territorial Israel
                    exclusively.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    The settlements can either remain using only their own
                    self-protection and that of the soldiers who are willing
                    to protect them, or its settlers can choose to relocate
                    to Israel, where they be given alternative homes. (as their
                    right as Israeli citizens)
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Preferably: stop giving relief to the Palestinians. If
                    it implies establishing a Palestinian state, so be it.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        That way, the Israelis will no longer need to support the settlements,
        which are a huge waste of resources, and can safely exit out of the
        settlements. Protecting Israel against attacks would be easier from
        within the territorial Israel, without having to protect tens of
        settlements and their inhabitants.
    </para>
</section>
<section id="israel_long_term_solution">
    <title>The Israeli Long-Term Part of the Solution</title>
    <para>
        Israel has a constitutional problem that prevents proper external
        relationship with Arabs. The problem is that Israel has constitutional
        racism and its bylaws discriminate against non-Jews in many ways. For
        proper Justice and Liberalism this constitutional racism needs to be
        eliminated. Otherwise, Arabs have a legitimacy to think Israel
        is their enemy, as it is clearly and constitutionally discriminates
        against them.
    </para>
    <para>
        The most important discrimination is in the immigration laws. At the
        moment, Jews can get automatic citizenship, while becoming an Israeli
        citizen for non-Jews is much more complicated. This has to be changed
        into one unified law for both Jews and non-Jews. The best option would
        be to allow anyone to enter Israel, and to work there, while giving
        citizenship to a person regardless of his religion or nationality after
        he or she has proved that he’s worthy of it.
    </para>
    <para>
        At the moment, there are only religious marriages, divorces, adoptions,
        etc. in Israel. This completely disallows Jews marrying non-Jews and
        other such anomalies. To resolve this problem, Israel must establish
        civil marriages, divorces and adoptions and other marital law.
    </para>
    <para>
        Arabs are at the moment exempted for army service, while Jews are
        obliged to serve there. To solve it either the army should be mandatory
        for everybody, or voluntary for everybody. The best solution is
        <ulink url="http://groups.yahoo.com/group/philosophy-il/message/25">to
            eliminate the draft completely and enact a voluntary
            service</ulink>.
    </para>
    <para>
        At the moment, there is also a discrimination in government funding
        between Israeli Arabs and Jews. This must be resolved.
    </para>
    <para>
        It should be noted that Israel is the land of the Israeli and not
        the land of the Jew. Eliminating such factors, may not completely
        eliminate the anti-Israeli sentiments that many Arabs have, but it
        will certainly help. At the moment, there’s a lot of evidence
        that serves as the basis for such sentiments.
    </para>
</section>
<section id="pales_solution">
    <title>Palestinian Solution</title>
    <para>
        Remember the peaceful and prosperous period of time a few years
        ago? There were few acts of violence, Palestinians cooperated with
        the Israelis, and Palestinians prospered. Palestinians should strive
        to re-enact this period.
    </para>
    <para>
        The Palestinian solution is simply to stop the terrorist acts. They
        are better off bargaining without them. Such acts only increase the
        Israeli hostility and hatred towards the Palestinians. The are
        many non-violent forms of opposing the occupation that are more
        effective (refer to Mohandas Gandhi and the Indian Opposition.)
    </para>
    <para>
        So Palestinians should not sanction terrorists and other activists,
        and those who are should quit.
    </para>
</section>
<section id="geneva_accord">
    <title>What’s Wrong with the Geneva Accord</title>
    <para>
        The Geneva Accord is not adequate as it is three serious flaws:
    </para>
    <para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It advocates disarming the terror organizations. I don’t
                    see how it can be done efficiently and the right to bear
                    arms also come to mind. I would advocate the opposite: give
                    arms to each and every Palestinian. That way, they will be
                    less afraid of the terror organizations, who in turn would
                    be much more afraid of them. (you could allow all Israelis
                    to carry arms as well, for good measure.)
            </para>
        </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                It advocates forcibly evacuating the Israeli settlements. By
                all means the Israeli Settlers have a right to live there as
                every lawful person has a right to live anywhere. The entire
                concept of immigration regulation and “fathers’ land” is
                wrong.
            </para>

            <para>
                What is wrong is forcing other people to protect them living
                there. (as force is always wrong) This distinction must be
                understood and followed.
        </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
        <para>
            Last, but probably most important is that it requires the
            mutual cooperation of both sides. One cannot expect the other
            side to follow his part of the deal, while my suggestion does
            not require the cooperation of the Palestinians.
        </para>
    </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>
</section>
<section id="separation_fence">
    <title>What’s Wrong with the Separation Fence?</title>
    <para>
        A suggestion was made to build a separation fence, protecting Israel
        and the settlements from the Palestinians. This suggestion is wrong from
        the following reasons:
    </para>
    <para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It is still based on the assumption that the problem lies
                    in the Palestinians. The Israelis fail to take
                    responsibility for their own problems.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Due to the fact that all the settlements are aimed to be
                    included in Israel’s part of the fence, it would be 1000s
                    of kilometers long in a 250*100 kilometer area. A huge and
                    costly construction project.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It will be a huge environmental disaster.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Can potentially become a large defense problem. (at times
                    of war).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Will make a lot of legitimate traffic very difficult.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Will make a lot of legitimate traffic very difficult.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    May not prevent the terrorist acts entirely - most
                    suicide terrorists passed through border-passings.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It is much less effective than withdrawing from the
                    occupied territories.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    It is not something that Israel is allowed to do, according
                    to International Law, and the status of the occupied
                    territories.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>
</section>
</article>    <!-- End of the article -->
