<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"/usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"[
]>
<!-- -->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!-- -->
<!-- $Log$ -->
<!-- -->
<!-- General reminders: -->

<article id="index">
    <articleinfo>
        <title>Objectivism and Open Source</title>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
                <surname>Fish</surname>
                <affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <email>shlomif@shlomifish.org</email>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <copyright>
             <year>2003</year>
            <holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
        </copyright>
      <legalnotice id="main_legal_notice">
            <para>
<!--Creative Commons License-->
This work is licensed under the <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 Licence</ulink> (or at your option a greater version of it).
            </para>
        </legalnotice>

        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>5034</revnumber>
                <date>12 May 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Started keeping track of version. Changed the "book"
                    schema to an "article"-based one. Changed more spelling
                    to Commonwealth one. Changed the two-level of Ethics
                    to "Ethical" and "Moral".
                </revremark>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </articleinfo>
<section id="introduction">

<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
The "open source" movement is perhaps the most important phenomenon
in the software world today. Thousands of developers and
millions of users worldwide create, maintain, support and use
high-quality software packages, that are made available for everyone
to use, modify and distribute. Many Objectivists may reject this
movement on the premises of it being anti-Capitalistic in nature. The
aim of this document is to show that they need not and should not.
</para>

<para>
This document will demonstrate that working on open source software
is not anti-Capitalistic, and that it is also an objectively moral
and healthy activity. It will explain why there is no dichotomy between
the open source world and Objectivism, and why Objectivists can
support it, without having guilt feelings of behaving un-Capitalistically.
</para>

</section>

<section id="what_is_open_source">

<title>What is Open Source?</title>

<para>
Open source is a relatively new name for a relatively old phenomenon that
is also called "free software". (this term preceded "open source" but it
too came a long time after the phenomenon emerged). I have written
<ulink url="http://fc-solve.shlomifish.org/oss-fs/docbook/">a previous
introduction to this phenomenon</ulink> which I advise to read if you're not
familiar at all with the term.
</para>

<para>
To sum up, an open source software is a software that is accompanied with
its original source code and can be freely used, modified, and re-distributed
without any charge. It is possible to charge money for a package that
contains free software components, but generally it is not economical to
base a business on it, because of the fact that it can later on be freely
distributed.
</para>

<para>
Some of the landmarks of the open source movement are the <ulink url="http://gcc.gnu.org/">GCC-based
software development kit</ulink>, the
<ulink url="http://www.apache.org/">Apache
web-server</ulink> and other Internet servers, the
<ulink url="http://www.mozilla.org/">cross-platform Mozilla
web-browser</ulink>, various high-level languages such as
<ulink url="http://www.perl.org/">Perl</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://www.python.org/">Python</ulink>,
<ulink url="http://www.tcl.tk/">Tcl</ulink> or
<ulink url="http://www.ruby-lang.org/en/">Ruby</ulink>;
the <ulink url="http://www.x.org/">X-Windows Graphics System</ulink>
 and desktops built on top.
There are also
several operating systems whose every essential component is open source.
They include the <ulink url="http://www.linux.org/">Linux (or GNU/Linux)
Operating System</ulink>, and some of the
<ulink url="http://www.bsd.org/">various
BSDs</ulink>
</para>

<para>
Open source software provides a low-cost, highly customizable, and often
more reliable or technically superior alternative to commercial, non-free
software. The open source world maintains an online web of mailing lists,
web forums, IRC channels, web-sites and other resources with which
people who are more knowledgable in some respects help their less
experienced peers.
</para>

</section>

<section id="what_is_objectivism">

<title>What is Objectivism?</title>

<para>
Objectivism is a philosophy put forth by Ayn Rand, and later further
developed by others. It has a strong emphasis on individualism, objectivity
and Capitalism. Objectivism is based on the premise that existence exists
and is common to all conscious individuals independtly of what anyone think
it is. As such it rejects such notions as Subjectivism (that reality is
subjective to any individual), and mysticism (that thoughts can alter reality).
</para>

<para>
One of the central themes of the Objectivism is that the conscious individual
is an end to himself, and should strive to fullfill his own happiness and
well-being. It demonstrates that by acting out of their rational self-interest
, individuals best benefit others as well.
</para>

<para>
Similarly it believes that Altruism (advocating the must to contribute to an
external cause) is a harmful notion that one has to reject from within
and without. Objectivism does not oppose individuals voluntarily
contributing time, effort, or other resources to further the well-being
of others. However, it demonstrates that claiming that you are only worthy
of living if you help an external cause (the poor, your country, your
religion, etc) is a harmful notion that has caused a great deal of strife
in the world.
</para>

<para>
Objectivism Support Capitalism as the ideal way of running a country
and vows for Laissez-Faire Capitalism, as the ultimate form of it.
</para>

<section id="about_neo_tech">

<title>About Neo-Tech</title>

<para>
<ulink url="http://www.neo-tech.com/">Neo-Tech</ulink> is an idea
system based on Objectivism that also incorporates Psychology and Business
Management, and reaches even bolder conclusions. Summarizing Neo-Tech
is not possible in this scope because the material put forth by it
is huge. It's also not particularily relevant because this document is aimed
at Objectivists (and non-Objectivists) who have not accepted Neo-Tech yet.
</para>

<para>
However, I will borrow some concepts and text from the Neo-Tech literature
to demonstrate my points, and hope they will be commonly accepted enough by
everyone.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="two_levels_of_morality">
<title>Two Levels of Ethics and How Open Source Measures Against Them</title>

<para>
There are two levels of Ethics: Ethos and Morality.
An ethical action is such that is allowed under objective ethics. I.e:
if you wish to perform it, then no-one can prevent you from doing it. It may
not necessarily be a good action to take, but it is still allowed. A
non-ethical action is such that will harm others and so is not allowed.
</para>

<para>
Now an ethical action is moral if it delivers genuine gain for
you or for someone else. This distinction should be made because some
ethical actions are very harmful (such as commiting suicide or
consuming harmful substances).<footnote id="ammoral" label="Ammoral">
    <para>
        Related to moral and ethical choices are ammoral decisions. An ammoral
        choice is a matter of taste and is neither moral nor immoral.
        Examples are: your favourite food, your favourite Ice-cream flabour,
        your preferences in members-of-the-appropriate-sex, what you prefer
        to do at the moment, etc.
    </para>
</footnote>
</para>


<para>
The aim of this section is to show that working on open source software is not
only ethical but moral as well.
</para>

<section id="why_oss_is_ethical">
<title>Why Open-Source is Ethical</title>

<para>
The best summary of what is ethical and what isn't can be found
in the <ulink url="http://www.neo-tech.com/neotech/advantages/advantage83.html">
Neo-Tech Constitution</ulink>. This document contains a preamble, followed
by three articles, followed by 6 axioms. The articles are the most relevant
and I'll bring them here:
</para>

<para>
<orderedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
No person, group of persons, or government may initiate force, threat of force, or fraud against the person or property of any individual.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Force may be morally and legally used only in defense against those who violate Article 1.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
No exception shall ever exist to Articles 1 &amp; 2.
</para>
</listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>

<para>
The validity of this definition is self-evident. Now, based on it, what
can we say about creating open-source software? It surely does not involve
initiatory force, coercion or fraud. Working on free software is done
voluntarily and its distribution does not involve harming anyone.
</para>
<para>
While vendors of commercial software may lose money or go out of business
out of competition with open-source software, it does not constitute of
force. Competition is one of the cornerstones of Capitalism. This is similar
to selling a cheaper and/or better product at the marketplace and taking
market share out of the competition.
</para>
<para>
Thus, creating and maintaining open source software is a constitutional action.
</para>
</section>
<section id="why_oss_is_beneficial">
<title>Why Open-Source Development is Moral</title>

<para>
Naively, some Objectivists may come to believe that working on open-source
software is, while perfectly ethical, not a good action to take.
"You work on software that the masses could use, and instead of selling
it and earning a honest buck, you give it away to everybody, and have
others benefit from your efforts. What's in it for you?" But let's first
formulate a definition of what is moral and what isn't.
</para>

<para>
Again, I will extract a suitable definition out of the Neo-Tech text:
</para>

<para>
"The meaning of moral in Neo-Tech is simple and direct: Whatever is
consciously done to help fill human biological needs is good and moral
(e.g., the productive actions of honest people). Whatever is consciously
done to harm or prevent the filling of human biological needs is bad
and immoral (e.g., the destructive actions of mystics and neocheaters)."
</para>

<para>
"moral" here is "beneficial" in our terminology. The validity of this
definition is also evident. So how Open-Source measures against it? Very
well, actually. Open source software was so far used by millions of users
worldwide, greatly facilitated some of the jobs they had to do with their
computer, and generally contributed to everyone's well-being. The very
action of creating a useful software for everyone to use is beneficial as
it eventually can help fill human biological needs.
</para>

<para>
Now, some hardcore Objectivists can ask "But what about your own self-
interest?". Self-interest here is relevant, but in subversive ways.
The open-source developer does not economically benefit from the software
he wrote, as much as he would, had he sold it commercially (and assuming
it would indeed become successful). However, he does benefit, from having
more potential users and co-developers, from making sure his software or
one of similar vestiges will remain available as time goes by, and from
a boost of happiness knowing that people are using your software.
</para>

<para>
Usually, getting a non-free piece of software to become successful would
take a lot of effort on the developer's part, and you always risk a
player with better resources competing with you. While it is itself beneficial
as well, it may not yield the same immediate and long-term profit from
working on an open-source package.
</para>
</section>
</section>

<section id="beyond_morality">
<title>Beyond Morality: Why Open Source is Good for You</title>

<para>
The reasons that make open-source a viable choice technically,
psychologically and economically were already given in
<ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/">Eric Raymond's</ulink>
excellent <ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/">
"The Cathedral and the Bazaar" series</ulink>. In the first part,
<ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/cathedral-bazaar/">"The Cathedral and the Bazaar"</ulink>, Raymond describes the dynamics
of a small "Bazaar-style" open-source project, and analyzes why
this system works so well for developing software.
</para>

<para>
In the second part, <ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/homesteading/">Homesteading the Noosphere</ulink> Raymond analyzes the
customs of the open source community. He demonstrates that because of the
abundance of computer resources such as computing power, network bandwidth,
hard-disk capacity - there is no scarsity economics involved in the
Internet world. Instead, there is a gift culture, in which people are esteemed
according to what they give away (namely, contributions to open source
software)
</para>

<para>
The third part, <ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/magic-cauldron/">"The Magic Cauldron"</ulink> analyzes the economics of the
open-source world. It demonstrates why non-free commercial software is
problematic and why open-source works so well. It gives several places in which
companies and individuals can utilise distributing a software under an
open-source licence for their own commercial gains. He also dispels the
myth that programmers will be out of job because of free software by
noting that the majority of code in the world (and what the vast majority
of programmers are working on) is code for internal use: in-house applications,
customizations of programs, embedded software, software that accompanies
hardware, software that powers web-sites, etc. Such software has no sale
value, and so its developers will not be damaged if open source takes over.
</para>

<para>
The whole series is a very recommended read.
</para>

<para>
<ulink url="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/">Joel Spolsky</ulink> later
continued the Magic Cauldron theme in his essay
<ulink url="http://www.joelonsoftware.com/articles/StrategyLetterV.html">
Strategy Letter V</ulink>. He took the Micro-economics principle of
complementary products, and showed why supporting open-source software
can be a wise decision to make complementary products in greater demand. A complementary product is such that
when its in greater abundance, demand for the complementary product will
become higher. For example, if flights to Florida became cheaper, then
there would be greater demand for Florida Hotel Rooms. Open source software
can be a complementary product to hardware or services involved in supporting
it, which explains why companies like IBM or Sun are financing it.
</para>

<para>
Aside from all that, working on open-source software is a fun and rewarding
experience. One becomes more experienced and learn a lot, interacts
with users and co-developers (some of them living thousands of kilometers from
where you are), and generally becomes happy of having done something
useful.
</para>

<para>
Generally, the amount of work an open source developer invests in his
software is vastly neglible compared to the benefit he makes out of the
work of all the other developers. As someone once noted, in the open-source
model everyone contributes a brick and in return everyone gets a full house
for himself. By decentralizing effort, and splitting the development into a
large number of well-defined projects, the open source world ensures that
development is done at a highly accelerated pace.
</para>

</section>

<section id="why_dichotomy">

<title>Why the Apparent Dichotomy Exists in the First Place?</title>

<para>
Finally, it's time to analyze why the apparent dichotomy between open-source
and Objectivism exists in the first place. The most important reason is
because some non-free software is sold, and because open source software
is made available for everyone to freely use and distribute. So, we see the
vendors of proprietary software as healthy Capitalists (which is true), and
automatically deduce that open source software is anti-Capitalistic.
</para>

<para>
However, software is different in the fact that the cost of duplicating
it and distributing it is virtually zero. A software developer is not
encumbered if his software has 100,000 of users instead of just 1,000.
While developing the software is time consuming, there is no reason not
to share it after one has invested this initial time.
</para>

<para>
Some people may come to believe that sharing anything is bad. But as Eric
Raymond notes in the excellent film "Revolution OS": "Open source is
voluntary sharing. Communism puts a gun against your head and forces you
to share.". While sharing hammers or food does not make sense economically
because such things take a positive amount of time to manufacture every
unit of (albeit such action is perfectly constitutional), sharing software
is not encumbered by these real-world constraints. That put aside,
giving away something to your friends, was not held as illogical even
by Ayn Rand herself.
</para>

<para>
Another thing that hinders the acceptance of Open Source software is the
belief that "if you want something good, you have to pay for it.". This
myth does not hold in the software world, because a software can achieve
good quality by incremental contributions from its voluntary developers.
When a developer works on a software, there is the pure joy of creation
and other social rewards, and it does not matter if he makes any revenue
off selling the software. There is a similar case when developing other
types of artwork.
</para>

<para>
Alternatively, the entity that pays the developer to write the software
gains from other aspects of the software besides its sale value. (as previously
noted).
</para>

<para>
The facts also speak for themselves. The Linux operating system and other
pieces of open-source software (or for that matter freeware), have millions
of users who can testify for their superior quality and working experience.
</para>

</section>

<section id="oss_and_capitalism">
<title>Open Source and Capitalism</title>

<para>
Some may claim that the Open Source development methodology contradicts
Capitalism: after all, a final product is produced, and given away for free.
This is while the general theme of Capitalism is to competitively create
values that are sold in the marketplace.
</para>

<para>
A bit bucket once produced and finalised (a procedure that may require a lot
of money, effort and time), can be later distributed free-of-charge by
electronic means, without causing loss to the originator of the bit bucket.
This is oas pposed to physical products such as food or tools, which cost money
to produce and distribute each unit of.
</para>

<para>
Thus, it economically makes sense to distribute software or other bit buckets
free-of-charge. The fact that vendors of proprietary software do it for money,
does not preclude a costless alternative by someone else. Capitalism has
endorsed distributing cheaper alternatives to products for a long time.
</para>

<para>
For a more thorough discussion of the economics of open source software refer
to Eric Raymond's Essay <ulink url="http://www.catb.org/~esr/writings/cathedral-bazaar/magic-cauldron/">"The Magic Cauldron"</ulink>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="community_and_collectivism">

<title>The Open Source Community and Collectivism</title>

<para>
One of the corner-stones of Objectivism is its opposition to Collectivism.
Namely considering a collective of individuals as more important than its
individuals, or thinking that one should sacrifice the well-being or happiness
of individuals for the collective.
</para>

<para>
The open-source world exhibits a very prosperous, active and often zealous
community of users, contributors and advocates. Is this an indication of
Collectivism?
</para>

<para>
No, it isn't. Collectivism is not against forming collectives. Some
collectives, like many countries, cities, and businesses, clubs and so on are
or can be benevolent. The only problem comes when the leaders of the collective
stress the welfare of the collective above the welfare of its individuals. This
is generally not the case for the Open Source community.
</para>

<para>
Moreover, the members of the Open Source community are active there at will.
There's no force, threat of force, or fraud involved by anyone to convince
him to become an open-source user or activist. If people just use open-source
software because of its benefits or lower price, without contributing anything
back, it is considered OK and fully allowed by the licences of the software.
</para>

<para>
Thus, the open source community is not a collectivist phenomenon, and
participating in it should not be regarded as such.
</para>

</section>

<section id="doc_info">

<title>Document Information</title>

<section id="about_the_author">
<title>About the Author</title>
<para>
My name is Shlomi Fish and I am a user, developer and advocate of
open-source software. I also use commercial software, if I need to,
but usually don't enjoy using it quite as much as the open-source
equivalents. I am also a firm believer in Objectivism and Neo-Tech.
</para>
<para>
You can learn more about me by visiting
<ulink url="http://www.shlomifish.org/">my homepage</ulink>.
</para>
</section>

<section id="why_this_doc_was_written">
<title>Why this document was written?</title>

<para>
I once searched Google for "objectivism open source" and came upon
an article on Open Source written by an Objectivist in a three part series
about the Microsoft trial. However, the article proved to be inaccurate
and showed a general misunderstanding of what open source was all about.
</para>

<para>
This article aims to be a better attempt at the job, from someone who is
an insider of the open source world.
</para>
</section>

<section id="software_used_in_creation">
<title>Software Used in the Creation of this Document</title>

<para>
This document was written (and is available) in DocBook/XML, and
was rendered into HTML, PDF, and Word RTF using the DSSSL stylesheets,
OpenJade, and Jadetex and TeX. The process was managed using GNU make
and the files were uploaded using the rsync program.
</para>

<para>
The text itself was edited using the
<ulink url="http://www.vim.org/">Vim</ulink> text editor. This took place
entirely on a Mandrake Linux 9.1 system. All of the above are open source
software.
</para>

</section>

<section id="copyright">

<title>Copyright</title>

<!-- Creative Commons License -->
<para>
This work is licensed under a
<ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">Creative
    Commons License</ulink> - The Attribution License Version 2.0 or
greater. Year of Copyright is 2003.
</para>
<!-- /Creative Commons License -->


<!--

<rdf:RDF xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
<Work rdf:about="">
   <dc:title>Objectivism and Open Source</dc:title>
   <dc:date>2003</dc:date>
   <dc:description>An Essay that explains why the Open Source Software culture and methodology is compatible with Objectivism Philosophy and Thought.</dc:description>
   <dc:creator><Agent>
      <dc:title>Shlomi Fish</dc:title>
   </Agent></dc:creator>
   <dc:rights><Agent>
      <dc:title>Shlomi Fish</dc:title>
   </Agent></dc:rights>
   <dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text" />
   <license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/" />
</Work>

<License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/">
   <permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction" />
   <permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution" />
   <requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice" />
   <requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution" />
   <permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks" />
</License>

</rdf:RDF>

-->

</section>

<section id="thanks">

<title>Thanks</title>

<para>
Thanks should go to
<ulink url="http://nadav.harel.org.il/">Nadav Har’El</ulink> and
<ulink url="http://www.zak.co.il/">Omer Zak</ulink> for reviewing the early
drafts of this document and supplying some useful corrections and
comments. Thanks also to Einat Ya'akobovitch for inspiring some further
additions to the document.
</para>
</section>

</section>

</article>    <!-- End of the book -->
