<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"/usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"[
]>
<!-- -->
<!-- $Id$ -->
<!-- -->
<!-- $Log$ -->
<!-- -->
<!-- General reminders: -->

<article id="index">
    <articleinfo>
        <title>Park - Park is, is not, is too, is not Arc</title>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
                <surname>Fish</surname>
                <affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <email>shlomif@iglu.org.il</email>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <copyright>
             <year>2004</year>
            <holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
        </copyright>
      <legalnotice>
            <!-- Ci vis pacem -->
            <para>
                <!-- belum. ;-) -->
                This document is copyrighted by Shlomi Fish
                under the
                <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">Creative
                    Commons Attribution License version 2.5</ulink>
                (or at your option a greater version). The code samples are
                under the Public Domain.
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>3</revnumber>
                <date>21 June 2006</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Started working on this document after forking the template
                    of an older one.
                </revremark>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </articleinfo>

<section id="about_park">
    <title>Park - Park is, is not, is too, is not Arc</title>


    <para>
    Park
        <footnote id="about_the_slogan">

            <para>
            The "Park - Park is, is not, is too, is not Arc" slogan is
            temporary. The permanent slogan so far seems like it would
            be "Park - a LISP that starts with P".
            </para>
        </footnote>
    is a new dialect of Lisp, based on
    <ulink url="http://www.paulgraham.com/arc.html">Paul
    Graham's Arc effort</ulink>. Park is in fact a malicious and incompatible
    fork of Arc. A fork not of the code, which is still not available to the
    public, but of the concept and motivation.
    </para>

    <para>
    The origin of the name is with an initial implementation for Arc that I
    wanted to write for Parrot, called PArc or Parc. However, then I realised
    I disagree with Graham about some of his language design elements. A few
    days ago I came with a revelation that it was hopeless waiting for
    Mr. Graham to actually release either a final spec to the public of Arc
    or a actual working code. Arc <ulink url="http://www.paulgraham.com/arcll1.html">was announced at the LL1 conference at Novemeber 2001</ulink>. It's
    been almost 5 years from now, and there's still not a working code or a
    coherent spec. Furthermore, Graham stopped adding the ideas people sent
    him to the <ulink url="http://www.archub.org/arcsug.txt">emails collection
    containing them</ulink> (including one that I sent a few years ago, which
    I know he is aware of because he responded to my message).
    </para>

    <para>
    Thus enter Park. The name stems from "Parc" but is actually an English
    world. One can say that Park is a LISP that starts with "P", or that
    working with it is like a stroll in the Park. Park has
    <ulink url="http://www.paulgraham.com/popular.html">the design goals of
    Arc</ulink> but:
    </para>

    <para>
    <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    Is different and incompatible.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Has a working (albeit so far informal) spec.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Encourages participation from the community (using such web resources
    as a Subversion repository, a Wiki, etc.)
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Encourages people to create and hack on implementations for it.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Would try to get version 0.2.0 of the SPEC (the first stable version of
    the language) out of the door as soon as possible, so people can create
    implementations that they can rely on.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
    One note about myself. My name is
    <ulink url="http://www.shlomifish.org/">Shlomi Fish</ulink> and I'm a
    software enthusiast and a writer. I am not the ideal person to design
    Park, but I believe and hope that I have the right attitude. If you happen
    to know better about somethings, please post your corrections to the
    mailing lists to the mailing list. Corrections in the form of patches
    against the Docbook/XML source are preferable. Several of them or even
    just one that is accepted will get you a Subversion commit access. And
    naturally everyone can edit the wiki.
    </para>

    <section id="why_am_i_doing_it">
        <title>Why am I Doing it?</title>
        <blockquote>
            <attribution><ulink url="http://groups.google.com/group/comp.lang.perl/msg/620a1599759c9bc?hl=en">Larry Wall</ulink></attribution>
            <para>
            All language designers are arrogant. Comes with the territory.
            </para>
        </blockquote>
        <para>
            Why am I doing it? For several reasons:
        </para>
        <para>
            <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        <ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0066620724/103-5528911-1875020">Because it's fun.</ulink> This is by itself a good
                        reason.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Because I found that designing your own language is
                        one of the best ways to learn more about the original
                        languages it is based on. When I designed the
                        <ulink url="http://www.shlomifish.org/rindolf/">Perl
                            dialect "Rindolf"</ulink>, I learned that some
                        features I suggested for it were already doable in
                        Perl 5.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Because something good may eventually come out of it.
                        The existing popular dialects of LISP are Common LISP,
                        Scheme (which some people claim is not entirely Lispy)
                        and some domain-specific Lisp dialects like Emacs Lisp
                        and Autolisp, which are not useful for general
                        programming.
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        The Common Lisp and Scheme standards still exhibit
                        some relics of the Lisp distant past, where it was
                        expected to run
                        on such now obscure systems as
                        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PDP-10">the
                            PDP-10</ulink> and
                        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Incompatible_Timesharing_System">ITS</ulink> or the LISP Machine. They do not correspond to
                        the modern's world "All the world is a VAX" and
                        "Everything on top is a UNIX" reality. (Which has
                        persisted for better or for worse).
                    </para>

                    <para>
                        The implementations themselves do little to solve
                        this problem, as they differ in the APIs they provide
                        for such basic mechanisms that programmers of other
                        dynamic languages (like Perl, Python, PHP, Ruby or
                        Tcl) take for granted like Random File I/O, Sockets,
                        Regular Expressions, CGI Programming and
                        Web Automation, Graphical User-interface, Database
                        Connectivity etc.
                    </para>

                </listitem>

            </orderedlist>
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="why_a_new_dialect">
        <title>Why a new Dialect?</title>

        <para>
            Paul Graham explains it very well in <ulink url="http://www.paulgraham.com/arcfaq.html">the
                Arc FAQ</ulink>, and in
            <ulink url="http://www.paulgraham.com/popular.html">"Being
                Popular"</ulink>. Park is Arc done faster, and hopefully
            also better.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>

<section id="what_park_is_based_on">
    <title>What Park is based on</title>

    <para>
    The following languages have influcened Park:
    </para>

    <para>
    <orderedlist>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Arc and Scheme. And to some extent Common LISP.
    </para>
    </listitem>


    <listitem>
    <para>
    Perl 5 and Perl 6.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Python.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
    <para>
    Smalltalk and Ruby.
    </para>
    </listitem>

    </orderedlist>
    </para>
</section>

<section id="elements_of_design">
    <title>Elements of Design</title>
    <section id="arc_is_object_oriented">
        <title>Arc is Object Oriented (Everything is an Object)</title>

        <para>
        Paul Graham wrote <ulink url="http://www.paulgraham.com/noop.html">Why
        Arc isn't Especially Object-Oriented.</ulink>. His conclusion for why
        this is the case are:
        </para>

        <blockquote>
        <para>
         I personally have never needed object-oriented abstractions. Common
         Lisp has an enormously powerful object system and I've never used it
         once. I've done a lot of things (e.g. making hash tables full of
         closures) that would have required object-oriented techniques to do in
         wimpier languages, but I have never had to use CLOS.
        </para>
        <para>
        Maybe I'm just stupid, or have worked on some limited subset of
        applications. There is a danger in designing a language based on one's
        own experience of programming. But it seems more dangerous to put stuff
        in that you've never needed because it's thought to be a good idea.
        </para>
        </blockquote>

        <para>
        Well, maybe it's because I'm younger, but having worked with Perl 5
        extensively, I've used its oject system (and some OO-support modules)
        a lot. While I have inherited some classes in Perl 5, I also often
        use an object just to make sure it can be instantiated.
        </para>

        <para>
        Furthermore, having learned a bit about Perl 6 and Ruby, I believe that
        making everything an object, can be advantageous because one can
        more easily inherit from it, and add methods (and multimethods) to
        constants or regular variables (e.g: <quote>6->my_func();</quote>),
        or even easily override default behaviour.
        </para>

        <para>
        So there we go. Note that Park will not be overly-Object-Oriented
        (OOO). One would be able to declare global functions and variables,
        and write scripts or modules without wrapping it in Objects. (Read
        what <ulink url="http://www.builderau.com.au/program/0,39024614,39160082,00.htm">Damian
        Conway has to say about the Hello World program in Java</ulink> for
        why I don't like it).
        </para>

        <para>
        Here are some features of the object system:
        </para>

        <orderedlist>

            <listitem>
            <para>
                Supports multiple-inheritance.
            </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
            <para>
                Methods can be added to classes at run-time (like Smalltalk
                or Ruby).
            </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
            <para>
                Supports
                <ulink url="http://use.perl.org/~Ovid/journal/27656">traits</ulink>
                (or as the Perl 6 people call them "Roles").
            </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
            <para>
                The fields of every object will be stored as an associative
                array, accessible using a special method. (This associative
                array will also be an object since everything is. I wonder
                how the Python people have solved it, but it's probably
                doable.)
            </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
            <para>
                The member variables of every object will be stored as an
                associative array, accessible using a special method. (This
                associative array will also be an object since everything is.
                I wonder how the Python people have solved it, but it's
                probably doable.)
            </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
            <para>
                Similarly to Perl5 and Python (and as opposed to Java, C++
                or PHP) there won't be any built-in "public",
                "protected", "private", etc. access-control for methods of
                objects by default. Such things can probably be implemented by
                tweaking the method class and/or the class meta-class, or in
                different ways completely, but I don't find it appropriate
                for Park.
            </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
            Multi-methods will be supported. Multimethods are functions that
            are dispatched according to more than one object based on the
            best matching multimethod signature. The syntax for this would
            be the mcall function (short for multi-call):
            </para>
<programlisting>
(mcall my-multi-method ([ object1 object2 object3])
    optional-param1 optional-param2 optional-param3
)
</programlisting>
            <para>
            The standard way to invoke a method is to use the
            <literal>call</literal> function, which propagates according to
            only a single argument:
            </para>
<programlisting>
(def-method "MyClass::init"
    ((this)
        (set (this sum) 0)
    )
)
(def-method "MyClass::add"
    ((this n)
        (+= (-&gt; this sum) n)
    )
)
(def-method "MyClass::getsum"
    ((this)
        (-&gt; this sum)
    )
)
(set new-summer (new MyClass))
(call add new-summer 5)
(call add new-summer 7)
(call add new-summer 13)
(print (call getsum new-summer) "\n")
</programlisting>

            <para>
            This will print 24 and a newline.
            </para>
            <para>
            Note that usually the call would be redundant, and you could
            use a simple function call. However, such a function call would
            be subject to other Perl 5-like calling semantics.
            </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>

    </section>

    <section id="lexical_scoping_and_dynamic_scoping">
        <title>Lexical Scoping and Dynamic Scoping</title>

        <para>
        Scheme and Common Lisp which are the most modern popular
        LISP dialects use lexical scoping, and since Perl 5 adopted it,
        it has been become very popular and mainstream, outside Lisp.
        </para>

        <para>
        The default localization of values in Park would be lexical. However,
        having used Perl 5's <literal>local</literal>, I am aware of
        <ulink url="http://perl.plover.com/local.html">several good uses for
        dynamic scoping in a mostly lexical scoping language</ulink>. So,
        there will be a way to localise variables dynamically in Park.
        </para>

        <para>
        One killer feature like that would be a way to do something like:
        </para>
<programlisting>
(do-using-local-state
    (
        (set a "hello")
        (my-func-with-side-effects)
    )
    (
        # Rest of code here.
    )
)
# a is no longer hello and (my-func-with-side-effects) effects' are reversed.
</programlisting>

        <para>
        Of course, this feature is still pie-in-the-sky, and I'm waiting for
        a good analysis of complexity and/or efficient working implementation.
        </para>
    </section>

    <section id="full_posix_conventions">
        <title>Park would be Fully POSIX</title>
        <para>
            Park will be expected to run on a Unix or a Unix-like system
            (such as Win32) and will provide APIs for such common POSIX
            and P-Languages operations as random file I/O, sockets, regular
            expressions, manipulating ASCII text, Unicode and other
            encodings. It may also have platform-specific modules for managing
            processes, creating new processes, etc. (as is the case for
            Perl 5, for example.)
        </para>
        <para>
            All of these things will eventually be part of the Park spec,
            and their APIs would be common to all implementations.
        </para>

        <section id="monads_for_files">
            <title>Thoughts about using Monads for Files</title>
            <blockquote>
                <attribution>
                An anonymous Perl 5 and
                <ulink url="http://www.pugscode.org/">Pugs</ulink> hacker
                about Haskell's Monads.
                </attribution>
                <para>
                I understood Monads for exactly 5 minutes. Then the
                understanding left my head. It was too hard for me
                to keep there.
                </para>
            </blockquote>
            <para>
                As cool as Monads are I'm skeptical about using them in
                files by default. I know how to use File I/O in Haskell, but
                still don't understand when Monads are needed. My personal
                Haskell style so far made no use of them except for file Input
                and Output.
            </para>
            <para>
                One will be able to implement Monads in Park and use them
                for file I/O. There may even be a default Monad class. However,
                the default file Input/Output API will either be a reflection
                of the POSIX one, or alternatively something similar
                in spirit to
                <ulink url="http://search.cpan.org/search?query=perlio&amp;mode=module">PerlIO</ulink>
                or the Python or Ruby files and sockets I/O classes.
            </para>

            <para>
            Above this API one can build as many abstractions to his
            liking, including Monads.
            </para>
        </section> <!-- /monads_for_files -->

        <section id="bootstrapping_self_hosting_and_c_hosting">
            <title>Bootstrapping, Self Hosting and C Hosting</title>

            <para>
                Bootstrapping is the process of implementing a virtual machine
                by implementing it using an existing virtual machine. So,
                for example perl 5, CPython, ruby, php and the Tcl interpreter
                are all written in ANSI C. That way they can be bootstrapped
                to run on any system for which a C compiler (such as
                <ulink url="http://gcc.gnu.org/">the Open-Source gcc</ulink>
                is available).
            </para>
            <para>
                A related concept is Self-hosting, where a virtual machine's
                compiler or interpreter is written in itself. So for example,
                gcc is written in C and requires a C compiler to be built.
            </para>
            <para>
                For C it is not really a problem, because one can
                use gcc or a different C compiler to cross-compile enough
                programs for it to run there conveniently. However,

            </para>

        </section> <!-- bootstrapping_self_hosting_and_c_hosting -->

        <section id="constants_in_park">
            <title>Constants in Park</title>

            <blockquote>
                <attribution>
                    An anonymous designer of his own DOS 8086 Assembly written in
                    itself, and used to write other programs, in which numbers
                    that start with 0 are hexadecimal.
                </attribution>

                <para>
                    "I am not in Rome."
                </para>
            </blockquote>

            <para>
            I encountered some Scheme implementations in which identifiers
            were case-sensitive, and some in which they were case-insensitive.
            To match what is the norm nowadays, and becase I like it better,
            Park requires case-sensitive identifiers.
            </para>

            <para>
            Numbers in Park can be decimal, octal (if they start with "0"),
            or hexadecimal (if they start with 0x). Following Perl's lead,
            one will be able to use underscores (<literal>_</literal>)
            within numbers (e.g: <literal>100_000</literal> instead of
            <literal>100000</literal>).
            </para>

            <section id="strings_quoting_and_interpolation">
                <title>Strings, Quoting and Interpolation</title>

                <section id="string_constants">
                    <title>String Constants</title>
                    <para>
                        String constants will be written in a large
                        correspondence to the C, Perl 5 and Perl 6
                        conventions. For example, a "\n" will designate
                        a newline. The exact type and quoting of the string
                        will be determined by a few optional Perl 6-like
                        modifiers. Here are a few examples:
                    </para>
<programlisting>
# The (qq ... ) is not really needed but it doesn't hurt.
(my mystring (qq "Hello there, Hackers! Welcome to Park"))
(print mystring "\n")
(my regex (m :p5 "H..kers"))
(say (=~ mystring regex)) # Prints "Hackers"
(my conv (tr "H" "B"))
(say (=~ mystring conv)) # Prints "Bello there, Backers!..."
(my newstring mystring)
(=~! newstring conv)
# newstring is now "Bello there, Backers!..."
# (You gotta love S-expressions.)
</programlisting>
                </section>
                <section id="string_interpolation">
                <title>String Interpolation</title>
                <para>
                    There was a very interesting presentation in an
                    <ulink url="http://www.perl.org.il/">Israeli Perl Mongers
                        meeting</ulink> about strings, quoting and
                    interpolation in other languages and Perl. The presentation
                    noted among else that in other languages one has to write
                    relatively
                    ugly code like <literal>"Hello" &amp; Name &amp; "! What's up?"</literal>
                    rather than the Perl <literal>"Hello $Name! What's
                        up?"</literal>.
                </para>

                <para>
                    In Perl 5 the interpreter has some heuristics for
                    determining the end of the interpolated expression, which
                    can be any arbitrary Perl expression. Perl 6 goes one
                    step further and parses the string and translates it into
                    Perl 6 code, so one can safely include arbitrarliy complex
                    code there. (In a similar fashion to the Korn shell
                    "$(...)" construct).
                </para>

                <para>
                    What I plan is to have such interpolation in Park as well
                    for some types of strings. The syntax will look something
                    like that:
                </para>

<programlisting>
(my i 5 j 7)
(print "${i} + ${j} = $(+ i j)\n")
</programlisting>

                <para>
                    As expected this prints "5 + 7 = 12" (followed by a
                    newline).
                </para>

                <para>
                    Another thing I'd like to have is shell or Perl 5-like
                    here documents (<literal>&amp;&amp;"EOF" ... EOF</literal>)
                </para>
                </section>

            </section> <!-- strings_and_interpolation -->

        </section> <!-- constants in Park -->

    </section> <!-- full_posix_conventions -->

</section>
</article>    <!-- End of the article -->
