<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<article>

    <section id="rindolf_spec"><title>Rindolf Specification Document</title>

<section id="version">
    <title>Version</title>

<para>
    0.3.5
</para>

</section>

<section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
This document is meant to describe the Rindolf programming language which
is a dialect of Perl. It describes the main changes between it and Perl
version 5.6.x.


</para>

<para>
Good knowledge of Perl is assumed.


</para>

</section> <!-- /introduction -->

<section id="author"><title>Author</title>

<para>
Shlomi Fish
</para>

<para>
E-mail: shlomif@shlomifish.org
</para>

<para>
    Homepage: <ulink url="http://www.shlomifish.org/">http://www.shlomifish.org/</ulink>
</para>

</section> <!-- /author -->

<section id="philosophy"><title>Philosophy</title>

<para>
The purpose of this section is to explain the motivation behind Rindolf,
what it is meant to accomplish, and what not. This section should be
consulted before one wishes to add new functionality to Rindolf, in order
to see if it corresponds with the philosophy.
</para>

<section id="philosophy_assumptions">
    <title>The Assumptions behind Rindolf</title>
    <para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Perl is a <emphasis>family</emphasis> of programming
                    languages.
                </para>
            </listitem>


            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Perl 5 is a good language.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Perl 5 is not good enough for some purposes.
                </para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Perl 6, by not being backward compatible, does not provide
                    a real answer to the Perl 5 deficiencies.
                </para>
            </listitem>


            <listitem>
                <para>
                    Rindolf aims to be an improved dialect of Perl compatible
                    to Perl 5.
                </para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>


</section>

<section id="philosophy_explanation"><title>Explanation

</title>
    <para>
        OK, here's the deal: if Perl 6 would have better designed, less bloated
        with superfluous features, and backward-compatible with Perl 5, I would
        not have started Rindolf. In fact, I consider Rindolf an anti-thesis
        to Perl 6. Thus, don't wonder if I criticize Perl 6 a lot, because
        it is the reason for starting Rindolf in the first place.
    </para>

    <para>
        Perl 5 is a good language. Yet, it is facing a problem: competition.
        Perl faces competition from Python, PHP and to lesser extent Ruby, Tcl
        and other less dominant languages vowing for the so-called "scripting
        languages category". There's nothing wrong with this competition, and
        if someone is content programming in another language, there's no
        reason to tell him to use Perl instead. Still, it would not be good
        if Perl 5 lost ground due to the fact that it lacked features,
        which other languages possessed in a straightforward manner.
    </para>

    <para>
        Now, Perl 6 is the wrong solution for the problem. As Perl 5 served
        as a handy scripting, glue and integration language in the past years,
        which saw an explosion of the Internet, of Linux, and of computing
        in general, there are now millions of lines of Perl 5 code written by
        hundreds of thousands of programmers. (perhaps even milliards LOCs
        written by millions of programmers - it's hard for me to approximate).
        These pieces of code do their job, work very nicely and are sometimes
        tweaked and modified as time goes by.
    </para>

    <para>
        What is present in CPAN is just the tip of the iceberg. We can expect
        many
        modules in CPAN to have ad-hoc code that does the same job in many
        other places around the world. (I know I wrote a lot of code, that I
        later found out that there is a CPAN module that does exactly that).
        Furthermore, and equally importantly we can expect that there are now
        millions of Perl 5 programmers of varying skill and knowledge who
        constantly maintain such code or write new one for their own purposes.
    </para>

    <para>
        Now, here comes a rhetorical question: exactly how are all of them
        going to convert to Perl 6, which is incredibly different and not
        compatible with Perl 5?
    </para>

    <para>
        The answer is they are not going to. They are going to stick to
        Perl 5. Converters, you say? They are not going to work for several
        reasons. First of all, the programmers themselves are used to Perl 5.
        As we all know, everyone has his own Perl 5 style which is different
        than others.
        <footnote id="cross_river_twice">
            <para>And it is possible that a programmer writing the same script twice will not write the same script!</para>
        </footnote>
        Teaching them all Perl 6 is a recipe for failure. Secondly, a converter
        will probably convert your code to something crude and hard to manage.
        (if it will convert it correctly at all - eval "" anyone?). Lastly,
        people will be very reluctant to use the converter, if the code is
        already working in Perl 5. "It's working - don't touch". Perl 5 is
        probably going to be around for a while, so why bother converting a
        perfectly good code to the incompatible, new-fangled Perl 6?
    </para>

    <para>
        And that's where Rindolf kicks in. Rindolf is a Perl dialect that
        is fully backwards compatible with Perl 5, yet offers some features
        not present there. Running "rindolf test.pl" will 99% of the time
        yield the same results as running "perl test.pl". A person can take
        a code written for perl5, use it as is with Rindolf, and gradually
        add Rindolf-specific features should he wish to.
    </para>

    <para>
        Rindolf maintains backwards-compatiblity because Perl 5 is good
        enough as a basis for a language. More importantly, it is a language
        that is in wide use today, and people depend on.
    </para>

</section>

<section id="philosophy_perl4">
    <title>Analogy with the Perl 4/Perl 5 Conversion</title>
    <para>
        A few years ago, Larry Wall decided to dump Perl 4 for good and to
        create Perl 5, which was not backward compatible. Right now, the
        lack of backwards compatibility in Perl 6 is rationalized on similar
        notes. The situation, however, is completely different.
    </para>
    <para>
        Perl 4 was a system and scripting language that still originated from
        the same Perl 1 codebase. It did not have half the features that Perl 5
        has, and it was very hard to write maintainable code in it. I've seen
        Perl 4-like code written in Perl 5, and it was not a pretty sight.
        (I ended up Perl5-ing it). Perl 4 was an ad-hoc language used by a
        (relatively to nowadays small) number of UNIX sys-admins and users
        and was not much more than an awk with an attitude.
    </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, Perl 4 code could have been converted with some effort
        to Perl 5. Perl 5, in fact, still includes some operators only for
        backwards compatibility to Perl 4.
    </para>
    <para>
        The situation today is very different. Perl 5 is widely deployed and
        used by many more users around the world. It is not only used for system
        scripts, but for automating web processes (in thousands of sites used
        by millions of online users), for complex text processing, database
        access, GUI programming (take the Mandrake system utilities and
        installer for example), games (Frozen-Bubble is a notable example),
        numerical processing (PerlDL) and almost everything else under the Sun
        that does not require very fast low-level processing.
    </para>
    <para>
        Furthermore, it is very usable and supports most of the modern
        programming paradigms very well: Object-Oriented Programming,
        Functional Programming, Exceptions, text-processing, garbage collection,
        nested data structures, arbitrarily-sized data, etc. I'm not saying
        it's a perfect language, but inventing something entirely different,
        just to solve its defincies is sure to make many users (if not most)
        unhappy.
    </para>
    <para>
        Now is the point for incremental renovation. Don't throw everything
        away. Start with what you have and build on there, without breaking
        everything. That's exactly what Rindolf aims to be.
    </para>
</section>
<section id="philosophy_cpp">
    <title>Analogy with C++ and ANSI C</title>
    <para>
        The analogy between Rindolf and Perl 5 and C++ and ANSI C is naturally
        something that needs to be addressed. C++ has seen wide use in the
        industry, while has almost been completely rejected by the open-source
        community who sticked to the bare ISO C 89'. Even some software houses
        maintain ANSI C codebases of various sizes, which they do not indeed to
        convert to C++. Is Rindolf going to have the same fate?
    </para>
    <para>
        The answer is that it makes no different this way or another. I don't
        mind people sticking to the bare Perl 5 subset because Perl 5 is fine
        as it is. In fact, considering the Parrot architecture, I may write
        the Rindolf compiler in Perl 5 and keep it in Perl 5. (assuming rindolf
        will be based on Parrot). I believe that C++ could have had much
        more success, if it supported a saner subset of functionality, and did
        not push the standard beyond the limits of functionality, that takes
        compilers a lot of time to support properly.
    </para>
    <para>
        Single-inheritance is useful (it is nicer than the Gtk+-style
        implementation in software), as are templates, ,operator
        overloading and friend functions. But at the moment, Standard C++ has
        become a completely different language than ANSI C, which is still
        backwards compatible. Mozilla, for instance, restricts itself to
        only a very small subset of the functionality to maintain
        compatibility with different broken compilers. (I also know someone
        who used friend classes or functions in his code, which worked well
        in gcc, and later broken in a different Solaris proprietary compiler)
    </para>
    <para>
        Rindolf will still essentially be Perl 5-like with a Perl 5 feel
        and behaviour. Moreoever, C++ has proved of some use to many projects,
        and is still commonly used. As much as there is a hype about Java and
        .NET, they are not compatible with ANSI C, and so aren't actually
        a replacement for C++.
        <footnote id="mikmod_for_java">
            <para>
            I did in fact
            convert an entire ANSI C codebase (MikMod) to Java through several
            stages of C++. This took a lot of time, and the resultant code
            was completely not compatible with the Java conventions. If I had
            to make MikMod play nice with C++, all I needed were a few
            extern "C" declarations.
        </para>
        </footnote>

            If Perl 5 is ANSI C, then Perl 6 is going
        to be something like Java. Rindolf will be C++, and the analogy is
        perfectly fine.
    </para>
</section>

<section id="philosophy_competition">
    <title>How to handle the Competition?</title>
    <para>
        When one is facing a competition, one has to admit it, to understand
        it is a good thing, but also to try not to lose ground. Many times
        two competitors each gain new users. Many times users are gained by
        one on the expense of the other. At the moment, Perl faces competition
        from Python, Ruby, Tcl, O'Caml and some other minor players. Our most
        serious competitor is Python.
    </para>
    <para>
        Now if you ask a common programmer who knows Perl and Python well
        enough what he thinks of both languages there are several possible
        answers. One is "I <emphasis>love</emphasis> perl and despise
        everything that is Python." (I fall into this camp) One is "Python
        rocks, while Perl is a hideous, ugly inconsistent language". (I know
        some people who think that way). And another common one is "Perl is
        OK. Python is OK. Perl is good for some things, python for others.
        I like them both". A less common one is "They are both stupid. C++/
        Java/LISP is the ultimate language!".
    </para>
    <para>
        Now it's hard to tell which person will tell you which. It depends on
        the character of the Person, what he was used to before, and many other
        factors. My mother language was BASIC, and so I found Perl highly
        attractive. Later on when I learned other paradigms (The SICP stuff,
        Lambda Calculus, Object Oriented Programming, FP, nested data
        structures, etc.) I could easily find them in Perl 5. But then there
        may be other BASIC hackers who would prefer Python or Ruby.
    </para>
    <para>
        There are dog people who prefer Perl, and there are dog people who
        prefer Python. There are cat people who prefer Perl (like me), and there
        are cat people who prefer Python. Now, one can notice that the fact that
        Perl resembles a natural language, and it is possible to write with
        it in various styles (even mixing several styles in one program) make
        it highly attractive to people who like think about
        <emphasis>how they are going to write the code</emphasis>, and translate
        it naturally into code. People who like a strict syntax and conventions,
        an "everything is an object" concept, lack of "inelegant" features, and
        the "There's One Way to Do it" dogma prefer Python. Some people accept
        both opposing camps and like both languages
    </para>
    <para>
        Many of the members of the Python camp are loud, keep professing the
        supposed advantages of its language, how maintainable the code can
        become, and how everyone is capable of understanding it. While Python
        has many features Perl does not yet have, it also does not have many
        others (here documents, labeled loops with breaking and continuing, a
        continue block, the use strict pragma and so forth). It also overloads
        every operator to many things: + can be used for both adding numbers,
        concatenating strings and concatenating arrays, three uses that are
        three different operators in Perl. The Perl people on the other hand
        take the "if you like programming in Python/C/C++/Java/Ruby/whatever,
        then hack on and stay cool".
    </para>
    <para>
        I have already met two relative very young newbies whom I told
        that they should start with learning Perl, and they said "Perl? Why
        not Python?" Apparently, some people are under the impression that
        Perl is an inferior language to Python. It's very easy to get it. Eric
        Raymond recommends in the <ulink url="http://www.tuxedo.org/~esr/faqs/hacker-howto.html">How to become a Hacker</ulink> HOWTO to start with learning
        Python and then learn C/C++, Perl, LISP, Shell and Java. (and
        afterwards become familiar with other languages that are of lesser
        significance to the world). I would recommend someone to start with
        Perl instead, but this is a difference of opinions between me and
        Raymond, which is not productive to delve on. (he took the time to
        write the HOWTO and so he gets to endorse his paritcular favourite)
    </para>
    <para>
        My point in making Rindolf is to make sure it has most of the important
        features Python (and similar languages like Ruby, Tcl or Haskell) has
        and Perl does not. I'd hate to lose ground because someone tried to
        do something in Perl and did not. However, as opposed to Perl 5, I'm
        not going to be concerned with Java (enough to make the arrow operator
        a "."), C++ (which supports Object Oriented Programming roughly as
        much as COBOL supports Functional Programming), C#, Visual Basic,
        Smalltalk or any language that is nowhere near Perl and does not
        compete for the same niche.
    </para>
    <para>
        The Perl niche is high-level languages
        optimized for writing a lot of code quickly, commonly referred to as
        "scripting languages". These are the languages that most people like
        for their day to day hacking, that can be used as subtitute for shell
        scripts (like I did when I first worked as a web-technician on UNIX),
        and can be used for GUI programming, numerical programming (with some
        extensions), simple games, text processing (naturally), web scripting,
        automating system tasks, and almost anything where you can afford to
        spend some overhead and don't need every single CPU cycle. Perl 6 from
        my impression aims to feel the niche for every possible use under the
        sun. But we cannot invent a language that will be good for anything,
        just as we cannot invent such a screw-driver.
    </para>
</section>

</section> <!-- /philosophy -->
<section id="oop_features">
    <title>Object Oriented Programming Features</title>

    <section id="package_level_namespaces">
        <title>Package Level Namespace</title>
        <para>
            Rindolf will support the <symbol>class MyClass { ... }</symbol>
            construct to designate package and file level namespaces. Its
            advantage over <symbol>package</symbol> would be that it can be
            nested:
        </para>
        <para>
<screen>
class Hello {
    class Good {
        sub my_func
        {
            print "my_func is called!\n";
        }
    };
    sub another_func
    {
        print "another_func is called!\n";
    }
};

Hello::Good::my_func();
Hello::another_func();
#
# prints:
# my_func is called!
# another_func is called!
</screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This should make it more convenient that specificying
            <literal>package Hello;</literal> and
            <literal>package Hello::Good;</literal> and so forth.
        </para>
        <para>
            Generally such classes are considered lightweight namespaces.
            They are visible to an outside package, however, may override
            other "global" packages. Moreover, an external package will first
            look for global packages before them.
        </para>
    </section> <!-- Package Level Namespaces -->
    <section id="classes_as_first_order_objects">
        <title>Classes as First Order Objects</title>
        <para>
            In similar to the <literal>sub { ... }</literal> syntax
            it would be possible to do a
            <literal>$myclass = class { ... }</literal>, construct and get
            a reusable class as a scalar. (=first order object). In Perl 5,
            namespaces are global and cannot be created on the fly without
            some namespace collision prevention Voodoo. In Rindolf, such
            classes can simply be assigned to variable.
            (<literal>bless</literal> and similar operators will accept such
            classes as their second argument):
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>
my $myclass = class {
    sub new {
        my $class = shift;
        my $self = {};
        bless($self, $class);
        #
        $self->{'counter'} = 10;
        pt_return $self;
    }
    sub decrement
    {
        my $self = shift;
        sleep(1);
        my $val = --$self->{'counter'};
        print "$val\n";
        if ($val == 0)
        {
            die "Take off!";
        }
    }
};

my $countdown = $myclass->new();
for(;;)
{
    $countdown->decrement();
}
            </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            This class references will also be accepted by @ISA and all other
            operators requiring class names.
        </para>
    </section> <!-- Classes as First Order Objects -->
    <section id="expand_and_extend">
        <title><literal>expand</literal> and <literal>extend</literal></title>
        <para>
            Rindolf will provide two operators named <literal>expand</literal>
            and <literal>extend</literal> that would enable manipulating such
            namespaces efficiently.
        </para>
        <para>
            <literal>expand</literal> takes an entire class and dumps a cope of
            all of its package-scope symbols into the current namespace.
            <literal>extend</literal> takes a class reference and extends with
            another class. Together they can be used to manipulate classes.
        </para>
        <para>
            Here is a similar example with some <literal>expand</literal>
            and <literal>extend</literal> magic:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>
my $class1 = class {
    sub hello {
        my $you = shift;
        print "Hello $you!\n";
    }
};

my $class2 = class {
    sub goodbye {
        my $you = shift;
        print "Goodbye!\n";
    }
};

class You {
    expand($class1);
    expand($class2);
    sub message
    {
        my $you = shift;
        my $message = shift;
        hello($you);
        print "$message\n";
        goodbye($you);
    }
};

my $object_class = class {
    sub new
    {
        my $class = shift;
        my $name = shift;
        my $self = {};
        bless($self, $class);
        $self->{'name'} = $name;
        pt_return $self;
    }
    sub msg
    {
        my $self = shift;
        my $message = shift;

        pt_return message($self->{'name'}, $msg);
    }
};

extend $object_class, typeref{CLASS}{YOU};

my $person = $object_class->new("Muli");
$person->msg("Time to track system calls!");
            </screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Note the <literal>typeref</literal> operator which is a generic
            way of casting references, that is introduced due to the fact
            that we are running out of special characters in the keyboard
            (:-)). It will be available for hashes, arrays and others
            language primitives.
        </para>
    </section> <!-- Classes as first order objects -->
    <section id="defining_new_operators">
        <title>Defining New Operators</title>
        <para>
            In Rindolf it would be possible to define completely new operator
            and modify the syntax and grammar of the language on the fly. Thus,
            the PerlDL guys can easily define the more Matlab like
            <literal>.*</literal> and <literal>.*=</literal> instead of
            perl's <literal>*</literal> and dump <literal>x</literal> in
            favour of <literal>*</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
            At the moment perl5 uses lex and yacc which I am almost certain
            will not allow to define new operators. However, I believe such
            change is something that I've always missed in C++ and Perl, and
            I really like about Haskell. So, it is going to be implemented.
        </para>
    </section> <!-- Defining New Operators-->

</section> <!-- OOP Features -->

<section id="new_additions">
    <title>New Additions to the language</title>
    <section id="fundamental_io_subsystem">
        <title>A Fundamental I/O Subsystem</title>
        <para>
            perl 5 depends on typeglobs to initialize filehandles, and on
            <literal>local</literal> to localize them. However, this does not
            fall very nicely with Perl's lexical scoping, which makes it
            necessary to use such modules as <literal>FileHandle</literal>
            which behave more lexically, but may not be well-supported.
        </para>
        <para>
            Rindolf will have a fundamental I/O subsystem which I dub
            <literal>aFile_*</literal> after its function names. Generally,
            this subsystem is not meant to be used directly (albeit it can be)
            and will be available for those writing low-level file
            manipulation APIs.
        </para>
        <para>
            This filesystem will have support for most basic facilities (File
            I/O, sockets, pipes, ioctl's and fcntl's, asyncrounous I/O, etc)
            and should be flexible enough. Typeglobs will use it, as will all
            other modules (directly or indiretly) and it will behave in a
            completely Perl 5-ish manner.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="better_hash">
        <title>A Better Hash Construct</title>
        <para>
            Rindolf will supply an internally coded hash that will support most
            of the hash extensions (such as <literal>StrictHash</literal>,
            <literal>Tie::RefHash</literal>). I believe Perl 5 already has
            a pragma that can auto-magically initialize any hash declared with
            <literal>my</literal> with a tie statement, so this hash can be
            made to be used by default.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section id="proper_tail_recursion">
        <title>Proper Tail Recursion</title>
        <para>
            The new statement <literal>pt_pt_return</literal> (short for
            "point pt_return") will behave in a similar manner to
            <literal>pt_return</literal> only will be proper tail recursive if
            possible.
        </para>
        <para>
            The new statement <literal>line_pt_return</literal> will always be
            non-proper tail recursive. A pragrma
            <literal>use Recursion</literal> will exist that will enable to
            decide how a plain <literal>pt_return</literal> will behave, and
            should be very flexible in doing that.
        </para>
        <para>
            I give a choice between both types of tail recursion because
            proper tail recursion is faster and consumes O(1) memory while
            non proper tail recursion is easier to debug.
        </para>
        <section id="proper_tail_recursion_example">
            <title>Examples</title>
            <para>
                Here's an example using <literal>pt_return</literal>:
            </para>
            <para>
                <screen>
sub gcd
{
    my ($a,$b) = @_;
    if ($b > $a)
    {
        pt_return gcd($b,$a);
    }
    if ($b == 0)
    {
        return $a;
    }
    else
    {
        pt_return gcd($b, $a % $b);
    }
}

print gcd(@ARGV[0 .. 1]), "\n";
                </screen>
            </para>
            <para>
                Here's the same example, using the <literal>Recursion</literal>
                module:
            </para>
            <para>
                <screen>
#!/usr/bin/perl -w

use Recursion;

BEGIN
{
    Recursion::set_default('pt');
}

sub gcd
{
    my ($a,$b) = @_;
    if ($b > $a)
    {
        return gcd($b,$a);
    }
    if ($b == 0)
    {
        return $a;
    }
    else
    {
        return gcd($b, $a % $b);
    }
}

print gcd(@ARGV[0 .. 1]), "\n";
                </screen>
            </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="regex_data_structure">
        <title>Nested Variable to Hold the Regex Search Results</title>
        <para>
            <!-- TODO: Add -->
            At the moment, querying the results of a regular expression pattern
            match using the <literal>$0, $1, $2</literal> variables leaves
            a lot to be desired. As another way of doing things, Rindolf will
            provide a <literal>$^RR</literal> variable which would be a Perl
            5 data-structure that is nested to a necessary depth to contain
            the results of the pattern and sub-pattern matches.
        </para>
        <para>
            Here's an example:
        </para>
        <para>
            <screen>
#!/usr/bin/perl

use string;

my $string = "[(5,6), (7,3), (8,9)], [(5,7), (2,10)], [(100,92),(14,8)]";

# Define a pattern for (x,y)
my $pt_pattern = "\s*\(\s*(\d+)\s*,\s*(\d+)\s*\)\s*";
# Define a patern for an array of points [pt1,pt2,pt3,pt4]
my $array_pattern = "\[(?:${pt_pattern}\s*,)*${pt_pattern}\]";
# Define a pattern for an array of arrays of points arr1,arr2,arr3
my $whole_pattern = "(?:${array_pattern}\s*,)*${array_pattern}"
$string =~ /$whole_pattern/;

my $results = $^RR;

print "a[0][2].x = ", $results->[0]->[2]->[0], "\n"; # prints 8
print "a[1][1].y = ", $results->[1]->[1]->[1], "\n"; # prints 10
            </screen>
        </para>
    </section>
</section> <!-- New Additions to the Language -->
<section id="lisp_like_features">
    <title>LISP-like Features</title>
    <section id="reusable_vms">
        <title>Re-usable Virtual Machines Instances</title>
        <para>

        </para>
    </section> <!-- Re-usable Virtual Machines Instances -->
</section><!-- LISP-like Features -->
</section>


</article>    <!-- End of the book -->
