<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="docbook-css/driver.css" type="text/css"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" 
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>

<article id="index">
    <articleinfo>
        <title>Dealing with Hypomanias</title>
        <authorgroup>
            <author>
                <firstname>Shlomi</firstname>
                <surname>Fish</surname>
                <affiliation>
                    <address>
                        <email>shlomif@iglu.org.il</email>
                    </address>
                </affiliation>
            </author>
         </authorgroup>
         <copyright>
             <year>2008</year>
            <holder>Shlomi Fish</holder>
        </copyright>
      <legalnotice>
            <para>
<!--Creative Commons License-->
This work is licensed under the <ulink url="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/">Creative Commons Attribution 2.5 License</ulink> (or at your option a greater version of it).
		<!--/Creative Commons License--><!-- <rdf:RDF xmlns="http://web.resource.org/cc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
		<Work rdf:about="">
			<license rdf:resource="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/" />
	<dc:title>The Case for File Swapping</dc:title>
	<dc:date>2005</dc:date>
	<dc:description>An essay that explains why Internet File Swapping (using Peer-to-Peer networks, etc.) is not only moral and ethical, but also should be legal, and cannot be banned. Discusses other issues.</dc:description>
	<dc:creator><Agent><dc:title>Shlomi Fish</dc:title></Agent></dc:creator>
	<dc:rights><Agent><dc:title>Shlomi Fish</dc:title></Agent></dc:rights>
	<dc:type rdf:resource="http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/Text" />
		</Work>
		<License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Reproduction"/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Distribution"/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Notice"/><requires rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/Attribution"/><permits rdf:resource="http://web.resource.org/cc/DerivativeWorks"/></License></rdf:RDF> -->                
            </para>
        </legalnotice>
        <abstract>
            <para>
                I'll discuss some of my experience as a person with Bipolar
                Disorder (or Mania-Depressia), and how I deal with the various
                periods of "hypomania": periods of strong excitement and 
                feelings of self-grandioisity.
            </para> 
        </abstract>

        <revhistory>
            <revision>
                <revnumber>5389</revnumber>
                <date>30 May 2008</date>
                <authorinitials>shlomif</authorinitials>
                <revremark>
                    Forked the template from a previous work and working on 
                    it.
                </revremark>
            </revision>
        </revhistory>
    </articleinfo>

<section id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <!-- TODO : Rephrase -->

    <para>
        The topic in question are 
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypomania">Hypomanias</ulink>,
        which while containing the word "mania" are actually below mania, and 
        the person is still in control to some extent, and, with some 
        awareness, may realise he's in a bad condition.
    </para>

    <para>
        Hypomanias are a variation on 
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_depression">Clinical 
            Depressions</ulink>. The latter are not everyday "I am depressed." 
        depressions, but rather a feeling that one is bad, and being
        consumed with guilt, with a tendency of being less communicative and 
        less able to perform one's responsibilities.
    </para>
    
    <para>
        I probably have <ulink 
            url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bipolar_disorder">Mania-Depressia</ulink> (or "Bipolar disorder") because I had a 
        single "Great Mania" and a few smaller manias, and have frequent 
        Hypomanias, and have been clinically depressed or clinically anxious 
        at the time. So I'm writing about this from experience.
    </para>

</section>

<section id="symptoms">
    <title>Symptoms</title>
    <section id="symptoms-of-depression">
        <title>Symptoms of Depression</title>
        <para>
            Quoting from <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clinical_depression">the 
                Wikipedia</ulink>, the symptoms of depression are:
        </para>

        <blockquote>
            <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Persistent sad, anxious or "empty" mood 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Loss of appetite and/or weight loss or conversely overeating and weight gain 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Insomnia, early morning awakening, or oversleeping 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Restlessness or irritability
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Psychomotor agitation or psychomotor retardation
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Feelings of worthlessness, inappropriate guilt, helplessness
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Feelings of hopelessness, pessimism 
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Difficulty thinking, concentrating, remembering or making decisions
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Thoughts of [[death]] or suicide or attempts at suicide
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Loss of interest or pleasure in hobbies and activities that were once enjoyed
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Withdrawal from social situations, family and friends
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Decreased energy, fatigue, feeling "slowed down" or sluggish
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Persistent physical symptoms that do not respond to treatment, such as [[headache]]s, [[digestion|digestive]] problems, and [[chronic pain]]
                    </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>
                        Decrease/Feeling in motor-speed (time seems to slow down)
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </blockquote>

        <para>
            These are mostly the external symptoms. While the exact thoughts
            differ from person to person, here is how I felt:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I felt I was bad and evil. That I was a bad person, having a 
                    bad influence on the world, and that "God hated me".
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    I felt this was my true state, and that my happy, capable, 
                    intelligent and active state was due to "a pact with the 
                    devil" or something along these lines.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para>I found that the thoughts haunted me, that I couldn't really sleep, and
was afraid of thinking.</para></listitem>


<listitem><para>I believed the entire world was bad and kept perceiving everything as bad.</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>I had trouble communicating with others, and was afraid to tell them how
I felt.</para></listitem>

<listitem>
    <para>
I found it harder to do things that I normally find easy to do. For example,
I spent hours on end solving a single math problem. I kept convincing myself
that it should be easy which made me feel much worse.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem>
    <para>
I was consumed and overwhelmed with guilt. I felt guilty for many things
that I perceived as wrong.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

    </section>
    <section id="symptoms-of-hypomanias">
        <title>Symptoms of Hypomanias</title>
        <para>
            In regards to hypomanias, Wikipedia <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hypomania">gives the following symptoms</ulink>:
        </para>

        <itemizedlist>
<listitem>
    <para>
        Pressured speech; rapid talking
    </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>
        Inflated self-esteem or grandiosity;
    </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>
        Decreased need for sleep;
    </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>
        Flight of ideas or the subjective experience that thoughts are racing; 
    </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>
        Easy distractibility and attention-deficit (superficially similar to attention deficit hyperactivity disorder);
    </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>
        Increase in psychomotor agitation; and
    </para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
    <para>
        Steep involvement in pleasurable activities that may have a high potential for negative psycho-social or physical consequences.
    </para>
</listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
            It's a pretty good description of me when I'm hypomanic.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
<section id="depressed-people-i-know">
    <title>People I Know who Suffer from Depressions</title>
    <para>
        Many people (mostly computer developers) I've talked with admitted to 
        have been clinically depressed:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>
                One of my best friends has admitted that she used to have many 
                depressions. Whenever I met her in real life, or talked with 
                her (on the phone, on instant messaging, etc) she seemed very 
                cheerful, fun loving, intelligent, and rational.
            </para>

            <para> She claimed that when she is depressed she tends not to
                communicate a lot and also cannot achieve too much at work,
                which she said only makes her feel worse. I can relate to both
                of these, as I recall that that was the case for me on both
                accounts when I was depressed.  </para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

            <para> I talked with a programmer, well into his 50's (and still
                active) who admitted to having got into depressions several
                times in the past. He again seemed normal (if somewhat
                eccentric to me).  </para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

            <para> One time on irc.oftc.net someone joined and spoke in
                l33t-speak, asking how he can be a "haxor". People thought he
                was a troll, but I ended up PMing him and it turned out he was
                depressed. I spent the afternoon trying to help him.
                Eventually, at evening, he claimed that he was feeling better
                and parted. (It is known that often depressed individuals feel
                better in the evening and at night.) </para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

            <para>
                A fellow programmer I talked with admitted to having got into 
                depressions in the past, and that she tried to function 
                despite that.
            </para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

            <para>
                A fellow Perl monger I talked with said that he sometimes 
                exhibited some of the symptoms of hypomania. He seemed 
                very hyperactive to me, so I wasn't really surprised, but it 
                may also be plain excitement and not a medical condition.
            </para>

        </listitem>
        
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
        <ulink url="http://www.mental-health-today.com/bp/famous_people.htm">A 
            list of some famous people who had Mania-Depressia can be
            found at 
            http://www.mental-health-today.com/bp/famous_people.htm</ulink>.
        Bipolar disorder is relaively uncommon and many more people are 
        Unipolar and only have depressions and anxieties. Depressions and
        anxieties are considered the "common cold" of mental illnesses, and 
        are exhibited in a large amount of the populace.
    </para>

    <para>        
Someone told me that he read a study that said that roughly 50% of the
authors in the English language today have Mania-Depressia. I haven't been
able to find it online and would appreciate any references.
    </para>

</section>
<section id="dealing-with-clinical-depressions">
    <title>Dealing with Clinical Depressions</title>

    <para>
There is a lot of mis-information and dis-information about depressions in
the public. When I was depressed and hypomanic as a teenager I didn't know
how to call these "conditions", or how to effectively deal with them. If,
after reading the description on the Wikipedia, you feel that you have been
depressed in the past, read on.
</para>

<para>
The best advice I can give on dealing with clinical depressions (and possibly
also as a preventitive measure or just to understand what people think) is
to buy <ulink url="http://www.amazon.com/Feeling-Good-Therapy-Revised-Updated/dp/0380810336">the excellent book "Feeling Good"</ulink>.
</para>

<para>
    It is a self-help guide for <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_behavioral_therapy">cognitive-behavioural therapy</ulink>, that was
originally written in English and was recommended to me by my therapist.
Just reading it helped me understand the source of my hypomanias, and I found
the exercises recommended there to be helpful as well.
</para>

<para>
Note that if you are depressed, (and much more if you're feeling suicidal),
you need to consult a cognitive-behavioural therapist for a session, as
soon as possible. I am not a mental health professional and am not qualified 
to give professional therapy, and this essay is not a substitute for it.
</para>

</section>

<section id="few-facts-to-realise">
    <title>A Few Facts that Should Be Realised</title>
    <section id="mentally-ill-is-not-eccentric">
        <title>Mentally Ill is not Eccentric</title>

        <para>
            When people say that someone is "crazy", "insane", "out of his 
            mind" etc. they usually mean that he or she is eccentric or 
            behaving irrationaly, not that they are mentally unsound. I know 
            and have heard about many people who are eccentric or very 
            eccentric and yet are perfectly sane, and lead perfectly happy 
            lives.
        </para>

        <para>
            There's a difference between conformism or "being normal" and 
            mental health. 
        </para>

    </section>
</section>

</article>    <!-- End of the article -->
